<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Startups | minimaxir]]></title>
  <link href="minimaxir.com//startups/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-12T19:58:33-07:00</updated>
  <id>minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let Myspace's Justin Timberlake Bring Sexy To The Entire Internet]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2013/01/sexy-will-haunt-your-dreams/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-15T21:36:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2013/01/sexy-will-haunt-your-dreams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>TechCrunch writer Sarah Perez recently wrote <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/15/lost-on-new-myspace-cant-escape-justin-send-help/">an incredibly hilarious article</a> about <a href="https://new.myspace.com/">Myspace</a>&rsquo;s recent redesign, and the&hellip;overemphasis of a certain former N'Sync band member. Justin Timberlake, the spearhead of Myspace&rsquo;s music-oriented redesign, stresses his clean-shaven image with a handsome yet somber black-and-white portrait that always seems to follow you where you go.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m OK with this. There are certainly far <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/03/ethics-self-promotion/"><em>worse</em></a> ways to promote a startup.</p>

<p>His moody yet charmful face adds a touch of class to any website. But why does he have to stay constrained to Myspace? Why not let Justin Timberlake dominate the world?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>No Such Thing As Too Much Sexy</h2>

<p>If you are reading this post on a desktop or laptop, you&rsquo;ll see a handsome fellow in the lower-right corner. This is Justin Timberlake of the Mickey Mouse Club. Say hi.</p>

<p>Using the power of the Stylish extension for Chrome and Firefox, Mr. Timberlake has already made his mark on many startups around the internet.</p>

<p><a href="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest2-e1358404534897.png"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest2-e1358404534897.png" alt="" /></a>
TechCrunch</p>

<p><a href="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest9-e1358404467980.png"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest9-e1358404467980.png" alt="" /></a>
Facebook</p>

<p><a href="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest8-e1358404790348.png"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest8-e1358404790348.png" alt="" /></a>
Twitter</p>

<p><a href="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest7-e1358404639594.png"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest7-e1358404639594.png" alt="" /></a>
Instagram</p>

<p><a href="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest5-e1358404610346.png"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest5-e1358404610346.png" alt="" /></a>
Dropbox</p>

<p><a href="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest4-e1358404660737.png"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest4-e1358404660737.png" alt="" /></a>
Imgur</p>

<p><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en"><img src="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en" alt="" /></a>
Google Search</p>

<p>To accomplish this magic, I use the Stylish browser extension, which can be used with either <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en">Chrome</a> or <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/stylish/">Firefox</a>. I have used Stylish <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/">before, with browser filters</a>, and it worked very well. If you want your own moody Justin, follow these steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Install the Stylish extension for your browser.</li>
<li>In the extension preferences, go to &ldquo;Managed Installed Styles&rdquo; and select &ldquo;Write New Style&rdquo;</li>
<li><p>Paste this CSS code in the &ldquo;Code&rdquo; textbox:</p>

<pre><code>body, ._li, .main {
background-image: url(http://i.imgur.com/UN5HE.png) !important;
background-position: right bottom !important;
background-repeat: no-repeat !important;
background-attachment: fixed !important;
}
</code></pre></li>
</ol>


<p>And you&rsquo;re done! Justin will appear pretty much everywhere. Yes, there are a lot of <em>!important</em> declarations, but Justin Timberlake is an important man.</p>

<p>In fact, by using the HTML snippet in this <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/display-justin-timberlake-sexiness">GitHub repository</a>, you can add Justin to your own site!</p>

<p>Feel free to narrow down the domains where Justin appears by using Stylish as necessary. Although, why would you do such a thing!?</p>

<h2>Taking Justin To The Next Level</h2>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/816440400_1965379.gif?resize=400%2C232" alt="816440400_1965379" /></p>

<p>Now that we can make Justin appear anywhere, let&rsquo;s put his power to good use. TechCrunch writer Alexia Tsostis recently made a post about the <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/16/were-bringing-techcrunch-back/">upcoming redesign of TechCrunch</a>, which, I admit, is long overdue.</p>

<p>In the post, Alexia spoils that the redesign will include lots of sparkles. And a picture of the Justin-man himself. Above is a mockup made by Chris Velazco, another TechCrunch writer, and it is indeed marvelous. (except for the lack of a comments section!)</p>

<p>But why wait for the redesign? We have Timberlake Technology. We can do it <em>now</em>.</p>

<p>Using the power of Stylish, I present to you, a sneak peek into TechCrunch&rsquo;s 2013 redesign.</p>

<p>I made a <em>few</em> stylistic additions as well. It&rsquo;s magic.</p>

<p>You can find a copy of the CSS I used to emulate this wonderful layout in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/techcrunch-1999">this GitHub repository</a>.</p>

<p>Will you let Timberlake enrich <em>your</em> life? He&rsquo;s waiting. In the lower-right corner of your screen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Auto-Save Images From Reddit To Computer Without Visiting The Site (Using IFTTT)]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T21:32:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>TL;DR: Use this <a href="https://ifttt.com/recipes/74285">IFTTT recipe</a>, and change the subreddit value in the parameter of the Feed URL as needed.</em></strong></p>

<p>In <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">a previous post</a>, I joked about a hypothetical social media strategy in which an automated script does Facebook brand management by stealing the top cute images from <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a> &ndash; an aggregator of trending topics and images &ndash;  and reposting them on the Facebook page, additionally adding a cute message encouraging users to LIKE, SHARE, and COMMENT!  We get easy social media fame for no monetary cost.</p>

<p>Out of curiosity, I wanted to see if it was feasible to create such a script. Both Reddit and Facebook indeed have APIs that make it easy. But then I have to set up a server to check Reddit periodically, ensure that no images are duplicated, etc., and that can take time to implement and ensure that it works correctly (<em>all</em> the images must be cute!). I looked into <a href="https://ifttt.com/">IFTTT</a>, a relatively new startup that talks between different popular web services to automate simple tasks, like posting to Twitter whenever you post to Facebook.</p>

<p>As it turns out, yes, this is possible, and you can also save the top images on Reddit to your computer via any cloud storage service without ever visiting the website too! Just use <a href="https://ifttt.com/recipes/74285">this IFTTT recipe</a>! There are a few interesting caveats, though&hellip;</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Really Simple Syndication is&hellip;Really Simple?</h2>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/redditrss2.png?resize=304%2C242" alt="redditrss2" /></p>

<p>IFTTT allows users to extract information from RSS feeds, which one might typically be used to read blogs and news articles. The RSS feed typically provides the title, author, date, and content of a post: the important things. However, RSS has more applications: it can distribute other data, such as weather and desktop wallpapers. IFTTT allows other apps to load image and audio files from an RSS feed, but only if the RSS feed link links to the content itself.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this won&rsquo;t work on Reddit by default, as its RSS feeds do not contain a direct link to the photo and instead link to the Reddit comments on the image. Image-based websites, such as <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/">BuzzFeed</a> and <a href="http://interfacelift.com/wallpaper/downloads/date/any/">InterfaceLift</a> also implement a similar system because they don&rsquo;t want their users just to use a script to download images and bypass the website and its lovely revenue-generating advertisements. Therefore, the RSS feed alone won&rsquo;t work with IFTTT.</p>

<p>During my research into my social media exploitation hypothesis, I found a <a href="http://blog.stevemould.com/rss-feed-reddit-stories-score-threshold/">blog post by Steve Mould</a> that provides a way to translate data from Reddit&rsquo;s JSON API to an RSS feed using a service called <a href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/">Yahoo Pipes</a>. This modified RSS feed, when given a subreddit and a score threshold, obtains the top Reddit posts in that subreddit above that karma threshold (upvotes &ndash; downvotes), and returns a feed item which contains direct link to the referenced URL.</p>

<p>Here is <a href="http://bit.ly/W1ypdf">my variation of his Reddit Pipe</a>. My script to process the API has a few changes (such as using Reddit&rsquo;s &ldquo;hot&rdquo; posts, instead of the top posts; hot posts update much more frequently). Testing it with r/aww and a threshold of 50 karma, I received 177 very cute pictures on my computer in a week.</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/redditcute.png?resize=625%2C382" alt="redditcute" /><br/>
From that Pipe, you can get the data in a RSS feed URL. Right-click and copy that feed URL into a IFTTT recipe as the source. For the action, use the <strong></strong> variable to retrieve the image URL.</p>

<h2>With Great Power Comes Great Cuteness</h2>

<p>Yes, you can save the Reddit images to your computer automatically using <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</a>. Or <a href="https://drive.google.com">Google Drive</a>. Or <a href="https://skydrive.live.com/">SkyDrive</a>. Or even get a cute email every hour!</p>

<p>Thanks to IFTTT, there are many other creative things you can do with the feed that you can include in a recipe:</p>

<ul>
<li>Auto-post the image to your Tumblr or WordPress blog. Easy cuteness, and you&rsquo;ll be the source!</li>
<li>Auto-curate the cute photos to your Facebook or Twitter account. All your friends will love you!</li>
<li>Get social media fame for no additional monetary cost by publishing the cute images to your Facebook Page, with an encouragement to LIKE SHARE and COMMENT! My original hypothesis was correct!</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/redditnega.png?resize=625%2C418" alt="redditnega" /></p>

<h2>Caveats</h2>

<p>One caveat in using Yahoo Pipes is that it is rate limited to 200 runs in a 10 minute interval, meaning that the IFTTT recipe provided will likely fail if more than 200 people use the feed. If that does happen, just clone my pipe, and use the RSS feed from the clone for your own personal recipe.</p>

<p>Also, there&rsquo;s no rate limiting on when recipes are triggered and images are posted/downloaded. You can trigger multiple images simultaneously, which may be considered spammy if you are posting to social media. In that case, increase the karma threshold to reduce the frequency of the postings and to maintain a high quality of the images.</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/redditifttt.png?resize=625%2C239" alt="redditifttt" /><br/>
Getting socially-vetted photos on your computer without any effort is a useful timesaver. A solution to a first world problem, perhaps, but it&rsquo;s the little things that count!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Do Many Tweets Begin With A Period?]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2013/01/prefixed-period/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-04T21:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2013/01/prefixed-period</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not a Twitter fanatic. Although I do have <a href="https://twitter.com/minimaxir">a Twitter account</a> with about 300 followers,  Facebook&rsquo;s Subscribe feature <a href="http://www.facebook.com/max.woolf">on my Facebook profile</a> has met my use case for publishing sarcastic quips and cool links for a broad audience over the internet. I mostly use my Twitter account to read tweets from tech columnists, yet I don&rsquo;t even comment on their tweets because <strong>tweets that are replies to someone are not visible in the home timeline of my followers</strong>. I can understand the intuition behind this behavior: Twitter conversations can contain a lot of low-content tweets, and Twitter doesn&rsquo;t want its users to be spammed.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve noticed that many tweets from actual Twitter fanatics begin with a prefixed period, such as <em>&ldquo;.@minimaxir wow funny joke!&rdquo; </em>and <em>&ldquo;.@minimaxir is a huge dork!&rdquo;</em>. I thought the dot was a typo, until I noticed many people also prefixing the period, seemingly randomly, in their own tweets. All of those tweets seemed like witty replies that begged for mass exposure, and so I eventually realized that <strong>beginning your reply Tweet with a period (.) allows it to be seen by all your followers. </strong>Otherwise, only the replyee will receive notification of the reply.</p>

<p>Having your reply tweets appear to your followers only if you begin them with a prefixed period is not intuitive at all. And this particular behavior and its workaround are not documented in <a href="https://support.twitter.com/groups/31-twitter-basics/topics/109-tweets-messages/articles/14023-what-are-replies-and-mentions">Twitter&rsquo;s help docs</a>. And replying to tweets is a core feature of Twitter. How many users would be able to deduce this behavior? How many brands, who rely on user engagement, are even aware of this behavior?</p>

<p>As it turns out, I was only partially correct. It&rsquo;s even <em>less</em> intuitive.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>XY = @(Z)</h2>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/twitter2.png?resize=513%2C181" alt="twitter2" /></p>

<p>I recently saw <a href="https://twitter.com/ScottyLabs/status/286921265514700801">a tweet</a> in my timeline that had a prefixed period, but clearly was not a reply to anyone. Confused, I pointed out that prefixed periods aren&rsquo;t necessary if the tweet is not a reply. <a href="https://twitter.com/amyquispe">Amy Quispe</a>, founder of ScottyLabs and a CS senior at Carnegie Mellon University with much more startup knowledge than myself, pointed out that I was wrong, and <strong>if the tweet begins with a @, it will not appear in your follower&rsquo;s timelines, regardless of whether it&rsquo;s a reply or a mention</strong>.</p>

<p>Anyone who tweets, for example, &ldquo;<em>@SHO_Dexter is my favorite television show! Season 7 was AWESOME!!!</em>&rdquo;, will likely not have that tweet seen by any of their followers. Therefore, it&rsquo;s incredibly easy, and incredibly likely, for that behavior to unintentionally trigger a false positive for spam. Again, would a person notice that one of his/her tweets is not being seen? It&rsquo;s bad for the user, and it&rsquo;s even bad for @SHO_Dexter, who misses out on the free advertising.</p>

<p>As it turns out, <em>that</em> <em>correction** was still only partially correct</em>, as there&rsquo;s one more important caveat:<strong> if a tweet by X begins a tweet with an @ mention of Y, and if Z is a follower of <em>both</em> X and Y, then Z will see the tweet. If the second condition is not true, then Z will not see the tweet.</strong></p>

<p>Twitter is apparently a course in deductive reasoning. To be fair, this caveat is clearly stated in the help docs, and this behavior makes sense in the context of mutual friends among users. Nevertheless, it&rsquo;s not intuitive at all, and it&rsquo;s mostly irrelevant: a prefixed period tweet reaches all of your followers, 100% of the time.</p>

<h2>The Pestilent Prefixed Period Problem</h2>

<p>Twitter users want maximum reach. Brands want maximum reach. Therefore, everyone will use the prefixed period for replies and mentions. Those who don&rsquo;t use prefixed periods on Twitter will be left behind in this cutthroat game of social media.</p>

<p>There are two problems with encouraging prefixed periods:</p>

<ol>
<li>It alienates newcomers to Twitter. Some online communities do have unwritten behaviors: <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a>, for example, invokes &ldquo;vote fuzzing&rdquo; on popular posts, which disguises the true amount of upvotes and downvotes on any particular post by adding fake upvotes/downvotes. You won&rsquo;t find that in any Reddit documentation, which leads to the frequent outbursts of &ldquo;WHO THE HELL WOULD DOWNVOTE THIS PUPPY?&rdquo; Quirks like these don&rsquo;t make communities exclusive: it makes them insular.</li>
<li><strong>It looks tacky and ugly</strong>. That&rsquo;s not a trivial complaint. Every @mention tweet looks like someone made a typo. I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s the brand image Twitter wants.</li>
</ol>


<p>How could Twitter address this? An option would be to adopt a system similar to Facebook&rsquo;s <em>ad hoc</em> post visibility settings, and allow users to set the reach of an individual tweet as necessary. Another option is to have an <em>All your replies and @mentions are shown to all your followers</em> account option that is opt-in, and let the user&rsquo;s followers determine whether the content is spam.</p>

<p>Twitter, with an impending IPO, needs to help potential newcomers out in any way possible. Eliminating the need for prefixed periods is a great start to increasing accessibility.</p>

<p><em>PS: I am not a huge dork.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Startup Promo Video Using... PowerPoint?]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-29T21:28:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I noticed deep in the documentation for PowerPoint 2010 that it <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/powerpoint-help/turn-your-presentation-into-a-video-HA010336763.aspx">supports video output</a> for presentations. Like a good nerd, I experimented to see what it could actually do. My first test of the functionality was a humor video about pitching a <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">hypothetical startup named NegaCycl</a>, complete with animation and narration, which I trashed and eventually retooled because I&rsquo;m bad at verbal comedic delivery. Interestingly, the output video was a 1:1 comparison to what was displayed on my own computer screen during the presentation. Naturally, I decided to test it even harder.</p>

<p>What I have here is another hypothetical, non-real startup named Filtrzzz (based on a <a href="http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10151356495205450&amp;set=a.432190050449.225968.582270449&amp;type=1">popular Facebook post</a> I made), animated and rendered using PowerPoint, with more complicated objects such as embedded audio and video, and an attempt to sync the presentation timing with the audio for dramatic effect. Plus sarcastic humor, of course.</p>

<p>PowerPoint video creation is feasible if you don&rsquo;t have or can&rsquo;t afford dedicated video software and need a promo video in a pinch, as may be the case with an actual startup.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/filtrzzz-ppt.png?resize=625%2C288" alt="filtrzzz ppt" /></p>

<p>The Filtrzzz video relies heavily on slide transitions (the &ldquo;zoom&rdquo; effects at the beginning), text animations (the fade in/fade out on the text at the end), and embedding of media (the background song and the product demos), all of which are very easy to implement, although as with any video, a little trial-and-error is necessary to get a good &ldquo;feel&rdquo; for effect duration, effect intensity, etc.</p>

<p>PowerPoint has the native ability to record timings (i.e. when to progress to the next slide/animation) and voice narrations on a per-slide basis in the Slide Show tab. You can either record the timings while running through a presentation normally (good for maintaining a consistent pace through animations), or record <em>ad hoc</em> per slide (good for voice narration, which is independent from other slides). If timings and narrations are present, when the presentation runs, it will use those timings and play in auto-pilot. When the presentation is exported as a video, it will follow these timings and include the spoken narrations.</p>

<p>The maximum quality output for video through PowerPoint is 720p WMV, which is sufficient for a startup video since users likely are watching the video YouTube-embedded in a webpage. For comparison, I video-captured the presentation using Camtasia at 1080p and rendered the final video as a high-bit rate MP4: the visual quality between the two versions is indistinguishable at non-full screen resolutions. (when watching a video in 1080p at small sizes, the quality is actually even worse!)</p>

<p>You can see the 1080p MP4 version of the Filtrzzz video <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s2ZajsuPomg">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re developing a startup promo video where you narrate a description of your product, include a few pictures, and add a few animations/transitions for added flare, PowerPoint videos might be an option to consider. At the least, it&rsquo;s a good introduction to those looking to break into organized video production.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>By the way, Filterzzz would never work as a real product (nor would I ever publicly post hypothetical startups that could actually be feasible business ideas) for a few reasons:</em></p>

<ol>
<li><em>The way the filters work depends on the internal design of the webpage. Since many websites have highly maverick designs, the filter isn&rsquo;t guaranteed to work 100% on all websites.</em></li>
<li><em>As you saw in the video, the performance impact of the filters on browser speed varies, at least with my implementation. The performance would need to be consistent among all websites in order to avoid user outrage.</em></li>
<li><em>The biggest point: reading text on a filtered background for long periods of time <strong>hurts eyes</strong>. Any startup which tried to promote this business idea would be sued into bankruptcy within a month.</em></li>
</ol>


<p><em>Per #3 and the personal liability it poses, I won&rsquo;t be releasing my source code for the filters, but you can easily create your own by using the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en">Stylish extension for Chrome</a> and implementing <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/filters/understanding-css/">CSS filters</a> into a style.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Totally-Real Totally-Serious Startup Pitch For Venture Capital]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-26T21:26:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Here are presentation slides and a transcript from a totally-real totally-serious startup pitch I did recently for a group of<strong> </strong></em>totally-real totally-serious venture capitalists for <em>totally-real totally-serious venture capital.</em>**</p>

<p><em>This presentation is totally-real totally-serious and not fabricated in any way whatsoever for the purpose of humor. The business and technical terminologies used in this presentation are totally-real totally-serious representations of my own knowledge. I </em>totally-real totally-serious <em>pinky-swear!</em></p>

<p><em>[This isn&rsquo;t real.]</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<h2><strong>Introduction</strong></h2>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide1.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide1" /></p>

<p>Good afternoon, and thank you all for giving me the opportunity to present my startup proposal. I&rsquo;m Max Woolf, I&rsquo;m here with NegaCycl, and I&rsquo;m going to make you a billion dollars, no problem.</p>

<p>Today, I&rsquo;ll be talking about NegaCycl, and I hope that by end of the presentation, you&rsquo;ll agree that this startup is timeless. First, I&rsquo;ll be discussing the inspiring, book-and-movie-deal-worthy events that led toward this business idea. I&rsquo;ll tell you a bit about NegaCycl and how it works, and lastly, you&rsquo;ll see a few cool ways we plan to market the business.</p>

<p>Our mission at NegaCycl is simple: <strong>we are a web application that allows us to provide our users the quickest routes &ndash; regardless of where and <em>when</em> they want to go to.</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide4.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide4" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m here today to formally ask you for $2.01 million in seed money for NegaCycl. Yes, that $0.01 million is significant.</p>

<h2><strong>The Eureka Moment</strong></h2>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide6.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide6" /></p>

<p>On a cold Monday night in November after work, I turned on my TV and began to watch the pilot episode of Start-Ups: Silicon Valley: a reality TV show on Bravo that captures the entrepreneurial essence of the Bay Area&hellip; which apparently involves a lot of dating and partying. Huh, you learn something new every day.</p>

<p>During the episode, the cast members throw an extremely classy toga party to celebrate the launch of some fitness startup no one really cares about.</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide7.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide7" /></p>

<p>After becoming incredibly inebriated at the party, the cast members played <em>the</em> most popular party game for nerds: Drunk Computer Science Trivia.</p>

<p>One question asked to a cast member was<em> &ldquo;How do you solve negative cycles?&rdquo;</em> I thought that was weird; I personally had never heard of the term &ldquo;negative cycle&rdquo; before, and the question didn&rsquo;t seem scripted like a typical Bravo show. What the heck are negative cycles, and how do you solve them?</p>

<p>After a few vicious Google searches, I discovered what negative cycles were. More importantly, I made a startling realization: people in the real world actually care about these negative cycles! And just think, if negative cycles are relevant to those who are incredibly drunk, imagine how important they&rsquo;ll be to those who are sober! Clearly, this market has been vali &ndash; <em>wait for it</em> &ndash;</p>

<p>dated! Yes, reality shows on Bravo are heavily edited for added drama, but no one can edit&hellip; inspiration.</p>

<h2><strong>What is NegaCycl?</strong></h2>

<p>Now, you may be asking &ldquo;What is NegaCycl?&rdquo; Yes, as you&rsquo;ve likely figured out, it&rsquo;s a portmanteau of &ldquo;negative&rdquo; and &ldquo;cycle&rdquo;, but there&rsquo;s a lot more to it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/gxfgcfg.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide10" /></p>

<p>Cycles are a part of a branch of computer science known as Graph Theory. In Graph Theory, graphs are networks which connect<em> blah blah blah</em>&hellip;</p>

<p>&hellip;this slide is boring. Moving on.</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide11.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide11" /></p>

<p>On this map are arbitrary numbers for each path which represent the amount of time it takes to go between each city. Let&rsquo;s say, for example, a person wants to go from Boston to New York. What&rsquo;s the route that will take the shortest total amount of time? Do you go Boston &ndash; San Diego &ndash; New York, or Boston &ndash; Atlanta &ndash; New York, or even Boston &ndash; Atlanta &ndash; St. Louis &ndash; New York? Solving it through brute force by calculating every possible route and their respective total times is not sexy.</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/jchjghjghj.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide12" /></p>

<p>In the previous slide, we made the implicit assumption that time always moves forward. That isn&rsquo;t necessarily true. Maybe in the future, some startup offering particle-accelerators-as-a-service gets too popular, their users accidently form a few black holes, and boom, time and space crack. Oops! It could happen to anyone, and once it does, time can move backward. In this example, you could go back and forth, or &ldquo;cycle&rdquo;, between Atlanta and St. Louis to go further and further back in time. In that case, the math to find the shortest route between Boston and New York becomes even less sexy.</p>

<p>We can&rsquo;t have unsexiness. We&rsquo;re a startup. We&rsquo;re sexy. And we know it.</p>

<p>Back to the Drunk Computer Science Trivia on Bravo: how do you solve negative cycles anyways? The cast member replied with<em> &ldquo;Are we talking Bellman&rsquo;s algorithm or Dijkstra&rsquo;s algorithm?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>And after a few more vicious Google searches, I discovered that the answer is&hellip; neither of those two algorithms because the show&rsquo;s cast members are dum-dums.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide14.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide14" /></p>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s get to the meat of the pitch: what<em> is</em> NegaCycl? It&rsquo;s simply a web app that calculates the route of the shortest amount of time for travel using the Bellman-Ford algorithm. The Bellman-Ford algorithm solves graphs containing these negative cycles, and thus in the context of travel, it can account for time moving backwards, as with Atlanta and St. Louis. Easy peasy lemon squeezy.</p>

<p>Currently, NegaCycl is the <em>only</em> startup that accounts for fractures in the space-time continuum. Sure, startups might use APIs from Facebook and Twitter in their own code, but no other startup uses the API&hellip; of the universe. Since the underlying 12 lines of pseudocode are so elegant and efficient, we&rsquo;ll be able to scale without breaking a sweat. We&rsquo;re going to do PHP, because Facebook uses PHP for their server language and Facebook has over 1 billion users, so it&rsquo;s legit. Lastly, this time-routing technology would be very useful for enterprise shipping companies, such as UPS and FedEx, and we could potentially license it to them. Imagine: you could receive your delivery from an online order&hellip;before you even order it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide15.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide15" /></p>

<p>Unfortunately, I don&rsquo;t have a working demo of the app to show you today, but here&rsquo;s a screenshot of the prototype. We&rsquo;re using Twitter Bootstrap as the core framework for our front-end interface, as it looks cool and it&rsquo;s free, and that&rsquo;s good enough for me!</p>

<h2><strong>How will we market NegaCycl?</strong></h2>

<p>There are a lot of players in the travel space. How will we market NegaCycl so that it stands out from the crowd? You&rsquo;ll see that we have that very well planned.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide18.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide18" /></p>

<p>With startups, one of the key drivers of success is who you know, and who <em>they</em> know. That&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;ve decided to utilize two very influential tech celebrities to help publicize NegaCycl: Michael Arrington, the founder and former head editor of TechCrunch, and Robert Scoble, a popular journalist with hundreds of thousands of social media followers,</p>

<p>I, personally, am Facebook friends with both of them. They&rsquo;re my biffles, my best friends for life!</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide19.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide19" /></p>

<p>During my time as a business major at Carnegie Mellon University, I&rsquo;ve learnt that brand identity is one of the most important assets for a business. Between two otherwise equal startups, the one whose logo is cleanest and whose web pages are shiniest will be the winner.</p>

<p>The name &ldquo;NegaCycl&rdquo; is very catchy. Note how there&rsquo;s no vowels in Cycl! Poor literacy is kewl nowadays, and the blatant deliberate typographical mistake will make our grammar-obsessed potential users much more likely to remember our name and curse us out on public forums. Hey, free advertising!</p>

<p>Additionally,  I&rsquo;ve taken great care in designing a unique logo myself for NegaCycl, one that will be remembered forever. Do you know how long it took me to align all the vectors to create this excellent logo? Like, 20 minutes. 20 minutes! Have you noticed that the logo looks like a bicycle? That&rsquo;s completely intentional. Have you noticed that the face is negative? That&rsquo;s also completely intentional. The visual subtext in this logo is quite clearly indicative of a logo for a future Fortune 500 company: a company named NegaCycl!</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide22.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide22" /></p>

<p>And now, my plan for social media promotion with NegaCycl. I&rsquo;ve developed a automated script that does community management for our Facebook brand page by using a proven effective strategy. At no additional cost. Trust me, I read <em>The Lean Startup</em> by Eric Ries, I&rsquo;m an expert at being lean.*<br/>
*</p>

<p>We start by finding cute pictures, which are statistically proven to have a greater response rate than boring startup press announcements <em>ugh</em>. The automated script parses Reddit, a link and image aggregator, and its API for the top cute pictures of the day. Then, the script applies a NegaCycl watermark in the lower-right corner of the image, and posts the image on our Facebook page for our fans to see. When our users inevitably share the image, we get <strong>all</strong> the credit. Everyone on Facebook will see NegaCycl as the harbinger of happiness and cuddles.</p>

<p>In the post message, we will ask questions to users, as they also make people more likely to respond. &ldquo;What do you think of this picture?&rdquo; &ldquo;What are you doing today?&rdquo; &ldquo;What is the answer to life, the universe, and everything?&rdquo; Things like that. The automated script does not spend time reading the user responses to the question because it&rsquo;s an asshole.</p>

<p>Lastly, we will encourage the users to Like, Share, and Comment on our pictures. Whenever a Facebook user does any of those three things on a NegaCycl post, the NegaCycl post then appears on the News Feeds of that user&rsquo;s friends, and the cycle repeats until Facebook is <em>ours. </em>And once we conquer Facebook, we&rsquo;ll conquer Twitter as well, and I guess we&rsquo;ll also conquer Google%2B because why not it&rsquo;s not hard.</p>

<p>We become a successful travel startup, or we pivot into a generic image regurgitator. Either works for me, really.</p>

<h2><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>

<p>You&rsquo;ve seen how we came up with the idea. You&rsquo;ve seen how we&rsquo;re going to execute the idea. You&rsquo;ve seen how we&rsquo;re going to promote the idea. NegaCycl will indeed change the way you use travel apps: you no longer have to ask &ldquo;where do I want to go to&rdquo;, but <em>when</em> do I want to go to.</p>

<p>NegaCycl may be a crazy idea for a startup, sure. We don&rsquo;t use any photo filters! However, it&rsquo;s the crazy ideas that are the most disruptive in Silicon Valley, and not only will we disrupt the travel space, but we will also disrupt the travel time.</p>

<p>As we said earlier, we ask you for $2.01 million, and we&rsquo;ll use this couple of millions to make a couple of billions. Piece of cake. Chocolate cake.</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide25.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide25" /></p>

<p>We will put your money to very good use.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re going to spend $1 million for a waterfront office in San Francisco. I want to look outside the window and be able to see the Golden Gate Bridge and Alcatraz. Alcatraz is so much fun!</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll use another $1 million to throw the most epic toga launch party ever. Bravo had a good one, and we&rsquo;re to going to top that. One word: Lions. Gladiatorial combat, anyone? We&rsquo;ll get so much press and word-of-mouth advertising, especially if someone gets killed!</p>

<p>Lastly, we&rsquo;ll use the remaining $0.01 million to hire a programmer to make the damn app.</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide26.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide1" /></p>

<p>In all, I hope that you&rsquo;ll invest your money in our startup. So, what did you think of this presentation? Do you think you&rsquo;ll invest in NegaCycl? Like, share, and comment!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
