<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Startups | minimaxir]]></title>
  <link href="minimaxir.com//startups/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-15T00:24:18-07:00</updated>
  <id>minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When a Startup Sends a Passive-Aggressive Email Every Day]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2013/05/overly-attached-startup/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-13T18:51:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2013/05/overly-attached-startup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple weeks ago, my best friend wanted to make a personal website. After talking with her about what types of features she wanted (home page, photo galleries, low price, etc.) I recommended that she use a website-building platform with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WYSIWYG">WYSIWYG</a> editor, such as <a href="http://www.wix.com/">Wix</a> or <a href="http://www.weebly.com/">Weebly</a>. I had heard good things about both websites, especially Weebly, a <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2007/01/15/weebly-goes-with-ycombinator/">Y Combinator startup</a> which has been <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/05/03/with-over-15m-sites-built-weebly-launches-new-planner-and-mobile-editor-brings-website-creation-service-to-android/">rolling out new features</a> and receiving positive reviews.</p>

<p>She registered for Weebly and loved it. I registered as well to check it out, and I was also impressed after creating a draft test website and experimenting with both drag-and-drop UI elements and raw HTML/CSS editing. Since Weebly has Contributor functionality, I was able to edit her website without having to access her account. I made a few CSS tweaks and that was it: I didn&rsquo;t publish my own website on Weebly, as I&rsquo;m very happy with this blog. :)</p>

<p>A day after her website was published, I received an e-mail from Weebly: a generic &ldquo;First Steps to Creating Your Website.&rdquo; It&rsquo;s just one email, I think, so I ignore it. And then, the next day, I receive another e-mail that was much less subtle: &ldquo;Your website misses you!&rdquo;</p>

<p>This is certainly the first time a startup&rsquo;s emails have tried to <em>guilt</em> me into using the service.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>An Email A Day Keeps The Users Away</h1>

<p><img src="/img/weebly1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>When I register for <em>any</em> business, not just including startups, I don&rsquo;t enjoy seeing any emails that aren&rsquo;t helpful or aren&rsquo;t expected. I&rsquo;m OK when businesses send emails that alert me when a new service has been launched or when a scheduled newsletter is released. In the former case, the email is directly relevant to my interests, in the latter case, the email is not an unexpected surprise.</p>

<p>In Weebly&rsquo;s case, and any other startup that resorts to forward emailing strategies as a form of &ldquo;growth hacking,&rdquo; they&rsquo;re invalidating my trust. A once-a-month announcement about your business is OK, but if I want to visit your website, I don&rsquo;t need to be reminded every <em>day</em>.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at the emails that Weebly has sent:</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 5th: First Steps to Creating Your Website</h2>

<p><img src="/img/weebly2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>This is actually a good first e-mail.</p>

<p>It adds a personal touch. I didn&rsquo;t pay much attention to it since I didn&rsquo;t plan on publishing my own website, but to a new customer, it makes them feel welcome.</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 6th: Your website misses you!</h2>

<p><img src="/img/weebly3.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I received this <em>the next day</em> after the previous email. My website misses me? It&rsquo;s been two days! Which you tell me with a rather disturbing amount of precision!</p>

<p>My website is not a cow in FarmVille. I don&rsquo;t need to publish my website immediately. In fact, if I were to publish a website, I would make sure it&rsquo;s polished first, in which case the email&rsquo;s push toward publishing ASAP would actually be insulting.</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 7th: Need Any Help?</h2>

<p><img src="/img/weebly4.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a totally-not-automatically-generated e-mail by a employee at Weebly. It lacks any Weebly branding, which supposedly gives it a more &ldquo;personal&rdquo; touch&hellip;except if Richard wanted to give it a personal touch, he would have included <em>my name</em>. The <a href="http://emailmarketing.comm100.com/email-marketing-ebook/can-spam-law.aspx">legally-mandated</a> unsubscribe link, a requirement for commercial emails, doesn&rsquo;t make me feel any more comfortable.</p>

<p>And again, it&rsquo;s only been three days.</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 8th: Max, check out your mobile website!</h2>

<p><img src="/img/weebly5.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>While that feature may be cool, finding an <em>excuse</em> to send me an e-mail really isn&rsquo;t necessary.</p>

<p>Weebly skipped May 9th, fortunately.</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 10th: Free vs. Pro: Which One is Right for You?</h2>

<p><img src="/img/weebly6.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>&ldquo;As you may have noticed.&rdquo; In that case, why bother sending the e-mail? Will the e-mail&rsquo;s argument be any different?</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 11th: Max, get 33% off at Weebly!</h2>

<p><img src="/img/weebly7.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Now we&rsquo;re mixing both overly precise user registration dates <em>and</em> &ldquo;as you may have noticed&rdquo; verbage! I did notice, as a matter of fact! I noticed <em>yesterday</em>!</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 12th: It&rsquo;s been 8 days, 2 hours, 30 minutes and 6 seconds&hellip;</h2>

<p><img src="/img/weebly8.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Ok, seriously, what the hell?</p>

<p>At this point, Weebly is seriously <em>threatening</em> me into publishing my website. Gone are the informative email subject lines: now, Weebly simply <em>reminds</em> me how much time I&rsquo;ve spent not working on a website. They&rsquo;ve graduated from passive-aggressive to just aggressive.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s genuinely terrifying is that Weebly actually created a custom email message to send to users to send after a week of having an unpublished site. <em>They tested this email behavior and thought this was a good idea.</em> Apparently, they never considered that a user could exist solely to contribute to another user&rsquo;s website.</p>

<p>Some might say that I should have unsubscribed if I was unhappy with Weebly&rsquo;s emails. Indeed, all the e-mails had unsubscribe links, hidden where most people won&rsquo;t see them of course. But that&rsquo;s not the point: if startups keep sending forward e-mails, <em>everyone</em> loses.</p>

<p>At the least, I&rsquo;m very cautious to recommend Weebly to anyone else.</p>

<hr>


<p><strong>UPDATE (5/14/13)</strong>: On the corresponding <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5704860">Hacker News thread</a>, David Rusenko, founder and CEO of Weebly, posted a response:</p>

<blockquote><p>I&rsquo;d like to jump in and clarify a few things. First, we have recently been testing the frequency of our email sending, and the author seems to have been bucketed into the &ldquo;more frequent&rdquo; group. That being said, we were actually planning on reducing the frequency of what we emailed the author by roughly 25%, including eliminating the &ldquo;Your website misses you&rdquo; and the &ldquo;It’s been 8 days, 2 hours, 30 minutes and 6 seconds…&rdquo; emails, among others. I just fast-tracked this and it&rsquo;s now live, so our email volume when you sign up is now much lower.</p>

<p>Second, we put a lot of effort into trying to send personalized email communication that is specific to your use case, but it looks like we missed a very important group, contributors to others' sites. This was a mistake. These emails may make sense if you were starting your own site, but they certainly don&rsquo;t make sense if you were just contributing to someone else&rsquo;s. I&rsquo;m going to make sure we revise that set of emails within 2 weeks to something more appropriate and even less frequent.</p>

<p>Last, as many here are correct to assume, we are constantly testing and refining our email communications. I think it&rsquo;s helpful to understand our customer&rsquo;s psychology when they are signing up for Weebly, it is instructive in understanding our thought process and why we send the emails we do.
Most of our customers (60%) consider themselves entrepreneurs. They are bringing a new idea to life, things like chairigami.com, themintspace.com, stealthelectricbikesusa.com or weeknightbite.com. They are quitting their full-time jobs to do this and it&rsquo;s a very frightening process.</p>

<p>Creating their site is especially daunting and difficult for them, even though it&rsquo;s so crucial to their success. Many of them start the process, want to finish, but give up. We&rsquo;ve found that the first week is the most crucial. In our email communications, it&rsquo;s our goal to try to help them across the finish line to a high-quality site.</p>

<p>In this case, we were emailing too often, and we&rsquo;ve stopped doing that. In general, most of our users do appreciate some help and encouragement along the way, and we will keep testing emails to try to make that as effective, helpful, and non-annoying as possible.</p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s good to hear that Weebly is aware of the issue, and I&rsquo;m thankful for David&rsquo;s response, although I&rsquo;ll still be keeping an eye on the close eye on how much spam they&rsquo;re still sending out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let Myspace's Justin Timberlake Bring Sexy To The Entire Internet]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2013/01/sexy-will-haunt-your-dreams/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-15T21:36:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2013/01/sexy-will-haunt-your-dreams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>TechCrunch writer Sarah Perez recently wrote <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/15/lost-on-new-myspace-cant-escape-justin-send-help/">an incredibly hilarious article</a> about <a href="https://new.myspace.com/">Myspace</a>&rsquo;s recent redesign, and the&hellip;overemphasis of a certain former N'Sync band member. Justin Timberlake, the spearhead of Myspace&rsquo;s music-oriented redesign, stresses his clean-shaven image with a handsome yet somber black-and-white portrait that always seems to follow you where you go.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m OK with this. There are certainly far <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/03/ethics-self-promotion/"><em>worse</em></a> ways to promote a startup.</p>

<p>His moody yet charmful face adds a touch of class to any website. But why does he have to stay constrained to Myspace? Why not let Justin Timberlake dominate the world?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>No Such Thing As Too Much Sexy</h2>

<p>If you are reading this post on a desktop or laptop, you&rsquo;ll see a handsome fellow in the lower-right corner. This is Justin Timberlake of the Mickey Mouse Club. Say hi.</p>

<p>Using the power of the Stylish extension for Chrome and Firefox, Mr. Timberlake has already made his mark on many startups around the internet.</p>

<p><a href="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest2-e1358404534897.png"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest2-e1358404534897.png" alt="" /></a>
TechCrunch</p>

<p><a href="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest9-e1358404467980.png"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest9-e1358404467980.png" alt="" /></a>
Facebook</p>

<p><a href="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest8-e1358404790348.png"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest8-e1358404790348.png" alt="" /></a>
Twitter</p>

<p><a href="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest7-e1358404639594.png"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest7-e1358404639594.png" alt="" /></a>
Instagram</p>

<p><a href="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest5-e1358404610346.png"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest5-e1358404610346.png" alt="" /></a>
Dropbox</p>

<p><a href="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest4-e1358404660737.png"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/justintest4-e1358404660737.png" alt="" /></a>
Imgur</p>

<p><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en"><img src="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en" alt="" /></a>
Google Search</p>

<p>To accomplish this magic, I use the Stylish browser extension, which can be used with either <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en">Chrome</a> or <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/stylish/">Firefox</a>. I have used Stylish <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/">before, with browser filters</a>, and it worked very well. If you want your own moody Justin, follow these steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Install the Stylish extension for your browser.</li>
<li>In the extension preferences, go to &ldquo;Managed Installed Styles&rdquo; and select &ldquo;Write New Style&rdquo;</li>
<li><p>Paste this CSS code in the &ldquo;Code&rdquo; textbox:</p>

<pre><code>body, ._li, .main {
background-image: url(http://i.imgur.com/UN5HE.png) !important;
background-position: right bottom !important;
background-repeat: no-repeat !important;
background-attachment: fixed !important;
}
</code></pre></li>
</ol>


<p>And you&rsquo;re done! Justin will appear pretty much everywhere. Yes, there are a lot of <em>!important</em> declarations, but Justin Timberlake is an important man.</p>

<p>In fact, by using the HTML snippet in this <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/display-justin-timberlake-sexiness">GitHub repository</a>, you can add Justin to your own site!</p>

<p>Feel free to narrow down the domains where Justin appears by using Stylish as necessary. Although, why would you do such a thing!?</p>

<h2>Taking Justin To The Next Level</h2>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/816440400_1965379.gif?resize=400%2C232" alt="816440400_1965379" /></p>

<p>Now that we can make Justin appear anywhere, let&rsquo;s put his power to good use. TechCrunch writer Alexia Tsostis recently made a post about the <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/16/were-bringing-techcrunch-back/">upcoming redesign of TechCrunch</a>, which, I admit, is long overdue.</p>

<p>In the post, Alexia spoils that the redesign will include lots of sparkles. And a picture of the Justin-man himself. Above is a mockup made by Chris Velazco, another TechCrunch writer, and it is indeed marvelous. (except for the lack of a comments section!)</p>

<p>But why wait for the redesign? We have Timberlake Technology. We can do it <em>now</em>.</p>

<p>Using the power of Stylish, I present to you, a sneak peek into TechCrunch&rsquo;s 2013 redesign.</p>

<p>I made a <em>few</em> stylistic additions as well. It&rsquo;s magic.</p>

<p>You can find a copy of the CSS I used to emulate this wonderful layout in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/techcrunch-1999">this GitHub repository</a>.</p>

<p>Will you let Timberlake enrich <em>your</em> life? He&rsquo;s waiting. In the lower-right corner of your screen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Auto-Save Images From Reddit To Computer Without Visiting The Site (Using IFTTT)]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T21:32:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>TL;DR: Use this <a href="https://ifttt.com/recipes/74285">IFTTT recipe</a>, and change the subreddit value in the parameter of the Feed URL as needed.</em></strong></p>

<p>In <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">a previous post</a>, I joked about a hypothetical social media strategy in which an automated script does Facebook brand management by stealing the top cute images from <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a> &ndash; an aggregator of trending topics and images &ndash;  and reposting them on the Facebook page, additionally adding a cute message encouraging users to LIKE, SHARE, and COMMENT!  We get easy social media fame for no monetary cost.</p>

<p>Out of curiosity, I wanted to see if it was feasible to create such a script. Both Reddit and Facebook indeed have APIs that make it easy. But then I have to set up a server to check Reddit periodically, ensure that no images are duplicated, etc., and that can take time to implement and ensure that it works correctly (<em>all</em> the images must be cute!). I looked into <a href="https://ifttt.com/">IFTTT</a>, a relatively new startup that talks between different popular web services to automate simple tasks, like posting to Twitter whenever you post to Facebook.</p>

<p>As it turns out, yes, this is possible, and you can also save the top images on Reddit to your computer via any cloud storage service without ever visiting the website too! Just use <a href="https://ifttt.com/recipes/74285">this IFTTT recipe</a>! There are a few interesting caveats, though&hellip;</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Really Simple Syndication is&hellip;Really Simple?</h2>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/redditrss2.png?resize=304%2C242" alt="redditrss2" /></p>

<p>IFTTT allows users to extract information from RSS feeds, which one might typically be used to read blogs and news articles. The RSS feed typically provides the title, author, date, and content of a post: the important things. However, RSS has more applications: it can distribute other data, such as weather and desktop wallpapers. IFTTT allows other apps to load image and audio files from an RSS feed, but only if the RSS feed link links to the content itself.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this won&rsquo;t work on Reddit by default, as its RSS feeds do not contain a direct link to the photo and instead link to the Reddit comments on the image. Image-based websites, such as <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/">BuzzFeed</a> and <a href="http://interfacelift.com/wallpaper/downloads/date/any/">InterfaceLift</a> also implement a similar system because they don&rsquo;t want their users just to use a script to download images and bypass the website and its lovely revenue-generating advertisements. Therefore, the RSS feed alone won&rsquo;t work with IFTTT.</p>

<p>During my research into my social media exploitation hypothesis, I found a <a href="http://blog.stevemould.com/rss-feed-reddit-stories-score-threshold/">blog post by Steve Mould</a> that provides a way to translate data from Reddit&rsquo;s JSON API to an RSS feed using a service called <a href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/">Yahoo Pipes</a>. This modified RSS feed, when given a subreddit and a score threshold, obtains the top Reddit posts in that subreddit above that karma threshold (upvotes &ndash; downvotes), and returns a feed item which contains direct link to the referenced URL.</p>

<p>Here is <a href="http://bit.ly/W1ypdf">my variation of his Reddit Pipe</a>. My script to process the API has a few changes (such as using Reddit&rsquo;s &ldquo;hot&rdquo; posts, instead of the top posts; hot posts update much more frequently). Testing it with r/aww and a threshold of 50 karma, I received 177 very cute pictures on my computer in a week.</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/redditcute.png?resize=625%2C382" alt="redditcute" /><br/>
From that Pipe, you can get the data in a RSS feed URL. Right-click and copy that feed URL into a IFTTT recipe as the source. For the action, use the <strong></strong> variable to retrieve the image URL.</p>

<h2>With Great Power Comes Great Cuteness</h2>

<p>Yes, you can save the Reddit images to your computer automatically using <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</a>. Or <a href="https://drive.google.com">Google Drive</a>. Or <a href="https://skydrive.live.com/">SkyDrive</a>. Or even get a cute email every hour!</p>

<p>Thanks to IFTTT, there are many other creative things you can do with the feed that you can include in a recipe:</p>

<ul>
<li>Auto-post the image to your Tumblr or WordPress blog. Easy cuteness, and you&rsquo;ll be the source!</li>
<li>Auto-curate the cute photos to your Facebook or Twitter account. All your friends will love you!</li>
<li>Get social media fame for no additional monetary cost by publishing the cute images to your Facebook Page, with an encouragement to LIKE SHARE and COMMENT! My original hypothesis was correct!</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/redditnega.png?resize=625%2C418" alt="redditnega" /></p>

<h2>Caveats</h2>

<p>One caveat in using Yahoo Pipes is that it is rate limited to 200 runs in a 10 minute interval, meaning that the IFTTT recipe provided will likely fail if more than 200 people use the feed. If that does happen, just clone my pipe, and use the RSS feed from the clone for your own personal recipe.</p>

<p>Also, there&rsquo;s no rate limiting on when recipes are triggered and images are posted/downloaded. You can trigger multiple images simultaneously, which may be considered spammy if you are posting to social media. In that case, increase the karma threshold to reduce the frequency of the postings and to maintain a high quality of the images.</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/redditifttt.png?resize=625%2C239" alt="redditifttt" /><br/>
Getting socially-vetted photos on your computer without any effort is a useful timesaver. A solution to a first world problem, perhaps, but it&rsquo;s the little things that count!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Do Many Tweets Begin With A Period?]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2013/01/prefixed-period/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-04T21:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2013/01/prefixed-period</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not a Twitter fanatic. Although I do have <a href="https://twitter.com/minimaxir">a Twitter account</a> with about 300 followers,  Facebook&rsquo;s Subscribe feature <a href="http://www.facebook.com/max.woolf">on my Facebook profile</a> has met my use case for publishing sarcastic quips and cool links for a broad audience over the internet. I mostly use my Twitter account to read tweets from tech columnists, yet I don&rsquo;t even comment on their tweets because <strong>tweets that are replies to someone are not visible in the home timeline of my followers</strong>. I can understand the intuition behind this behavior: Twitter conversations can contain a lot of low-content tweets, and Twitter doesn&rsquo;t want its users to be spammed.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve noticed that many tweets from actual Twitter fanatics begin with a prefixed period, such as <em>&ldquo;.@minimaxir wow funny joke!&rdquo; </em>and <em>&ldquo;.@minimaxir is a huge dork!&rdquo;</em>. I thought the dot was a typo, until I noticed many people also prefixing the period, seemingly randomly, in their own tweets. All of those tweets seemed like witty replies that begged for mass exposure, and so I eventually realized that <strong>beginning your reply Tweet with a period (.) allows it to be seen by all your followers. </strong>Otherwise, only the replyee will receive notification of the reply.</p>

<p>Having your reply tweets appear to your followers only if you begin them with a prefixed period is not intuitive at all. And this particular behavior and its workaround are not documented in <a href="https://support.twitter.com/groups/31-twitter-basics/topics/109-tweets-messages/articles/14023-what-are-replies-and-mentions">Twitter&rsquo;s help docs</a>. And replying to tweets is a core feature of Twitter. How many users would be able to deduce this behavior? How many brands, who rely on user engagement, are even aware of this behavior?</p>

<p>As it turns out, I was only partially correct. It&rsquo;s even <em>less</em> intuitive.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>XY = @(Z)</h2>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/twitter2.png?resize=513%2C181" alt="twitter2" /></p>

<p>I recently saw <a href="https://twitter.com/ScottyLabs/status/286921265514700801">a tweet</a> in my timeline that had a prefixed period, but clearly was not a reply to anyone. Confused, I pointed out that prefixed periods aren&rsquo;t necessary if the tweet is not a reply. <a href="https://twitter.com/amyquispe">Amy Quispe</a>, founder of ScottyLabs and a CS senior at Carnegie Mellon University with much more startup knowledge than myself, pointed out that I was wrong, and <strong>if the tweet begins with a @, it will not appear in your follower&rsquo;s timelines, regardless of whether it&rsquo;s a reply or a mention</strong>.</p>

<p>Anyone who tweets, for example, &ldquo;<em>@SHO_Dexter is my favorite television show! Season 7 was AWESOME!!!</em>&rdquo;, will likely not have that tweet seen by any of their followers. Therefore, it&rsquo;s incredibly easy, and incredibly likely, for that behavior to unintentionally trigger a false positive for spam. Again, would a person notice that one of his/her tweets is not being seen? It&rsquo;s bad for the user, and it&rsquo;s even bad for @SHO_Dexter, who misses out on the free advertising.</p>

<p>As it turns out, <em>that</em> <em>correction** was still only partially correct</em>, as there&rsquo;s one more important caveat:<strong> if a tweet by X begins a tweet with an @ mention of Y, and if Z is a follower of <em>both</em> X and Y, then Z will see the tweet. If the second condition is not true, then Z will not see the tweet.</strong></p>

<p>Twitter is apparently a course in deductive reasoning. To be fair, this caveat is clearly stated in the help docs, and this behavior makes sense in the context of mutual friends among users. Nevertheless, it&rsquo;s not intuitive at all, and it&rsquo;s mostly irrelevant: a prefixed period tweet reaches all of your followers, 100% of the time.</p>

<h2>The Pestilent Prefixed Period Problem</h2>

<p>Twitter users want maximum reach. Brands want maximum reach. Therefore, everyone will use the prefixed period for replies and mentions. Those who don&rsquo;t use prefixed periods on Twitter will be left behind in this cutthroat game of social media.</p>

<p>There are two problems with encouraging prefixed periods:</p>

<ol>
<li>It alienates newcomers to Twitter. Some online communities do have unwritten behaviors: <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a>, for example, invokes &ldquo;vote fuzzing&rdquo; on popular posts, which disguises the true amount of upvotes and downvotes on any particular post by adding fake upvotes/downvotes. You won&rsquo;t find that in any Reddit documentation, which leads to the frequent outbursts of &ldquo;WHO THE HELL WOULD DOWNVOTE THIS PUPPY?&rdquo; Quirks like these don&rsquo;t make communities exclusive: it makes them insular.</li>
<li><strong>It looks tacky and ugly</strong>. That&rsquo;s not a trivial complaint. Every @mention tweet looks like someone made a typo. I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s the brand image Twitter wants.</li>
</ol>


<p>How could Twitter address this? An option would be to adopt a system similar to Facebook&rsquo;s <em>ad hoc</em> post visibility settings, and allow users to set the reach of an individual tweet as necessary. Another option is to have an <em>All your replies and @mentions are shown to all your followers</em> account option that is opt-in, and let the user&rsquo;s followers determine whether the content is spam.</p>

<p>Twitter, with an impending IPO, needs to help potential newcomers out in any way possible. Eliminating the need for prefixed periods is a great start to increasing accessibility.</p>

<p><em>PS: I am not a huge dork.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Startup Promo Video Using... PowerPoint?]]></title>
    <link href="minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-29T21:28:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I noticed deep in the documentation for PowerPoint 2010 that it <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/powerpoint-help/turn-your-presentation-into-a-video-HA010336763.aspx">supports video output</a> for presentations. Like a good nerd, I experimented to see what it could actually do. My first test of the functionality was a humor video about pitching a <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">hypothetical startup named NegaCycl</a>, complete with animation and narration, which I trashed and eventually retooled because I&rsquo;m bad at verbal comedic delivery. Interestingly, the output video was a 1:1 comparison to what was displayed on my own computer screen during the presentation. Naturally, I decided to test it even harder.</p>

<p>What I have here is another hypothetical, non-real startup named Filtrzzz (based on a <a href="http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10151356495205450&amp;set=a.432190050449.225968.582270449&amp;type=1">popular Facebook post</a> I made), animated and rendered using PowerPoint, with more complicated objects such as embedded audio and video, and an attempt to sync the presentation timing with the audio for dramatic effect. Plus sarcastic humor, of course.</p>

<p>PowerPoint video creation is feasible if you don&rsquo;t have or can&rsquo;t afford dedicated video software and need a promo video in a pinch, as may be the case with an actual startup.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/filtrzzz-ppt.png?resize=625%2C288" alt="filtrzzz ppt" /></p>

<p>The Filtrzzz video relies heavily on slide transitions (the &ldquo;zoom&rdquo; effects at the beginning), text animations (the fade in/fade out on the text at the end), and embedding of media (the background song and the product demos), all of which are very easy to implement, although as with any video, a little trial-and-error is necessary to get a good &ldquo;feel&rdquo; for effect duration, effect intensity, etc.</p>

<p>PowerPoint has the native ability to record timings (i.e. when to progress to the next slide/animation) and voice narrations on a per-slide basis in the Slide Show tab. You can either record the timings while running through a presentation normally (good for maintaining a consistent pace through animations), or record <em>ad hoc</em> per slide (good for voice narration, which is independent from other slides). If timings and narrations are present, when the presentation runs, it will use those timings and play in auto-pilot. When the presentation is exported as a video, it will follow these timings and include the spoken narrations.</p>

<p>The maximum quality output for video through PowerPoint is 720p WMV, which is sufficient for a startup video since users likely are watching the video YouTube-embedded in a webpage. For comparison, I video-captured the presentation using Camtasia at 1080p and rendered the final video as a high-bit rate MP4: the visual quality between the two versions is indistinguishable at non-full screen resolutions. (when watching a video in 1080p at small sizes, the quality is actually even worse!)</p>

<p>You can see the 1080p MP4 version of the Filtrzzz video <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s2ZajsuPomg">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re developing a startup promo video where you narrate a description of your product, include a few pictures, and add a few animations/transitions for added flare, PowerPoint videos might be an option to consider. At the least, it&rsquo;s a good introduction to those looking to break into organized video production.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>By the way, Filterzzz would never work as a real product (nor would I ever publicly post hypothetical startups that could actually be feasible business ideas) for a few reasons:</em></p>

<ol>
<li><em>The way the filters work depends on the internal design of the webpage. Since many websites have highly maverick designs, the filter isn&rsquo;t guaranteed to work 100% on all websites.</em></li>
<li><em>As you saw in the video, the performance impact of the filters on browser speed varies, at least with my implementation. The performance would need to be consistent among all websites in order to avoid user outrage.</em></li>
<li><em>The biggest point: reading text on a filtered background for long periods of time <strong>hurts eyes</strong>. Any startup which tried to promote this business idea would be sued into bankruptcy within a month.</em></li>
</ol>


<p><em>Per #3 and the personal liability it poses, I won&rsquo;t be releasing my source code for the filters, but you can easily create your own by using the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en">Stylish extension for Chrome</a> and implementing <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/filters/understanding-css/">CSS filters</a> into a style.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
