<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gaming | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//gaming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-15T08:32:08-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[max@minimaxir.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Game Theory: How 70,000 Pokemon Players Sabotage Themselves]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/glory-to-the-helix/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-18T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/glory-to-the-helix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pok%C3%A9mon_Red_and_Blue_Versions">Pokemon Red and Pokemon Blue</a> remain as two of the most iconic games in video gaming history. They have retained a lot of nostalgia value for those who grew up playing the games (such as myself), and nowadays even adult gamers revisit such classics.</p>

<p>On the game live-streaming site <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/">Twitch.tv</a>, one user simply known as &ldquo;TwitchPlaysPokemon&rdquo; setup <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/twitchplayspokemon">a live-stream of Pokemon Red</a>, but with a twist: all game commands, such as &ldquo;up&rdquo;,&ldquo;down&rdquo;,&ldquo;left&rdquo;,&ldquo;right&rdquo;,&ldquo;b&rdquo;,&ldquo;a&rdquo;,&ldquo;select&rdquo;, and &ldquo;start&rdquo;, would be input by typing the appropriate command into the livestream chat. At first, this seems like a crazy idea: if thousands of people are inputting commands at the same time, could we accomplish <em>anything</em> in the game?</p>

<p><img src="/img/AcXmBbM.png"></p>

<p>As it turns out, it was an idea that had gone horribly right. By the time gaming forum NeoGAF <a href="http://www.neogaf.com/forum/showthread.php?t=768965">found the stream</a>, the channel had made an unexpected amount of progress; a group of 3,000 viewes made it past the first Gym (out of eight) and continued to move forward. A few days later, after the channel was covered by <a href="http://www.polygon.com/2014/2/17/5420334/twitch-plays-pokemon-captivates-with-more-than-6-5m-total-views">major news outlets</a>, the channel had completed <em>four</em> gyms, inspired the creation of a large amount of <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Luwz9wr8XkoekzU4zv3duj9D2K5AoAyqnYMcbCHZKqc">hilarious fan art</a>, and also created a <a href="http://askhelixfossil.com/">new religion</a>. You can read a summary of the stream&rsquo;s status <a href="https://docs.google.com/a/minimaxir.com/document/d/1Ka89uCBeLl9VV5GPlAKuW7yF8FGtnVmdbPnIwG8FnQ4/preview?pli=1&amp;sle=true">here</a>.</p>

<p>That being said, it was neither a straight nor short path to success. In the end, the gaming community fought its greatest enemy: itself. Twitch Plays Pokemon isn&rsquo;t about winning. It&rsquo;s about trying not to fail spectacularly. And they still fail regardless. It&rsquo;s an irresistible train wreck that&rsquo;s hard to stop watching.</p>

<h1>The Adventure Begins</h1>

<p>The first areas of Pokemon Red are relatively linear up until <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Vermilion_City">Vermilion City</a>, where the third gym is located. Before that, Pokemon Trainer Red, the player character, had a few interesting encounters thanks to the bizarre overlords of the Twitch chat. Red chose <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Charmander">Charmander</a> (later evolved into <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Charmeleon_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Charmeleon</a>) as his starter Pokemon, which he nicknamed <strong>ABBBBBBK (</strong> or &ldquo;Abby&rdquo; for short. He caught a few more basic Pokemon, including a <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pidgey">Pidgey</a> (later evolved into <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pidgeotto_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Pidgeotto</a>) and <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pidgeot_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Pidgeot</a>), 2 <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Rattata">Rattata</a> (one nicknamed <strong>JLVWNNOOOO</strong>, i.e. &ldquo;Jay Leno&rdquo;), a <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Drowzee">Drowzee</a>, and a <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Spearow">Spearow</a> which was traded for a <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Farfetch%27d">Farfetch&rsquo;d</a>, all of which gave him a full party of Pokemon.</p>

<p><img src="/img/MwarCER.png"></p>

<p>Since thousands of players are inputting commands at the same time, there is absolutely no strategy involved in Pokemon battles, which in most cases make the battles unwinnable. Thanks to the nature of RPG level-ups and a few lucky critical hits, Red can still persevere (although it will a few hours).</p>

<p>The Twitch channel was a very casual experience, until Red obtained HM 01 from the <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/S.S._Anne">S.S. Anne</a>, an item that requires a sequence of sequential button presses to operate.</p>

<p>Then things get complicated.</p>

<h1>Cutting A Thin Line</h1>

<p>HM 01 is an item that grants the Cut ability to a Pokemon, which is required to cut trees blocking progress; in this case, the tree in front of the Vermilion City Gym. In order to teach a Pokemon Cut, the player must:</p>

<ol>
<li>Bring up the Start menu.</li>
<li>Select &ldquo;Items.&rdquo;</li>
<li>Select HM 01.</li>
<li>Confirm that HM 01 is to be used.</li>
<li>Select a Pokemon to learn Cut.</li>
<li>Confirm that the selected Pokemon is to learn Cut.</li>
<li>Choose a move for Cut to replace.</li>
</ol>


<p>The kicker? Pressing the B button or choosing the wrong option during <em>any</em> of these 7 steps takes the process back a step.</p>

<p><img src="/img/1XSdWPY.jpg"></p>

<p>At this point in the stream, the audience hit 30,000 viewers. The increased activity caused an input delay of about 20 seconds from when the Twitch user input the command in chat to when the game recognized the command. This can make navigating menus difficult when an &ldquo;up&rdquo; or a &ldquo;down&rdquo; command is applied to a menu that isn&rsquo;t even visible yet.</p>

<p>Additionally, as the number of viewers in a stream increases, the number of trolls increases. And those trolls loved to spam the B button command.</p>

<p>Thanks to these two factors, the channel had failed to teach any Pokemon Cut for over <em>4 hours</em>. The stream chat became a bloodbath of blame.</p>

<p><img src="/img/p30F3g7.png"></p>

<p>Eventually, it happened. The Farfetch&rsquo;d was taught Cut. No one knows <em>how</em>, but it happened. But <em>that</em> was only one step towards progress.</p>

<p>The second step is actually Cutting the tree. In order to Cut:</p>

<ol>
<li>Face the tree.</li>
<li>Bring up the Start menu.</li>
<li>Select &ldquo;Pokemon&rdquo;</li>
<li>Select the Pokemon with Cut.</li>
<li>Select Cut.</li>
</ol>


<p>Same kickers as before, too. Facing the tree is even harder since the same up/down commands for navigating the menus can reorient Red away from the tree.</p>

<p>It took another 4 hours to cut down that tree. Later, when Red was defeated in the Gym, the tree respawned. Yeah.</p>

<p><img src="/img/NCo5N3j.png"></p>

<p>HM 01 was a harsh reminder that the more people present, the higher the chance that your task will fail. Not necessarily due to incompetence and disorganization, but due to mischief.</p>

<h1>Fighting The Ledge Boss</h1>

<p>After the Vermilion City Gym was (eventually) completed, the Twitch stream progressed through <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Kanto_Route_9">Route 9</a> toward <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Lavender_Town">Lavender Town</a>. Sounds simple, until Red hit this obstacle.</p>

<p><img src="/img/ledge.png"></p>

<p>Red must walk from the left to the right through the 1-character-wide path. If Red went down, the ledge is a one-way drop, and Red must walk back to the beginning to try again.</p>

<p>The Twitch chat must go &ldquo;right&rdquo; about 8 times <em>without going &ldquo;down&rdquo; at all</em>.</p>

<p>HM01 had input lag as a contributing factor to its failures. In this case, the trolls had <em>all</em> the power. One &ldquo;down&rdquo; ends the entire attempt. And the stream was even more popular with an audience of 50,000 people.</p>

<p><img src="/img/h2sFCtt.png"></p>

<p>The result? Crossing the ledge took over <em>12 hours</em>. And then Red was defeated by the trainer at the end of the ledge and so getting back across the ledge took an equally absurd amount of time.</p>

<p>Lesson learned? If trolls have absolute power, <em>they will use it</em> and they will use it without mercy.</p>

<p><em>EDIT 2/19: The defeat of the ledge boss was due to the intervention of another Twitch channel which <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/twitchplayspokemon/comments/1y1ee8/the_meta_strat_or_how_we_beat_the_ledge/">executed a meta-strategy</a>: press &ldquo;right&rdquo; in sync with the input delay: with enough people, Red would move right enough times.</em></p>

<h1>Disregarding Decision Trees</h1>

<p>After the ledge incident, the fanbase became paranoid. What other gameplay aspects in this playthrough could be compromised by trolls in the future? One concern is the PC system used to store Pokemon; the same system can also <em>release</em> them, removing them from the game forever. The risk of losing a top Pokemon to the PC due to trolls was too great and would make the game nearly unwinnable, and therefore the stream decided to avoid using the PC unless necessary.</p>

<p>Red progressed through Lavender Town and arrived at <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Celadon_City">Celadon City</a>, where the Twitch channel defeated the Gym Leader for the fourth badge (it took awhile: there was a tree outside <em>and</em> inside the gym!)</p>

<p>At this point in Pokemon Red, the game becomes more nonlinear, which started a debate on what next to do in game. Many pointed out that the party lacked a Pokemon which could learn Surf, a skill, like Cut, which was required to progress in the game much later. Red will eventually earn such a Pokemon which could learn Surf (<a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Lapras">Lapras</a>) as a part of the plot, who&rsquo;s a decent combatant too.</p>

<p>On the other hand, the player can also collect <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Eevee">Eevee</a> as a free Pokemon. Eevee has three evolutions: the terrible <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Flareon_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Flareon</a>, the good <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Jolteon_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Jolteon</a>, and the great <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Vaporeon_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Vaporeon</a> who can also learn Surf. But in order to evolve Vaporeon Eevee into , the party must a) buy a Water Stone, and not accidentally any other elemental stone instead and b) use the Stone <em>without accidentally tossing it</em> and destroying it. Both of which are difficult due to input lag and trolls.</p>

<p>The party had 5 Pokemon (after a Rattata was deposited  earlier into the PC), and so the stream only had the opportunity for get <em>one</em> Pokemon, since the stream did not want deposit any in the PC for fear of release. Which is the more rational path for getting a Pokemon with Surf: waiting to get a guaranteed Lapras, or getting the Eevee and hope the stream can evolve it into a Vaporeon? A guaranteed decent Pokemon or a chance at a great Pokemon?</p>

<p>As it turns out, when 70,000 people make a decision, they aren&rsquo;t exactly rational. Instead, hilarity ensued.</p>

<h1>Game Over Theory</h1>

<p>The stream obtained the Eevee (even after many said it was <a href="http://i.imgur.com/9cV06Yq.png">a bad idea</a>) and went to purchase a Water Stone. Due to input manipulation, they instead bought a Fire Stone, and later the Eevee evolved into the unhelpful Flareon. Chat becomes a bloodbath once again.</p>

<p><img src="/img/QGiFYYu.jpg"></p>

<p>In order to make room for Lapras in the future, the stream attempted to use a PC to deposit Flareon.</p>

<p><img src="/img/0ndYCF1.png"></p>

<p>Instead, both Abby and Jay Leno were permanently released.</p>

<p><img src="/img/tumblr_n157ldJl611rvlenbo1_1280.jpg"></p>

<p>The stream became completely derailed.</p>

<p>As of today, Twitch pushes on, but everyone who&rsquo;s participating in the stream has now learned a lesson: people act in their self interest and do what they think is best. Trolls have&hellip;different self-interests. And there will always be trolls. Knowing how to fail gracefully is always valuable.</p>

<p>At the least, the amount of progress the stream has made is still very, very impressive and unexpected.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Credit for all fan art goes to their respective artists: I&rsquo;m currently working on tracking them down.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When Uninstalling A PC Game Erases the Entire Hard Drive]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/working-as-intended/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/working-as-intended</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are many legitimate reasons for users to uninstall programs on their computer, such as freeing hard-disk space and lowering CPU overhead. A decade ago, when excessive hard-drive space was a luxury, avid PC gamers would frequently uninstall large, multi-gigabyte games that they were no longer playing in order to make space for new games.</p>

<p>Obviously, developers would prefer that their users not uninstall the software that they spent years creating.  Regardless, developers should ensure that the uninstall process works properly.</p>

<p>Otherwise, a poorly coded PC game uninstaller could delete not just the game, but the <em>entire hard drive</em>. That would be a problem.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Ragnarok</h1>

<p><span class="pull-right" style="padding: 20px"><a href="http://www.penny-arcade.com/comic/1999/01/06"><img src="/img/pennyarcademyth2.jpg" alt="" /></a></span></p>

<p>In late 1998, Bungie (which would later create the <a href="http://www.halowaypoint.com/en-us/">Halo</a> series) released <a href="http://mythipedia.wikia.com/wiki/Myth_II:_Soulblighter">Myth II: Soulblighter</a> for Windows. Myth II, a real-time tactics game, was received with great reception and highly-positive reviews.</p>

<p>But before the worldwide release, a Bungie employee <a href="http://halo.bungie.net/inside/history.aspx?link=juggernougat">uninstalled version 1.0</a> of Myth II, and afterwards, her PC refused to reboot:</p>

<blockquote><p>It was discovered by a very nice young lady in a Japanese office as she worked on the Asian versions of Myth – just as she was trying out the final build. She attempted to uninstall it from the main root folder of her hard drive – not brilliant, but pretty common practice – and perfectly fine for most games. The game proceeded to eat her hard drive like a fresh Bento Box.</p></blockquote>

<p>The Myth II Uninstaller worked by deleting the folder which contained the game files. However, this implementation assumed that the user installed Myth II in the default directory. (i.e. C:\Program Files\Myth II). If the user installed Myth II in a <em>different</em> directory, such as the <em>system root C:\</em>, then when the user uninstalled the game, <strong>all the files in the C drive were deleted.</strong> Boom.</p>

<p>As Bungie later explained <a href="http://www.macobserver.com/news/98/december/981229/bungierecall.html">in a press release</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>In certain unusual cases, using the Uninstaller can cause problems. If a user chooses an installation directory other than the default directory, they should NOT use the Uninstaller but should manually drag the Myth II folder into the Recycle bin and delete it.</p>

<p>Anyone who has the game but has not yet installed it is asked to wait for a new version of the Installer which we will release shortly. If you have already installed the game, there is no harm in playing it, but players should be careful not to use the Uninstall executable. If you have already Uninstalled and not experienced obvious problems, there is nothing to worry about.</p></blockquote>

<p>Calling the potential obliteration of an operating system a &ldquo;problem&rdquo; is an understatement.</p>

<p>Although the issue was not widespread, Bungie decided to do a recall of all Myth II CDs and redistribute a version 1.1, eliminating most of the game&rsquo;s profits in the process.</p>

<p>You could say that the Myth II version 1.0 uninstaller worked exactly as intended: it did indeed uninstall the game. It just worked <em>too</em> well.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>UPDATE October 2014</strong>: A year after this article was posted, someone submitted this article to the Reddit subreddit <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/todayilearned/">todayilearned</a>, where it <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/todayilearned/comments/2ka43x/til_that_in_the_game_myth_ii_soulblighter_due_to/">subsequently went viral</a>. In the comments, Reddit user rdmartell, a <a href="https://www.freelancer.com/u/rdmartell.html">former developer at Bungie</a>, posted more insight into the glitch:</p>

<blockquote><p>So I wrote the Myth TFL installer (not this one). The reason this happened is because you could install other maps and whatnot, and to make the uninstall clean, we had to recursively delete your data folder.
In the sequel, somehow that code (which did sanity checks) was used to delete the applications directory, instead of just the data directory in the applications directory.
So if you installed it on C:/, it would delete everything recursively from there.
Nowadays, uninstall usually leaves any user installed files (like saves or downloaded content) but at the time, as the article suggests, hard drive space was more precious. Also, I wasn&rsquo;t there for this issue, so I don&rsquo;t know the above for sure, but having written the previous installer, I&rsquo;m pretty confident that&rsquo;s what happened.</p></blockquote>

<p>Later in the thread:</p>

<blockquote><p>I actually think the bug was only there if you installed directly to root; not even in a folder. As I recall, that was the only way it deleted your entire HDD.
Unless it was discovered later by going into the uninstalled code that it could happen in other cases (which I never heard about), I think the issue was a bit overblown by the media. Still, the last thing you want to be responsible for is nuking a customer&rsquo;s hard drive.</p></blockquote>

<p>Small world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How MMO Players Proved that the Developers Bugged an Item Drop Rate]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/deep-breaths-more/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-30T23:23:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/deep-breaths-more</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="pull-right" src="/img/globecto.png"></p>

<p><a href="https://www.guildwars2.com/en/">Guild Wars 2</a> is an incredible massively-multiplayer online role-playing game. The goal of Guild Wars 2, developed by ArenaNet, is to save the world, complete quests, and get awesome loot; objectives similar to that of many other MMORPGs such as <a href="http://us.battle.net/wow/en/">World of Warcraft</a>. However, Guild Wars 2 differentiates itself from its spiritual predecessors with its dynamically-changing world, incredible graphics, and the elimination of annoying and tedious time-wasters that have plagued the MMORPG genre.</p>

<p>The best items in Guild Wars 2, naturally, require a large amount of effort and money to obtain. In order to create Legendary weapons, players must obtain large amounts of an item known as Globs of Ectoplasm. Globs of Ectoplasm (abbreviated as &ldquo;Ecto&rdquo;) are obtained randomly when a player salvages a Rare item using a Salvage Kit. Due to their high demand, Ecto effectively serve as a second currency in Guild Wars 2.</p>

<p>Using the best Salvage Kit (that doesn&rsquo;t require paying real-world money), players received, on average, 0.9 Ecto per Rare Item Salvage, a value that has been well-documented and well-tested. But after a patch released a couple days ago, <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/first">players on the Official Guild Wars 2 forums</a> and <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Guildwars2/comments/1fc540/ecto_salvage_rate_bug_being_looked_into_keep_your/">Reddit</a> began to notice that the drop rate for Ecto was <em>much</em> lower, with no mention in the patch notes.</p>

<p>How do you <em>prove</em> something that occurs at random now occurs less frequently?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>What is &ldquo;Random&rdquo;?</h1>

<p>The first rule of any official MMO forum: never accuse the developers of making implicit changes to the game unless you have proof. Such tactics are commonly employed by forum trolls and it makes building a community more difficult.</p>

<p>The second rule of any official MMO forum: never accuse the developers of manipulating probability. As with normal gambling, players can hit a streak of bad luck with loot drops, enemy critical attacks, etc. But the anecdotal data from one player is not sufficient proof of any probability change. (an <a href="http://www.wowwiki.com/Why_does_Onyxia_cast_Deep_Breath%3F">old meme</a> from the World of Warcraft era mocked the userbase&rsquo;s inability to comprehend the definition of random)</p>

<p>On May 28th, a player <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/first">noted on the official GW2 forums</a> that out of 166 salvages, he only received about 80 Ecto, or about 0.5 Ecto/Salvage. This is approximately <em>half</em> of the original rate of 0.9 Ecto/Salvage. Since the rate of new Ecto entering the market was halved with no change in demand, the Auction House <a href="http://www.gw2spidy.com/item/19721">price for Ecto</a> began to steadily rise.</p>

<p><img src="/img/gw2ecto.png"></p>

<p>The price increase in the short-term was not <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/stones-of-jordan/">economy-breaking</a>, but when you need 250 Ectos to create a Legendary weapon in the long-term, it can add up very quickly.</p>

<p>Other players provided their experiences in the thread, with limited results such as &ldquo;noticed this too, yesterday i salvaged 9 rares, got 4 ectos&rdquo; and &ldquo;20 rare at the end of my day, i save them before go bed: 0 ecto. wtf?&rdquo;. Such sample sizes are much too low to satisfy the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_large_numbers">Law of Large Numbers</a> and draw any remotely accurate conclusions.</p>

<p>Regina Buenaobra, ArenaNet Community Manager, eventually <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/page/3#post2115818">responded</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Changes to important things like salvage rates would be listed in the update notes if they have changed. If it’s not in the update notes, then no changes have been made by the development team.</p></blockquote>

<p>So Word of God implies that everyone is wrong. Issue over?</p>

<p>Of course not!</p>

<h1>No Such Thing As Too Much Data</h1>

<p>Despite Regina&rsquo;s dismissal, players continued to post in the thread and began quoting even larger sample sizes, such as a <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/2114853">salvaging 500 Rares</a> resulting in 286 Ectos (0.57 Ecto/Salvage) and <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/page/3#post2116461">salvaging 775 Rares</a> resulting in 402 Ecto (0.52 Ecto/Salvage). With those sample sizes, the probability that the true salvage rate is unchanged from 0.9 Ecto/Salvage is essentially zero.</p>

<p>John Smith, ArenaNet&rsquo;s resident economist, <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/page/4#post2116752">replied</a> that he&rsquo;ll &ldquo;look into this and get back to you.&rdquo; A day later, John made a <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/2122262">promise</a> that &ldquo;if we change anything involving ectos, there will be public information on it.&rdquo; Sure enough, on May 30th, a new patch was released with only <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/info/news/Game-Update-Notes-May-28-2013/2124609">one patch note</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Fixed a salvaging bug introduced in the last patch that sometimes caused salvage kits to yield incorrect results.</p></blockquote>

<p>And that was that, the price of Ecto almost immediately dropped. All was well.</p>

<p>John left one final <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/2124684">message</a>: &ldquo;Thanks to everyone for your help identifying the issue and providing great data for me to start with in my research.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Role-Playing Game With an Easily Exploitable Random Number Generator]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/guaranteed-to-be-random/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-23T20:26:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/guaranteed-to-be-random</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="pull-right" src="/img/GoldenSun.png"></p>

<p>When the Game Boy Advance was released in June 2001, Nintendo promised that the handheld device would be capable of delivering a home gaming console experience on-the-go. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Sun">Golden Sun</a>, developed by Camelot and published by Nintendo a few months after the console&rsquo;s release, exemplified the GBA&rsquo;s full capabilities with its hand-drawn environments, flashy battle effects, and <em>very</em> difficult dungeon puzzles which undoubtedly resulted in the sale of many strategy guides.</p>

<p>In Golden Sun, you play as a group of teenage mages called Adepts, who wield the power of the four elements (Earth, Fire, Wind, and Water) by casting spells with Psynergy. The antagonists of the game are a pair of jerks who are attempting to reawaken a dangerous and sealed power, and only four kids can stop them from destroying the world. Released two years later, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Sun:_The_Lost_Age">Golden Sun: The Lost Age</a> takes place immediately after the conclusion of the first game with a different quartet of Adepts and a new pair of jerks. In this sequel, it is revealed that the jerks who keep trying to kill you are not the bad guys and the whole conflict is just one big misunderstanding! Yes, the plot is very reminiscent of other Japanese-developed RPGs such as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_(video_game)">Final Fantasy</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chrono_Trigger">Chrono Trigger</a>, but it&rsquo;s still impressive for a game I typically played in the backseat of a car.</p>

<p>Like Final Fantasy and Chrono Trigger, Golden Sun has an inventory system where players earn new weapons and items by purchasing them at a store or by finding them as loot from defeating enemies in the world. The most powerful weapons, naturally, only drop from enemies at the end of the game with odds of less than 0.01% per kill. If you killed <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=binomial+distribution%28100%2C1%2F256%29">such enemies 100 times</a>, for example, you would only have a 32% expected chance of seeing a rare drop among all the kills. And killing that many enemies could take hours. It depends on the almighty will of Golden Sun&rsquo;s Random Number Generator.</p>

<p>As it turns out, the <a href="http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Random_Number_Generator">Golden Sun RNG</a> is so poorly implemented that players have found out how to make events with 1/256 probability occur <em>one hundred percent</em> of the time.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>You Make Your Own Luck</h1>

<p><a href="http://xkcd.com/221/"><img src="/img/random_number.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Soon after the first Golden Sun was released, players discovered that the first random enemy encounter the player enters after turning the GBA on was always a First Strike, where the player&rsquo;s party gets a free turn. Was this a cute gameplay mechanic intended to give the player a quick advantage, or was it indicative of a flaw in the game&rsquo;s RNG?</p>

<p>Most modern RNGs are partially seeded and randomized using a timer, i.e. the current time of the computer in microseconds. This makes it infeasable to reproduce the output of the RNG reliably.</p>

<p>However, the GBA does not have an internal clock, so time-based methods of seeding aren&rsquo;t possible. By the time the sequel was released in 2003, the
<a href="http://www.goldensunrealm.com/gs/nickpresta_rng-guide.txt">entire Golden Sun RNG</a> was reverse-engineered:</p>

<blockquote><p>Golden Sun uses the ANSI-C standard rand function as its Pseudo-Random Number
Generator.</p>

<p>There is one difference: Golden Sun&rsquo;s RNG uses an unsigned 4-byte number and
returns it with no shifting, so you&rsquo;d replace &ldquo;return ((next >>16) &amp; 32757);&rdquo;
with &ldquo;return (next &amp; 4294967295);&rdquo;</p>

<p>This, ordinarily, is a perfectly capable RNG, but there is one flaw with what
Golden Sun does with it.</p>

<p>It only makes a new random number when something random happens. What&rsquo;s more,
it uses <em>two</em> copies of the RNG to create two random numbers, and the
first RNG only handles battle situations.</p>

<p>As such, it is easy to control when a new random number is generated.</p>

<p>On top of this, the RNGs are seeded with 0 when the GBA is reset, and because
of the way the game has been programmed, the RNG controlling battle events will
<em>continue</em> to be 0 even when you load the game&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Golden Sun&rsquo;s Random Number Generator isn&rsquo;t &ldquo;random&rdquo; at all. It&rsquo;s manipulated <em>entirely</em> from player-controlled actions, from the moment the Game Boy Advance is turned on.</p>

<h1>Get Lucky</h1>

<p><img src="/img/kiku.png"></p>

<p>One of Golden Sun&rsquo;s contributions to the typical RPG character class customization is the <a href="http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Djinn">Djinn system</a>. In the game lore, Djinn are impish creatures that grant enhanced powers to Adepts. There are four types of Djinn, one for each element, that can be found in the overworld, and each Djinni can be used to either increase a character&rsquo;s statistics, or Unleashed to provide a powerful spell effect. Also, as with many other RPGs, Golden Sun implements an elemental rock-paper-scissors combat system: enemies are weak to an element and resistant to another.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.gamefaqs.com/">GameFAQs</a> forum user by the name of &ldquo;darkpanther&rdquo; discovered that using a Djinn Unleash with an element that is the enemy&rsquo;s weakness will not only increase the amount of Experience and Coins earned, but also <em>quadruple</em> the chance of the enemy dropping a rare item. (this fact is neither hinted anywhere in the game nor stated in any strategy guides)</p>

<p>This is essential toward manipulating the RNG. Normally, the rarest items such as <a href="http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Tisiphone_Edge">Tisiphone Edge</a> and <a href="http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Lachesis%27_Rule">Lachesis' Rule</a> have an &ldquo;Item-Class Chance&rdquo; of 9, meaning the item has a 1/(2<sup>9-1</sup>) = 1/256 chance of dropping per enemy kill. The &ldquo;DP Method&rdquo; decreases the ICC by 2, meaning the new drop rate becomes 1/(2<sup>7-1</sup>) = 1/64. But:</p>

<blockquote><p>As &lsquo;unpredictable&rsquo; as RNGs seem to be, if they are always seeded to the same
value and do not use a timer-based response, they will become predictable by
anyone who is good at noticing patterns. One pattern being, for example, that
the 31st random number that is calculated &ndash; 33727075 &ndash; will drop <em>any</em> item if
the enemy dying when this random number was called was just killed by an
elemental Djinn attack that it is weak to.</p></blockquote>

<p>Calculating the 31st random number would fail against an ICC9 item, but now works against an ICC7 item. (and all items of lower ICC too)</p>

<p>Therefore, <strong>in order to guarantee that an item drops, kill the appropriate enemy with an element-advantage Djinni such that the 30th random number is generated</strong>. (the 31st random number is generated on the enemy&rsquo;s death)</p>

<p>How do you ensure that you only create 31 random numbers? From the Golden Sun Wikia:</p>

<blockquote><p>Save the game and do a hard reset in the area where the monster that drops the item you need appears. Run around to get in a battle. If the encounter consists of a formation of 2 monsters, with at least one of them being the monster you want, proceed. If not, do another hard reset and try again.</p>

<p>During battle, have the entire party use multi-targetting Psynergy on the targets in the first turn, and since a battle right after a hard reset always involve your party attacking first where possible, the monsters will not be able to act. During the second turn, use two multi-targetting Psynergy on the enemies, and have the third party member (or fourth, if one of the three party members that act before uses Defend) unleash an attack Djinni of the element the monster is weak to on the monster. If by this point, the monster flashes in colour and dies, you will obtain the drop of that monster at the end of the battle, however rare it is. If the monster does not die then (either dies too soon or doesn&rsquo;t die by this step), adjust the power of your attacks until you get it just right.</p></blockquote>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/UCJzuSBQ1hU "></iframe></div></p>

<p>Moral of story: if you&rsquo;re making a video game, seed your RNGs with an algorithm that players can&rsquo;t manipulate 100%. Otherwise, hilarity will inevitably ensue. I forgive Camelot for implementing a simplistic RNG though; the two games' <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DaxYYwMqiso&amp;list=PL8C84ECF55B28DC74">awesome</a> <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M31afGXIGpQ&amp;list=PL586792F46D5A35D4&amp;index=13">soundtrack </a> more than makes up for it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Profanity-Laced Video Game Password That Breaks Everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/its-a-livin/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-16T20:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/its-a-livin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="pull-right" src="/img/metroidboxart.jpg"></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a fan of video games, you&rsquo;ve likely heard of the Metroid franchise. Released for the NES in 1986 by Nintendo, Metroid set a new standard for 2-D exploration in video games with its expansive power-up system, well-hidden secrets, and polished platforming controls. Due to its popularity, Metroid has been rereleased multiple times: as an unlockable in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metroid_Prime">Metroid Prime</a>, an unlockable in the remake <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metroid_Zero_Mission">Metroid: Zero Mission</a>, a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classic_NES_Series">standalone game</a> on the Game Boy Advance, the Wii Virtual Console, and the 3DS Virtual Console.</p>

<p>You play as Samus Aran, an armored bounty hunter who has infiltrated the base of the dreaded Space Pirates on Planet Zebes. Samus must defeat the leaders of the Space Pirates: the dinosaur Kraid, the dragon and memetic badass of the series <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridley_(Metroid)">Ridley</a>, and the AI construct <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother_Brain_(Metroid)">Mother Brain</a>. Additionally, Samus must find a way to defeat the Metroids, which are nearly-indestructible parasites that threaten all life. Yes, this was a plot written in the 80&rsquo;s.</p>

<p>Since the NES Metroid cartridge did not have the ability to save games, and the game itself took awhile to complete, Nintendo developed a password system to allow players to continue at a later time. Upon death, the player received a 24-character alphanumeric password that could be entered to restore all items the player has unlocked and remember which bosses the player has defeated. Most of these passwords were gibberish that required a pen-and-paper to write down and remember.</p>

<p>One password, however, is more memorable, and much more sinister.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>The Password is Always Swordfish</h1>

<p>Even before the days of the internet and personal computing, players <a href="http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/List_of_Metroid_passwords">found passwords</a> with unique properties.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/Narpas_Sword">Narpas Sword password</a>:</p>

<p><img src="/img/narpassword.png"></p>

<p>is essentially the debug mode for the game, with all items unlocked, infinite health, and infinite health for Samus.</p>

<p>Another, more revealing password is the <a href="http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/Justin_Bailey">Justin Bailey password</a>:</p>

<p><img src="/img/justinbailey.png"></p>

<p>This password starts the game with most unlockables obtained, but more notably, it changes Samus&rsquo;s sprite from an armored powersuit to a bikini swimsuit.</p>

<p>One password, discovered over 20 years later, long after the Metroid password system had been completely reverse-engineered, does not grant you all items. <em>This</em> password just crashes and resets the game:</p>

<p><img src="/img/engageridley.png"></p>

<h1>WTF?</h1>

<p>On a NES and various other rereleases, inputting that code will cause the game to either simply reset or transform the game into a glitched wonderland:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/x3UyVylP7AI "></iframe></div></p>

<p>But what happens when you enter the password on an emulated Virtual Console, where the game environment is sandboxed? In the case of the 3DS Virtual Console, the <em>3DS completely crashes</em>:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/pjQ7SjB_6a8 "></iframe></div></p>

<h1>Rated E for Everyone?</h1>

<p>You may be asking &ldquo;did someone at Nintendo actually program a consequence for profanity in the game? Is the glitching and crashing a punishment for the perverse player?&rdquo; In truth, the password is merely a coincidence.</p>

<p>As mentioned earlier, the password algorithm for Metroid has been reverse-engineered, and you can actually download a program to both generate and interpret such passwords <a href="http://games.technoplaza.net/mpg/">here</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/img/metroidpassgen.png"></p>

<p>The profane password is indeed a legitimate password (in which Ridley is already defeated, ironically enough). But why does it crash the game? The <a href="http://games.technoplaza.net/mpg/password.txt">Metroid Password Format Guide</a> explains the secret:</p>

<blockquote><p> There are five valid start locations. They are specified using bits 64-66.
  To start in Brinstar, all the bits should be off. Norfair, Kraid&rsquo;s Lair, and
  Ridley&rsquo;s Lair can be specified by turning their bit on and leaving the others
  off. Tourian is specified by turning on Norfair and Kraid&rsquo;s Lair
  simultaneously. Any other combination of these three bits is invalid and will
  cause Metroid to reset.</p>

<p>  The reset bit is part of the start location. There are 16 possible values,
  but only 5 valid ones. Turning on the reset bit will produce and invalid
  start location and cause Metroid to reset. This is why it is called it is
  called the reset bit, because it guarantees an invalid password.</p></blockquote>

<p>For the profane password, the reset bit is turned on, so it will always cause a reset. And that&rsquo;s why the weird behavior happens.</p>

<p>If you manually disable the reset bit using this tool in order to make the password valid, the new password becomes:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/img/metroidpassgen2.png"></p>

<p>Not as catchy, unfortunately.</p>

<p>In fact, the Justin Bailey password is also a completely coincidental password. Sometimes, passwords can just do very unexpected things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
