<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-08T00:29:33-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Universities Produce the Most Successful Startup Founders?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/alma-mater-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-20T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/alma-mater-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you read startup funding announcements on tech blogs frequently, you&rsquo;ve may have noticed that these startup founders have often attended prestigious universities. Founders who have graduated from Ivy League schools, such as Harvard, Yale and Princeton, unsurprisingly raise millions for their startups. Of course, top tier tech schools such as Stanford, MIT, and Carnegie Mellon foster a strong technical and entrepreneurial background: attributes which venture capitalists seek when investing in a startup founder. <em>(Disclosure: I&rsquo;m a Carnegie Mellon alumnus)</em></p>

<p>Do the tech universities produce more funded graduates than the Ivy League universities? Do the founders from Ivy League Universities receive more funding than those from the top tier tech universities?</p>

<p>Using TechCrunch&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.crunchbase.com/">CrunchBase</a> API, I obtained the data of about 2,500 startup founders in the United States who have created a startup which has received investment from venture capitalists.</p>

<p>With that data, I found some rather interesting trends.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Which universities produced the most amount of graduates who have received funding?</h1>

<p>Thousands of university graduates attempt to make a startup, but most will not succeed. Are the graduates of some universities more frequently successful?</p>

<p>Here are the Top 16 universities with the most number of successfully-funded graduates:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/founder-colleges.png"></p>

<p>Stanford has the most amount of funded graduates, which is unsurprising as it&rsquo;s located in the Silicon Valley heart of venture capital.</p>

<p>Seven out of the eight Ivy League Universities (colored green on the chart) are present, but most of the Ivies are  in the middle of the chart. MIT and UC Berkeley each have nearly <em>double</em> the amount of successful graduates from Yale and Columbia.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth noting that Tel Aviv University, an Israeli university, ties Duke University at 21.</p>

<h1>Which university&rsquo;s graduates have cumulatively raised the most amount of total funding?</h1>

<p>Another way to measure success is through the success of the founders&#8217; subsequent startups and the amount of venture capital they have raised.</p>

<p>Here are the Top 8 universities whose graduates have received the most amount of funding:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/sum-funding.png"></p>

<p>Harvard and Stanford graduates are very close in terms of total funding raised. However, there&rsquo;s a clear <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law">Power Law</a> in effect, as those two along with UC Berkeley, have  produced founders who&rsquo;ve generated much, much more venture funding than those of the other universities.</p>

<h1>Which university&rsquo;s graduates raise the most amount of money in their first round of funding on average?</h1>

<p>Startup founders with big, world changing ideas need lots of venture capital. Only the founders with <em>good</em> ideas will actually receive it.</p>

<p>Here are the average amount of first-round funding for the top 16 universities with the most number of successfully-funded graduates:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/avg-first-raised.png"></p>

<p>Carnegie Mellon and Princeton, which had a relatively low number of funded founders and a relatively low number of total capital raised, instead have a <em>significantly</em> higher amount of average first funding. UCLA also placed. Perhaps the students from these three universities tend to have more ambitious startup ideas?</p>

<p>At first glance, Stanford and Harvard appear to be the kings of startups. They have the most amount of graduates, and the most amount of total venture capital raised. The tech blogs would surely consider that a success, but could the greater funding for CMU/Princeton lead to the creation of the next billion-dollar startup? We can only wait and see.</p>

<p><em>UPDATE: As pointed out by robotcookies on the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6075862">corresponding Hacker News thread</a>, I missed UCLA in the first draft, which had 29 funded graduates. The charts have been updated.</em></p>

<hr />

<p>You are welcome to use the founder data from CrunchBase by <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddEV1LUpaQUVsdmJYcERoM0FNU3lPcVE&amp;usp=sharing">viewing the data on Google Drive</a>, or by <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/3jz2wsr4d6fc4t6/founders_w_college.csv">downloading the raw CSV</a>.</p>

<p><em>Notes:</em></p>

<ul>
<li><em>University data was standardized to make analysis easier (e.g. for Carnegie Mellon, the founders who listed their institution as &ldquo;Carnegie Mellon University&rdquo;, &ldquo;Carnegie Mellon,&rdquo; and &ldquo;CMU,&rdquo; all had their institution changed to be &ldquo;CMU&rdquo;.)</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #1 measures unique founders, so it does not double-count a founder who has founded more than one  funded startup.</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #2 assumes equal contribution of each founder to the funding: if a startup has a total funding of $100,000 with 2 founders, the amount used for the chart will be $50,000 for each founder.</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #3 ignores startup data for the chart which has a Series B, Series C, or Series D listed as their first round on CrunchBase, or if the amount raised was not provided.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Statistical Analysis of Medium.com Submissions to Hacker News]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/medium-normal/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-02T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/medium-normal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://medium.com/">Medium</a>, a relatively new startup by Twitter cofounder Evan Williams, is a blog network that emphasizes simplicity and quality above everything else. Writers on the invite-only platform typically post stories about deeply personal topics, such as fighting adversity, never giving up your dreams, changing flawed systems, and other things that make the readers feel happy. One of my favorite articles on Medium, <a href="https://medium.com/editors-picks/57a0128b53c9">Choosing Minecraft Over Disney</a>, describe how a parent&rsquo;s children chose technology over television.</p>

<p>As of recently, the frequency of links to Medium posts on the popular tech-oriented link aggregator <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news">Hacker News</a> has been increasing at an alarming rate. Since Medium&rsquo;s tales of triumph appeal to the ambitious entrepreneurs and startup founders of HN, the submissions are usually rapidly upvoted and easily make the front page, with  muted text helpfully noting that the link goes to medium.com. As a result, there has been <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5968593">cognitive</a> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5974209">dissonance</a> on Hacker News whether Medium has too strong a presence on the aggregator, or worse,  potentially gaming the system.</p>

<p>Using the <a href="https://www.hnsearch.com/api">HNSearch API</a>, I analyzed the submissions of links under the medium.com domain to Hacker News to see just how Medium keeps surging in popularity. The results, as always, are very revealing.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The collected data is a sample of 1,000 links (out of 1,355 total) submitted to Hacker News under the medium.com domain.  Each data point contains the Title of the article, the HN user who submitted it, the amount of upvotes it received, the time it was posted (in PST), and links to both the article and the HN comments thread for reference. You can view the <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddDBPNFlMQUYyX1FhUkVVY2g1TmVLM1E&amp;usp=sharing">data on Google Drive</a>, or download <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/xnktwi9kheyqf6v/medium.csv">the raw CSV</a> and play with the data yourself.</p>

<p>What does the data tell us about Medium?</p>

<hr />

<h1>How quickly has medium.com grown in popularity in the past few months?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-month.png"></p>

<p>Medium was launched <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/08/01/medium-obvious/">in August 2012</a>, and received relatively little attention as evidenced by the graph. But 8 months later, the frequency of medium.com submissions hockey-sticked, receiving almost 5x growth from March 2013 to April 2013. That certainly explains one of the reasons why the rise in medium.com links is just being noticed now.</p>

<hr />

<h1>When are medium.com posts being written and submitted to HN?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-by-hour.png"></p>

<p>The time of day a blog post is submitted makes all the difference in the world, especially if your blog platform targets readers in a specific region. Medium links are frequently posted and submitted around 10am PST / 1pm EST, which is smart as it&rsquo;s relatively early in the day for those living in the United States, and your potential readers would be more likely to read your post, and HN users are more likely to upvote.</p>

<hr />

<h1>Who are the Hacker News users who most frequently submit medium.com articles?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-top-submitters.png"></p>

<p>Of the 1,000 submissions, there were only 622 unique submitters of medium.com links, each submitting an average of 1.61 posts. Most only post their own articles, but others, like <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=rpsubhub">rpsubhub</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=mrbird">mrbird</a>, and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=nvk">nvk</a> submit Medium.com links more often. However, none of those users appear to be associated with Medium; they just submit links rather frequently.</p>

<hr />

<h1>What are the types of articles on medium.com submitted to Hacker News?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-wordcloud.png"></p>

<p>Medium&rsquo;s category system is somewhat obtuse, so I parsed the keywords from the titles of the submissions (using a method similar to <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data/">my last post</a>) in order to get an idea what type of content is submitted most from Medium. There are lots of posts that ask rhetorical questions (<strong>What?</strong>, <strong>How?</strong>, <strong>Why?</strong>), and even more posts about the personal self with <strong>I</strong>. Not only is Medium using the right language to facilitate interaction, it&rsquo;s also hitting the interests of HNers with keywords such as <strong>Design</strong> and <strong>Facebook</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h1>How successful <em>are</em> medium.com articles on Hacker News?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-front-page.png"></p>

<p>Out of the 1,000 submissions, only 158 had atleast 10 upvotes, which is enough to get the link to the front page, but not necessarily enough to keep it there. The graph is heavily right-skewed, with only 38 submissions getting above 100 points. It shows that medium.com links so not guarantee success, and even if you hit the front page, you have a low chance of hitting the coveted #1 ranking.</p>

<hr />

<p>Medium is definitely growing. HN is receiving more and more submissions which appeal to the average HN user, and posts are being submitted at all hours of the day. However, having a post at medium.com is not a panacea that will make your blog post be seen by thousands of people; you still need to write something interesting.</p>

<p>Time will tell. But if HN does indeed get bored of Medium, I believe the problem will correct itself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Predicting the Number of Likes on a Facebook Status With Statistical Keyword Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What makes people click the Like button on Facebook Statuses? Does the status say something funny? Does it contain a cool link or a funny photo? Does the status actively engage its readers?</p>

<p>Needless to say, brands on Facebook want to know the answers to these questions. The more people that Like their statuses on their Facebook Pages, the more exposure they gain, and the more money they earn. Many, many companies have been created for the sole purpose of maximizing the number of Facebook Likes.</p>

<p>By 2013, most brands have realized that photo posts and statuses that ask a question <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/questions-equals-reponses/">will generate <em>much</em> higher numbers</a> of Likes. Personally, that&rsquo;s not why <em>I</em> like a given Facebook status: I Like statuses that contain new and exciting things that are relevant to my interests. The first thing I read in a status is the Message: if the message is boring and uninteresting, then there&rsquo;s no reason for me to Like the status needlessly.</p>

<p>Can the keywords and language in a Facebook Status predict the number of Likes the status receives?</p>

<p>Running multivariate regressions on keywords from thousands of Facebook statuses, I&rsquo;ve discovered that the language used in a status <em>does</em> help predict the number of Likes a status receives, and actually could help brands learn much more about their fans.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Setup</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/rdataset.png"></p>

<p>In order to draw accurate conclusions from the analysis, large amounts of data are needed (and there&rsquo;s no such thing as too much data).</p>

<p>I decided to analyze the Facebook Pages of 3 extremely popular News sources: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cnn">CNN</a>, the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/nytimes">New York Times</a>, and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/bbcworldnews">BBC World News</a>. All three Pages have millions of fans, post the same types of Facebook statuses, and post statuses extremely frequently to Facebook (around 8-9 times a day). The statuses analyzed will be from June 1st 2012 to June 1st 2013, in order to both gather a large sample size (~3,000  statuses from each Page) and a ensure a consistent apples-to-apples comparison between the three sources.</p>

<p>The raw data, code, and a detailed technical explanation of the statistical techniques used to process the data can be found in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-keyword-regression-analysis">this GitHub repository</a>. (tl;dr, it&rsquo;s an optimized <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Least_squares">least squares</a> regression)</p>

<p><em>Can the keywords and language in a Facebook Status predict the number of Likes the status receives?</em> We&rsquo;re ready to test this hypothesis.</p>

<hr />

<h1>CNN</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/cnn_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Bourdain        1962.98         0
NEWS            1272.64         0
Photo           1154.6          0
Barack          1002.45         0
City            851.82          0
Monday          705.42          0
Obama           632.2           0
United          578.77          0
Mitt            562.29          0.01
South           508.43          0.03
America         505.83          0.01
Watch           470.51          0
Boston          398.13          0.05
New             326.74          0.03
ET              -433.96         0
North           -467.05         0.02
Check           -503.5          0
Travel          -988.99         0.02
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for CNN are political keywords.</li>
<li><strong>NEWS</strong> (&ldquo;BREAKING NEWS&rdquo;) predicts more Likes than <strong>Photo</strong> (i.e. <a href="http://www.facebook.com/5550296508/posts/10151626042186509">Travel Photo of the Day</a>).</li>
<li><strong>Bourdain</strong> refers to Anthony Bourdain, who very recently began <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Bourdain:_Parts_Unknown">a food and travel show</a> on CNN. I assume that targets CNN&rsquo;s primary demographic.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Barack</strong> (Barack Obama) predicts more likes than just <strong>Obama</strong>.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Monday</strong> predicts more likes most other keywords. Garfield would be disappointed.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>North</strong> (North Korea) predicts a <em>decrease</em> in Likes from the average. Is North Korea boring?</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Check</strong> (&ldquo;Check this out!&rdquo;) also predicts a decrease in Likes from the average. This is interesting because this call-to-action is usually associated with the other keywords. Perhaps it&rsquo;s not necessary?</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h1>NYTimes</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/nytimes_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Mills           1022.9          0
Democratic      496.32          0
Krugman         456.31          0
Senate          431.05          0
London          373.67          0.01
Oscar           367.64          0.01
Sandy           364.61          0
Olympics        339.15          0.01
Sunday          317             0
Clinton         314.64          0.02
You             247.07          0
Obama           237.98          0
Opinion         221             0
Michael         204.2           0.03
Credit          191.92          0.05
Tuesday         187.22          0.03
Times           178.69          0
See             160.12          0.01
Romney          157.66          0.04
Ed              140.86          0.01
Read            -101.23         0.05
Here            -182.72         0.04
Facebook        -187.75         0.02
Are             -216.3          0.01
While           -293.77         0.04
Quotation       -322.29         0.02
House           -362.1          0.01
Thanksgiving    -369.88         0.05
Convention      -448.34         0.01
Jersey          -505.98         0
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for NYTimes are political keywords and current events, such as Hurricane <strong>Sandy</strong> and the <strong>London</strong> <strong>Olympics</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Mills</strong> refers to Doug Mills, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/5281959998/posts/10150252479219999">photographer</a> for the New York Times. The power of photos!</li>
<li><strong>You</strong> and <strong>See</strong> are impactful call-to-action keywords, even though they don&rsquo;t ask any questions. (Interestingly, <strong>Are</strong>, which implicitly asks a question, predicts a decrease in Likes. Maybe people don&rsquo;t Like questions?)</li>
<li><strong>Clinton</strong> has a bigger impact than <strong>Obama</strong>.</li>
<li>No one likes <strong>Jersey</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h1>BBC World News</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/bbcworldnews_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Malala          488.1           0
Japan           186.32          0
Britain         167.25          0.01
That            155.01          0.01
AFP             154.97          0.02
Travel          153.41          0
Now             148.39          0.02
Would           146.45          0.03
Delhi           137.85          0.04
Let             134.93          0.03
Future          127.49          0.02
Barack          125.79          0.02
An              122.18          0.03
David           111.78          0.04
Do              111.13          0
Israel          101.31          0.04
Impact          87.94           0.05
South           78.62           0.03
It              62.7            0.01
The             55.7            0
US              -47.84          0.02
On              -86.22          0.04
BBC             -103.58         0
Sunday          -117.01         0.03
After           -122.38         0.05
Thursday        -143.91         0.03
Twitter         -144.55         0
City            -147.16         0.02
Hi              -149.85         0.03
BBCNewsUS       -150.48         0.03
House           -176.86         0.01
California      -187.57         0
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for BBC World News are keywords describing news around the world. Unlike CNN and NYTimes, there are very few impactful keywords related to domestic politics (such as Prime Minister <strong>David</strong> Cameron, and even <strong>Barack</strong> is more impactful than him.)</li>
<li><strong>Malala</strong> refers to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malala_Yousafzai">Malala Youdsfzai</a>, a Pakistani activist who survived an assassination attempt.</li>
<li>Implicit question keywords such as <strong>Let</strong>, <strong>Do</strong>, and <strong>Would</strong> are all very effective.</li>
<li>The simple salutation of <strong>Hi</strong> predicts a decrease in Likes. There&rsquo;s a British joke here somewhere.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p>The language used in Facebook Statuses can be very useful in identifying what words Fans like, and what words will be most useful in generating the most exposure. While my analysis can&rsquo;t predict the <em>exact</em> number of Likes a Status receives, and I likely <a href="http://xkcd.com/882/">broke a few rules of statistics</a> in the process of making this post, the impact of language and specific keywords on social media interaction is an endeavor worth pursuing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook Hashtags Are Fundamentally Broken]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/hashtag-hashtag/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-14T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/hashtag-hashtag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/">Facebook</a> added <a href="http://newsroom.fb.com/News/633/Public-Conversations-on-Facebook">searchable hashtags</a> to all status updates and user comments. As with <a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a>, whenever a Facebook user posts an status with a #hashtag, that hashtag becomes clickable and leads to a News Feed of all other publically-visible posts with that hashtag.</p>

<p>The implementation of hashtags in Facebook is an obvious move. Advertisements and television shows display hashtags all the time to encourage users to Tweet about them: it&rsquo;s free marketing, after all. Facebook can piggy-back off those already-existing hashtags and grow user adoption <em>very</em> quickly, especially with Facebook-owned <a href="http://instagram.com/">Instagram</a> already supporting hashtags.</p>

<p>However, Facebook is a fundamentally different social network than Twitter. While Twitter uses hashtags to quickly categorize a feed of 140-character thoughts, Facebook&rsquo;s content feeds  typically consist of long posts and large images. Additionally, while posts on Twitter are explicitly public or private, Facebook&rsquo;s privacy settings are more granular: if users don&rsquo;t make their posts Public, the hashtag is essentially useless. And the brands are going to <em>love</em> hashtags. Maybe too much.</p>

<p>The magic of Facebook is flat-out incompatible with the magic of hashtags.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Too Long; Didn&rsquo;t Read</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/facebooktwitter.png"></p>

<p>Since Twitter posts have a length limit, they&rsquo;re short and occupy a consistent amount of space on the webpage. Facebook posts can be near-unlimited length, utilize a large amount of a white space between posts, and also potentially contain an equally-long comment section. As a result, 5 Twitter posts can use the same amount of screen real-estate as 2 Facebook posts. Given the already incredibly low signal-to-noise quality ratio of #hashtag feeds (as evident above), this makes reading hashtag feeds on Facebook a chore.</p>

<h2>A Thousand Words Takes A Lot Of Space</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/bieber-twitter.png"></p>

<p>Facebook displays pictures embedded in posts natively in the feed, while Twitter requires the user to click the Tweet to see the photo. In this case, the ratio of Twitter:Facebook posts can be even worse, in this case 6 Twitter posts for 1 Facebook post.</p>

<h2>If A Hashtag Isn&rsquo;t Seen, Was It Posted?</h2>

<p>Twitter is opt-in private posting. Facebook is opt-<em>out</em> private posting. That&rsquo;s a big usability problem.</p>

<p>The Facebook hashtag feeds only show posts that are explicitly  made Public (or posts from your Friends which are set to a privacy of Friends Only). If the user is unaware that their posts are not Public by default, then their posts containing the hashtag will never be seen and the user won&rsquo;t be able to participate in social hashtag feeds.  Although Facebook has made improvements in helping users set the intended privacy level of a post, it makes the process of posting much more deliberate and much less impulsive than Twitter.</p>

<h2>#brand #branding #marketing #yolo #swag</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hashtagabuse.png"></p>

<p>Brands love hashtags. The more hashtags included in a Tweet, the more exposure the Tweet receives, right?</p>

<p>With Twitter, there&rsquo;s a limit on the number of hashtags in a Tweet due to the delicate balance between the number of hashtags, the length of the hashtags, and the length of the Tweet itself. On Facebook, you can include <strong>25</strong> hashtags in any post!</p>

<p>Since there&rsquo;s no consequence for abusing hashtags, expect to see more Facebook brands taking advantage this new free source of marketing. Expect to see Facebook get much more cluttered.</p>

<h2>Explicit Image Bombing</h2>

<p>A malicious user could theoretically insert shock images into popular hashtag feeds. During my testing of Facebook hashtags, there was a surprising amount of nudity in the seemingly-innocuous #many hashtag.</p>

<p>On Twitter, the volume of Tweets is much higher and the images are hidden by default, so the odds of such an attack working on Facebook are much higher than on Twitter.</p>

<h2>Comment Hashtags Different From Post Hashtags</h2>

<p>You can hashtag comments on Facebook posts like you can hashtag Facebook posts themselves. But hashtagged comments won&rsquo;t appear in the hashtag News Feed. Whereas on Twitter, Replies are also Tweets and can be hashtagged accordingly. This behavior isn&rsquo;t surprising, but it&rsquo;s still a big inconsistency.</p>

<hr />

<p>Will Facebook Hashtags fail due to the massive differences between Facebook and Twitter? It&rsquo;s hard to say, but I&rsquo;m skeptical that Facebook will be able to capture the hashtag magic.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When Uninstalling A PC Game Erases the Entire Hard Drive]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/working-as-intended/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/working-as-intended</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are many legitimate reasons for users to uninstall programs on their computer, such as freeing hard-disk space and lowering CPU overhead. A decade ago, when excessive hard-drive space was a luxury, avid PC gamers would frequently uninstall large, multi-gigabyte games that they were no longer playing in order to make space for new games.</p>

<p>Obviously, developers would prefer that their users not uninstall the software that they spent years creating.  Regardless, developers should ensure that the uninstall process works properly.</p>

<p>Otherwise, a poorly coded PC game uninstaller could delete not just the game, but the <em>entire hard drive</em>. That would be a problem.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Ragnarok</h1>

<p><span class="pull-right" style="padding: 20px"><a href="http://www.penny-arcade.com/comic/1999/01/06"><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/pennyarcademyth2.jpg" alt="" /></a></span></p>

<p>In late 1998, Bungie (which would later create the <a href="http://www.halowaypoint.com/en-us/">Halo</a> series) released <a href="http://mythipedia.wikia.com/wiki/Myth_II:_Soulblighter">Myth II: Soulblighter</a> for Windows. Myth II, a real-time tactics game, was received with great reception and highly-positive reviews.</p>

<p>But before the worldwide release, a Bungie employee <a href="http://halo.bungie.net/inside/history.aspx?link=juggernougat">uninstalled version 1.0</a> of Myth II, and afterwards, her PC refused to reboot:</p>

<blockquote><p>It was discovered by a very nice young lady in a Japanese office as she worked on the Asian versions of Myth – just as she was trying out the final build. She attempted to uninstall it from the main root folder of her hard drive – not brilliant, but pretty common practice – and perfectly fine for most games. The game proceeded to eat her hard drive like a fresh Bento Box.</p></blockquote>

<p>The Myth II Uninstaller worked by deleting the folder which contained the game files. However, this implementation assumed that the user installed Myth II in the default directory. (i.e. C:\Program Files\Myth II). If the user installed Myth II in a <em>different</em> directory, such as the <em>system root C:\</em>, then when the user uninstalled the game, <strong>all the files in the C drive were deleted.</strong> Boom.</p>

<p>As Bungie later explained <a href="http://www.macobserver.com/news/98/december/981229/bungierecall.html">in a press release</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>In certain unusual cases, using the Uninstaller can cause problems. If a user chooses an installation directory other than the default directory, they should NOT use the Uninstaller but should manually drag the Myth II folder into the Recycle bin and delete it.</p>

<p>Anyone who has the game but has not yet installed it is asked to wait for a new version of the Installer which we will release shortly. If you have already installed the game, there is no harm in playing it, but players should be careful not to use the Uninstall executable. If you have already Uninstalled and not experienced obvious problems, there is nothing to worry about.</p></blockquote>

<p>Calling the potential obliteration of an operating system a &ldquo;problem&rdquo; is an understatement.</p>

<p>Although the issue was not widespread, Bungie decided to do a recall of all Myth II CDs and redistribute a version 1.1, eliminating most of the game&rsquo;s profits in the process.</p>

<p>You could say that the Myth II version 1.0 uninstaller worked exactly as intended: it did indeed uninstall the game. It just worked <em>too</em> well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How MMO Players Proved that the Developers Bugged an Item Drop Rate]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/deep-breaths-more/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-30T23:23:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/deep-breaths-more</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="pull-right" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/globecto.png"></p>

<p><a href="https://www.guildwars2.com/en/">Guild Wars 2</a> is an incredible massively-multiplayer online role-playing game. The goal of Guild Wars 2, developed by ArenaNet, is to save the world, complete quests, and get awesome loot; objectives similar to that of many other MMORPGs such as <a href="http://us.battle.net/wow/en/">World of Warcraft</a>. However, Guild Wars 2 differentiates itself from its spiritual predecessors with its dynamically-changing world, incredible graphics, and the elimination of annoying and tedious time-wasters that have plagued the MMORPG genre.</p>

<p>The best items in Guild Wars 2, naturally, require a large amount of effort and money to obtain. In order to create Legendary weapons, players must obtain large amounts of an item known as Globs of Ectoplasm. Globs of Ectoplasm (abbreviated as &ldquo;Ecto&rdquo;) are obtained randomly when a player salvages a Rare item using a Salvage Kit. Due to their high demand, Ecto effectively serve as a second currency in Guild Wars 2.</p>

<p>Using the best Salvage Kit (that doesn&rsquo;t require paying real-world money), players received, on average, 0.9 Ecto per Rare Item Salvage, a value that has been well-documented and well-tested. But after a patch released a couple days ago, <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/first">players on the Official Guild Wars 2 forums</a> and <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Guildwars2/comments/1fc540/ecto_salvage_rate_bug_being_looked_into_keep_your/">Reddit</a> began to notice that the drop rate for Ecto was <em>much</em> lower, with no mention in the patch notes.</p>

<p>How do you <em>prove</em> something that occurs at random now occurs less frequently?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>What is &ldquo;Random&rdquo;?</h1>

<p>The first rule of any official MMO forum: never accuse the developers of making implicit changes to the game unless you have proof. Such tactics are commonly employed by forum trolls and it makes building a community more difficult.</p>

<p>The second rule of any official MMO forum: never accuse the developers of manipulating probability. As with normal gambling, players can hit a streak of bad luck with loot drops, enemy critical attacks, etc. But the anecdotal data from one player is not sufficient proof of any probability change. (an <a href="http://www.wowwiki.com/Why_does_Onyxia_cast_Deep_Breath%3F">old meme</a> from the World of Warcraft era mocked the userbase&rsquo;s inability to comprehend the definition of random)</p>

<p>On May 28th, a player <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/first">noted on the official GW2 forums</a> that out of 166 salvages, he only received about 80 Ecto, or about 0.5 Ecto/Salvage. This is approximately <em>half</em> of the original rate of 0.9 Ecto/Salvage. Since the rate of new Ecto entering the market was halved with no change in demand, the Auction House <a href="http://www.gw2spidy.com/item/19721">price for Ecto</a> began to steadily rise.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/gw2ecto.png"></p>

<p>The price increase in the short-term was not <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/stones-of-jordan/">economy-breaking</a>, but when you need 250 Ectos to create a Legendary weapon in the long-term, it can add up very quickly.</p>

<p>Other players provided their experiences in the thread, with limited results such as &ldquo;noticed this too, yesterday i salvaged 9 rares, got 4 ectos&rdquo; and &ldquo;20 rare at the end of my day, i save them before go bed: 0 ecto. wtf?&rdquo;. Such sample sizes are much too low to satisfy the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_large_numbers">Law of Large Numbers</a> and draw any remotely accurate conclusions.</p>

<p>Regina Buenaobra, ArenaNet Community Manager, eventually <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/page/3#post2115818">responded</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Changes to important things like salvage rates would be listed in the update notes if they have changed. If it’s not in the update notes, then no changes have been made by the development team.</p></blockquote>

<p>So Word of God implies that everyone is wrong. Issue over?</p>

<p>Of course not!</p>

<h1>No Such Thing As Too Much Data</h1>

<p>Despite Regina&rsquo;s dismissal, players continued to post in the thread and began quoting even larger sample sizes, such as a <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/2114853">salvaging 500 Rares</a> resulting in 286 Ectos (0.57 Ecto/Salvage) and <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/page/3#post2116461">salvaging 775 Rares</a> resulting in 402 Ecto (0.52 Ecto/Salvage). With those sample sizes, the probability that the true salvage rate is unchanged from 0.9 Ecto/Salvage is essentially zero.</p>

<p>John Smith, ArenaNet&rsquo;s resident economist, <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/page/4#post2116752">replied</a> that he&rsquo;ll &ldquo;look into this and get back to you.&rdquo; A day later, John made a <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/2122262">promise</a> that &ldquo;if we change anything involving ectos, there will be public information on it.&rdquo; Sure enough, on May 30th, a new patch was released with only <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/info/news/Game-Update-Notes-May-28-2013/2124609">one patch note</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Fixed a salvaging bug introduced in the last patch that sometimes caused salvage kits to yield incorrect results.</p></blockquote>

<p>And that was that, the price of Ecto almost immediately dropped. All was well.</p>

<p>John left one final <a href="https://forum-en.guildwars2.com/forum/game/gw2/Changes-to-ecto-salvage-from-rares/2124684">message</a>: &ldquo;Thanks to everyone for your help identifying the issue and providing great data for me to start with in my research.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Role-Playing Game With an Easily Exploitable Random Number Generator]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/guaranteed-to-be-random/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-23T20:26:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/guaranteed-to-be-random</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="pull-right" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/GoldenSun.png"></p>

<p>When the Game Boy Advance was released in June 2001, Nintendo promised that the handheld device would be capable of delivering a home gaming console experience on-the-go. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Sun">Golden Sun</a>, developed by Camelot and published by Nintendo a few months after the console&rsquo;s release, exemplified the GBA&rsquo;s full capabilities with its hand-drawn environments, flashy battle effects, and <em>very</em> difficult dungeon puzzles which undoubtedly resulted in the sale of many strategy guides.</p>

<p>In Golden Sun, you play as a group of teenage mages called Adepts, who wield the power of the four elements (Earth, Fire, Wind, and Water) by casting spells with Psynergy. The antagonists of the game are a pair of jerks who are attempting to reawaken a dangerous and sealed power, and only four kids can stop them from destroying the world. Released two years later, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Sun:_The_Lost_Age">Golden Sun: The Lost Age</a> takes place immediately after the conclusion of the first game with a different quartet of Adepts and a new pair of jerks. In this sequel, it is revealed that the jerks who keep trying to kill you are not the bad guys and the whole conflict is just one big misunderstanding! Yes, the plot is very reminiscent of other Japanese-developed RPGs such as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_(video_game)">Final Fantasy</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chrono_Trigger">Chrono Trigger</a>, but it&rsquo;s still impressive for a game I typically played in the backseat of a car.</p>

<p>Like Final Fantasy and Chrono Trigger, Golden Sun has an inventory system where players earn new weapons and items by purchasing them at a store or by finding them as loot from defeating enemies in the world. The most powerful weapons, naturally, only drop from enemies at the end of the game with odds of less than 0.01% per kill. If you killed <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=binomial+distribution%28100%2C1%2F256%29">such enemies 100 times</a>, for example, you would only have a 32% expected chance of seeing a rare drop among all the kills. And killing that many enemies could take hours. It depends on the almighty will of Golden Sun&rsquo;s Random Number Generator.</p>

<p>As it turns out, the <a href="http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Random_Number_Generator">Golden Sun RNG</a> is so poorly implemented that players have found out how to make events with 1/256 probability occur <em>one hundred percent</em> of the time.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>You Make Your Own Luck</h1>

<p><a href="http://xkcd.com/221/"><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/random_number.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Soon after the first Golden Sun was released, players discovered that the first random enemy encounter the player enters after turning the GBA on was always a First Strike, where the player&rsquo;s party gets a free turn. Was this a cute gameplay mechanic intended to give the player a quick advantage, or was it indicative of a flaw in the game&rsquo;s RNG?</p>

<p>Most modern RNGs are partially seeded and randomized using a timer, i.e. the current time of the computer in microseconds. This makes it infeasable to reproduce the output of the RNG reliably.</p>

<p>However, the GBA does not have an internal clock, so time-based methods of seeding aren&rsquo;t possible. By the time the sequel was released in 2003, the
<a href="http://www.goldensunrealm.com/gs/nickpresta_rng-guide.txt">entire Golden Sun RNG</a> was reverse-engineered:</p>

<blockquote><p>Golden Sun uses the ANSI-C standard rand function as its Pseudo-Random Number
Generator.</p>

<p>There is one difference: Golden Sun&rsquo;s RNG uses an unsigned 4-byte number and
returns it with no shifting, so you&rsquo;d replace &ldquo;return ((next >>16) &amp; 32757);&rdquo;
with &ldquo;return (next &amp; 4294967295);&rdquo;</p>

<p>This, ordinarily, is a perfectly capable RNG, but there is one flaw with what
Golden Sun does with it.</p>

<p>It only makes a new random number when something random happens. What&rsquo;s more,
it uses <em>two</em> copies of the RNG to create two random numbers, and the
first RNG only handles battle situations.</p>

<p>As such, it is easy to control when a new random number is generated.</p>

<p>On top of this, the RNGs are seeded with 0 when the GBA is reset, and because
of the way the game has been programmed, the RNG controlling battle events will
<em>continue</em> to be 0 even when you load the game&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Golden Sun&rsquo;s Random Number Generator isn&rsquo;t &ldquo;random&rdquo; at all. It&rsquo;s manipulated <em>entirely</em> from player-controlled actions, from the moment the Game Boy Advance is turned on.</p>

<h1>Get Lucky</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/kiku.png"></p>

<p>One of Golden Sun&rsquo;s contributions to the typical RPG character class customization is the <a href="http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Djinn">Djinn system</a>. In the game lore, Djinn are impish creatures that grant enhanced powers to Adepts. There are four types of Djinn, one for each element, that can be found in the overworld, and each Djinni can be used to either increase a character&rsquo;s statistics, or Unleashed to provide a powerful spell effect. Also, as with many other RPGs, Golden Sun implements an elemental rock-paper-scissors combat system: enemies are weak to an element and resistant to another.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.gamefaqs.com/">GameFAQs</a> forum user by the name of &ldquo;darkpanther&rdquo; discovered that using a Djinn Unleash with an element that is the enemy&rsquo;s weakness will not only increase the amount of Experience and Coins earned, but also <em>quadruple</em> the chance of the enemy dropping a rare item. (this fact is neither hinted anywhere in the game nor stated in any strategy guides)</p>

<p>This is essential toward manipulating the RNG. Normally, the rarest items such as <a href="http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Tisiphone_Edge">Tisiphone Edge</a> and <a href="http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Lachesis%27_Rule">Lachesis&#8217; Rule</a> have an &ldquo;Item-Class Chance&rdquo; of 9, meaning the item has a 1/(2<sup>9-1</sup>) = 1/256 chance of dropping per enemy kill. The &ldquo;DP Method&rdquo; decreases the ICC by 2, meaning the new drop rate becomes 1/(2<sup>7-1</sup>) = 1/64. But:</p>

<blockquote><p>As &lsquo;unpredictable&rsquo; as RNGs seem to be, if they are always seeded to the same
value and do not use a timer-based response, they will become predictable by
anyone who is good at noticing patterns. One pattern being, for example, that
the 31st random number that is calculated &ndash; 33727075 &ndash; will drop <em>any</em> item if
the enemy dying when this random number was called was just killed by an
elemental Djinn attack that it is weak to.</p></blockquote>

<p>Calculating the 31st random number would fail against an ICC9 item, but now works against an ICC7 item. (and all items of lower ICC too)</p>

<p>Therefore, <strong>in order to guarantee that an item drops, kill the appropriate enemy with an element-advantage Djinni such that the 30th random number is generated</strong>. (the 31st random number is generated on the enemy&rsquo;s death)</p>

<p>How do you ensure that you only create 31 random numbers? From the Golden Sun Wikia:</p>

<blockquote><p>Save the game and do a hard reset in the area where the monster that drops the item you need appears. Run around to get in a battle. If the encounter consists of a formation of 2 monsters, with at least one of them being the monster you want, proceed. If not, do another hard reset and try again.</p>

<p>During battle, have the entire party use multi-targetting Psynergy on the targets in the first turn, and since a battle right after a hard reset always involve your party attacking first where possible, the monsters will not be able to act. During the second turn, use two multi-targetting Psynergy on the enemies, and have the third party member (or fourth, if one of the three party members that act before uses Defend) unleash an attack Djinni of the element the monster is weak to on the monster. If by this point, the monster flashes in colour and dies, you will obtain the drop of that monster at the end of the battle, however rare it is. If the monster does not die then (either dies too soon or doesn&rsquo;t die by this step), adjust the power of your attacks until you get it just right.</p></blockquote>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/UCJzuSBQ1hU "></iframe></div>


<p>Moral of story: if you&rsquo;re making a video game, seed your RNGs with an algorithm that players can&rsquo;t manipulate 100%. Otherwise, hilarity will inevitably ensue. I forgive Camelot for implementing a simplistic RNG though; the two games&#8217; <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DaxYYwMqiso&amp;list=PL8C84ECF55B28DC74">awesome</a> <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M31afGXIGpQ&amp;list=PL586792F46D5A35D4&amp;index=13">soundtrack </a> more than makes up for it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Profanity-Laced Video Game Password That Breaks Everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/its-a-livin/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-16T20:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/its-a-livin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="pull-right" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/metroidboxart.jpg"></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a fan of video games, you&rsquo;ve likely heard of the Metroid franchise. Released for the NES in 1986 by Nintendo, Metroid set a new standard for 2-D exploration in video games with its expansive power-up system, well-hidden secrets, and polished platforming controls. Due to its popularity, Metroid has been rereleased multiple times: as an unlockable in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metroid_Prime">Metroid Prime</a>, an unlockable in the remake <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metroid_Zero_Mission">Metroid: Zero Mission</a>, a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classic_NES_Series">standalone game</a> on the Game Boy Advance, the Wii Virtual Console, and the 3DS Virtual Console.</p>

<p>You play as Samus Aran, an armored bounty hunter who has infiltrated the base of the dreaded Space Pirates on Planet Zebes. Samus must defeat the leaders of the Space Pirates: the dinosaur Kraid, the dragon and memetic badass of the series <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridley_(Metroid)">Ridley</a>, and the AI construct <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother_Brain_(Metroid)">Mother Brain</a>. Additionally, Samus must find a way to defeat the Metroids, which are nearly-indestructible parasites that threaten all life. Yes, this was a plot written in the 80&rsquo;s.</p>

<p>Since the NES Metroid cartridge did not have the ability to save games, and the game itself took awhile to complete, Nintendo developed a password system to allow players to continue at a later time. Upon death, the player received a 24-character alphanumeric password that could be entered to restore all items the player has unlocked and remember which bosses the player has defeated. Most of these passwords were gibberish that required a pen-and-paper to write down and remember.</p>

<p>One password, however, is more memorable, and much more sinister.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>The Password is Always Swordfish</h1>

<p>Even before the days of the internet and personal computing, players <a href="http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/List_of_Metroid_passwords">found passwords</a> with unique properties.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/Narpas_Sword">Narpas Sword password</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/narpassword.png"></p>

<p>is essentially the debug mode for the game, with all items unlocked, infinite health, and infinite health for Samus.</p>

<p>Another, more revealing password is the <a href="http://metroid.wikia.com/wiki/Justin_Bailey">Justin Bailey password</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/justinbailey.png"></p>

<p>This password starts the game with most unlockables obtained, but more notably, it changes Samus&rsquo;s sprite from an armored powersuit to a bikini swimsuit.</p>

<p>One password, discovered over 20 years later, long after the Metroid password system had been completely reverse-engineered, does not grant you all items. <em>This</em> password just crashes and resets the game:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/engageridley.png"></p>

<h1>WTF?</h1>

<p>On a NES and various other rereleases, inputting that code will cause the game to either simply reset or transform the game into a glitched wonderland:</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/x3UyVylP7AI "></iframe></div>


<p>But what happens when you enter the password on an emulated Virtual Console, where the game environment is sandboxed? In the case of the 3DS Virtual Console, the <em>3DS completely crashes</em>:</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/pjQ7SjB_6a8 "></iframe></div>


<h1>Rated E for Everyone?</h1>

<p>You may be asking &ldquo;did someone at Nintendo actually program a consequence for profanity in the game? Is the glitching and crashing a punishment for the perverse player?&rdquo; In truth, the password is merely a coincidence.</p>

<p>As mentioned earlier, the password algorithm for Metroid has been reverse-engineered, and you can actually download a program to both generate and interpret such passwords <a href="http://games.technoplaza.net/mpg/">here</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/metroidpassgen.png"></p>

<p>The profane password is indeed a legitimate password (in which Ridley is already defeated, ironically enough). But why does it crash the game? The <a href="http://games.technoplaza.net/mpg/password.txt">Metroid Password Format Guide</a> explains the secret:</p>

<blockquote><p> There are five valid start locations. They are specified using bits 64-66.
  To start in Brinstar, all the bits should be off. Norfair, Kraid&rsquo;s Lair, and
  Ridley&rsquo;s Lair can be specified by turning their bit on and leaving the others
  off. Tourian is specified by turning on Norfair and Kraid&rsquo;s Lair
  simultaneously. Any other combination of these three bits is invalid and will
  cause Metroid to reset.</p>

<p>  The reset bit is part of the start location. There are 16 possible values,
  but only 5 valid ones. Turning on the reset bit will produce and invalid
  start location and cause Metroid to reset. This is why it is called it is
  called the reset bit, because it guarantees an invalid password.</p></blockquote>

<p>For the profane password, the reset bit is turned on, so it will always cause a reset. And that&rsquo;s why the weird behavior happens.</p>

<p>If you manually disable the reset bit using this tool in order to make the password valid, the new password becomes:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/metroidpassgen2.png"></p>

<p>Not as catchy, unfortunately.</p>

<p>In fact, the Justin Bailey password is also a completely coincidental password. Sometimes, passwords can just do very unexpected things.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When a Startup Sends a Passive-Aggressive Email Every Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/overly-attached-startup/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-13T18:51:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/overly-attached-startup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple weeks ago, my best friend wanted to make a personal website. After talking with her about what types of features she wanted (home page, photo galleries, low price, etc.) I recommended that she use a website-building platform with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WYSIWYG">WYSIWYG</a> editor, such as <a href="http://www.wix.com/">Wix</a> or <a href="http://www.weebly.com/">Weebly</a>. I had heard good things about both websites, especially Weebly, a <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2007/01/15/weebly-goes-with-ycombinator/">Y Combinator startup</a> which has been <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/05/03/with-over-15m-sites-built-weebly-launches-new-planner-and-mobile-editor-brings-website-creation-service-to-android/">rolling out new features</a> and receiving positive reviews.</p>

<p>She registered for Weebly and loved it. I registered as well to check it out, and I was also impressed after creating a draft test website and experimenting with both drag-and-drop UI elements and raw HTML/CSS editing. Since Weebly has Contributor functionality, I was able to edit her website without having to access her account. I made a few CSS tweaks and that was it: I didn&rsquo;t publish my own website on Weebly, as I&rsquo;m very happy with this blog. :)</p>

<p>A day after her website was published, I received an e-mail from Weebly: a generic &ldquo;First Steps to Creating Your Website.&rdquo; It&rsquo;s just one email, I think, so I ignore it. And then, the next day, I receive another e-mail that was much less subtle: &ldquo;Your website misses you!&rdquo;</p>

<p>This is certainly the first time a startup&rsquo;s emails have tried to <em>guilt</em> me into using the service.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>An Email A Day Keeps The Users Away</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/weebly1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>When I register for <em>any</em> business, not just including startups, I don&rsquo;t enjoy seeing any emails that aren&rsquo;t helpful or aren&rsquo;t expected. I&rsquo;m OK when businesses send emails that alert me when a new service has been launched or when a scheduled newsletter is released. In the former case, the email is directly relevant to my interests, in the latter case, the email is not an unexpected surprise.</p>

<p>In Weebly&rsquo;s case, and any other startup that resorts to forward emailing strategies as a form of &ldquo;growth hacking,&rdquo; they&rsquo;re invalidating my trust. A once-a-month announcement about your business is OK, but if I want to visit your website, I don&rsquo;t need to be reminded every <em>day</em>.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at the emails that Weebly has sent:</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 5th: First Steps to Creating Your Website</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/weebly2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>This is actually a good first e-mail.</p>

<p>It adds a personal touch. I didn&rsquo;t pay much attention to it since I didn&rsquo;t plan on publishing my own website, but to a new customer, it makes them feel welcome.</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 6th: Your website misses you!</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/weebly3.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I received this <em>the next day</em> after the previous email. My website misses me? It&rsquo;s been two days! Which you tell me with a rather disturbing amount of precision!</p>

<p>My website is not a cow in FarmVille. I don&rsquo;t need to publish my website immediately. In fact, if I were to publish a website, I would make sure it&rsquo;s polished first, in which case the email&rsquo;s push toward publishing ASAP would actually be insulting.</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 7th: Need Any Help?</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/weebly4.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a totally-not-automatically-generated e-mail by a employee at Weebly. It lacks any Weebly branding, which supposedly gives it a more &ldquo;personal&rdquo; touch&hellip;except if Richard wanted to give it a personal touch, he would have included <em>my name</em>. The <a href="http://emailmarketing.comm100.com/email-marketing-ebook/can-spam-law.aspx">legally-mandated</a> unsubscribe link, a requirement for commercial emails, doesn&rsquo;t make me feel any more comfortable.</p>

<p>And again, it&rsquo;s only been three days.</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 8th: Max, check out your mobile website!</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/weebly5.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>While that feature may be cool, finding an <em>excuse</em> to send me an e-mail really isn&rsquo;t necessary.</p>

<p>Weebly skipped May 9th, fortunately.</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 10th: Free vs. Pro: Which One is Right for You?</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/weebly6.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>&ldquo;As you may have noticed.&rdquo; In that case, why bother sending the e-mail? Will the e-mail&rsquo;s argument be any different?</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 11th: Max, get 33% off at Weebly!</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/weebly7.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Now we&rsquo;re mixing both overly precise user registration dates <em>and</em> &ldquo;as you may have noticed&rdquo; verbage! I did notice, as a matter of fact! I noticed <em>yesterday</em>!</p>

<hr>


<h2>May 12th: It&rsquo;s been 8 days, 2 hours, 30 minutes and 6 seconds&hellip;</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/weebly8.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Ok, seriously, what the hell?</p>

<p>At this point, Weebly is seriously <em>threatening</em> me into publishing my website. Gone are the informative email subject lines: now, Weebly simply <em>reminds</em> me how much time I&rsquo;ve spent not working on a website. They&rsquo;ve graduated from passive-aggressive to just aggressive.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s genuinely terrifying is that Weebly actually created a custom email message to send to users to send after a week of having an unpublished site. <em>They tested this email behavior and thought this was a good idea.</em> Apparently, they never considered that a user could exist solely to contribute to another user&rsquo;s website.</p>

<p>Some might say that I should have unsubscribed if I was unhappy with Weebly&rsquo;s emails. Indeed, all the e-mails had unsubscribe links, hidden where most people won&rsquo;t see them of course. But that&rsquo;s not the point: if startups keep sending forward e-mails, <em>everyone</em> loses.</p>

<p>At the least, I&rsquo;m very cautious to recommend Weebly to anyone else.</p>

<hr>


<p><strong>UPDATE (5/14/13)</strong>: On the corresponding <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5704860">Hacker News thread</a>, David Rusenko, founder and CEO of Weebly, posted a response:</p>

<blockquote><p>I&rsquo;d like to jump in and clarify a few things. First, we have recently been testing the frequency of our email sending, and the author seems to have been bucketed into the &ldquo;more frequent&rdquo; group. That being said, we were actually planning on reducing the frequency of what we emailed the author by roughly 25%, including eliminating the &ldquo;Your website misses you&rdquo; and the &ldquo;It’s been 8 days, 2 hours, 30 minutes and 6 seconds…&rdquo; emails, among others. I just fast-tracked this and it&rsquo;s now live, so our email volume when you sign up is now much lower.</p>

<p>Second, we put a lot of effort into trying to send personalized email communication that is specific to your use case, but it looks like we missed a very important group, contributors to others&#8217; sites. This was a mistake. These emails may make sense if you were starting your own site, but they certainly don&rsquo;t make sense if you were just contributing to someone else&rsquo;s. I&rsquo;m going to make sure we revise that set of emails within 2 weeks to something more appropriate and even less frequent.</p>

<p>Last, as many here are correct to assume, we are constantly testing and refining our email communications. I think it&rsquo;s helpful to understand our customer&rsquo;s psychology when they are signing up for Weebly, it is instructive in understanding our thought process and why we send the emails we do.
Most of our customers (60%) consider themselves entrepreneurs. They are bringing a new idea to life, things like chairigami.com, themintspace.com, stealthelectricbikesusa.com or weeknightbite.com. They are quitting their full-time jobs to do this and it&rsquo;s a very frightening process.</p>

<p>Creating their site is especially daunting and difficult for them, even though it&rsquo;s so crucial to their success. Many of them start the process, want to finish, but give up. We&rsquo;ve found that the first week is the most crucial. In our email communications, it&rsquo;s our goal to try to help them across the finish line to a high-quality site.</p>

<p>In this case, we were emailing too often, and we&rsquo;ve stopped doing that. In general, most of our users do appreciate some help and encouragement along the way, and we will keep testing emails to try to make that as effective, helpful, and non-annoying as possible.</p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s good to hear that Weebly is aware of the issue, and I&rsquo;m thankful for David&rsquo;s response, although I&rsquo;ll still be keeping an eye on the close eye on how much spam they&rsquo;re still sending out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diablo III Economy Broken by an Integer Overflow Bug]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/stones-of-jordan/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T21:53:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/stones-of-jordan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://us.battle.net/d3/en/">Diablo III</a>, Blizzard&rsquo;s highly-awaited online-only Action RPG released almost a year ago to the day, has had its share of technical difficulties. From <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/error-37">Error 37</a> to lag spikes that can cause hundreds of hours to go to waste, Blizzard has spent the past year improving the game backend to better accommidate the millions of active players.</p>

<p>Diablo III is also noted for its economy, with an emphasis on a region-wide auction house where players can trade one-in-a-million items for millions and billions of gold. (inflation is crazy). Additionally, Diablo III emphasized the use of a Real World Auction House, where players can sell gold or items for real world cash.</p>

<p>Today was the launch of <a href="http://us.battle.net/d3/en/blog/9647272/patch-108-now-live-5-7-2013">Patch 1.0.8</a>, a patch which promised improvements to character progression. After spending a few weeks on a Public Test Realm, where players volunteered to tested the patch to ensure that there were game-breaking exploits, the patch released successfully.</p>

<p>Except for one patch note that was added last minute and not tested in the PTR. And it&rsquo;s a patch note that broke the economy to tiny pieces.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The patch notes from the final build contained this change:</p>

<blockquote><p>The stack size for gold sales on the auction house has been increased from 1 million to 10 million.</p></blockquote>

<p>Normally, on the Real Money Auction House, the player can only sell money in 1 million gold increments. In 1.0.8, the player can sell it in 10 million increments. So, what happens when the player tries putting an absurd amount of money on the Auction House?</p>

<p>Reddit user tyropro <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Diablo/comments/1dx3wv/some_speculation_on_how_the_gold_bug_made_it_to/">has a nice explanation</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The gold &ldquo;dupe&rdquo; involved creating a RMAH auction for billions of gold while staying under the $250 limit. The example I saw in a video was 6 billion gold (600 x 10,000,000 at $0.39 per stack, for $234). When they posted this auction only ~1.7 billion appeared to be for sale, with the rest &ldquo;missing&rdquo; until they sent it to their stash and ended up with more than they started with. The exact numbers from a duping video:</p>

<pre><code>Create RMAH auction for:            6,000,000,000 gold
Auction shows up as:                1,705,032,704 gold
This much is missing!               4,294,967,296 gold
The missing amount, divided by 2:   2,147,483,648 gold
</code></pre>

<p>2,147,483,648 (or 231) is the maximum value you can store in an int32 in programming. I&rsquo;m no programmer, but I took one class in high school and was taught about the limits of different variable types. See:</p>

<p>Simply put, their RMAH gold selling code wasn&rsquo;t written to handle numbers over 2,147,483,648 properly, and the result was duplicate gold being added to people&rsquo;s stashes.</p></blockquote>

<p>4,294,967,296 is also 232, or the bound on an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integer_(computer_science)#Common_long_integer_sizes">unsigned integer</a>, which would be an interesting implementation choice on Blizzard&rsquo;s part.</p>

<p>And so, the dupers created these 6-billion-gold auctions which only appears to sell as 1.7 billion (and therefore only had 1.7 billion deducted from the current balance), canceled them, and were fully refunded the 6 billion for a net profit of the difference (4.2 billion). Repeat <em>ad nauseum</em>.</p>

<p>A popular game streamer showed off the exploit. Other streamers followed. It was easily reproducible and <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Diablo/comments/1dw9kr/there_is_a_gold_dupe_on_na_currently_this_is_the/">everyone knew how to reproduce it</a>.</p>

<p>Hilarity ensued.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/diablo31.png" alt="diablo31" /></p>

<p>Yes, that&rsquo;s 420 <em>billion</em> gold.</p>

<p>After buying up all the duped items in the Auction House, the items were then sold on the Real Money Auction House. For real money. And people bought them.</p>

<p>This is the definition of a worst-case scenario for Diablo III. All because of an untested patch note. What could Blizzard do? Performing a roll-back would wipe all progress obtained by players for the patch day, which would result in a lot of bad PR. But leaving the economy as-is will devalue all items in the game (and Diablo III is all about getting items).</p>

<p>In the end, Blizzard <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Diablo/comments/1dx4a7/there_will_officially_be_no_rollback_after_the/">has not done a roll-back</a>, but instead <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Diablo/comments/1dwk6x/d3_inigomontoya_just_got_banned_for_real/">banned anyone who duped</a>, and <a href="http://i.imgur.com/x5S9Zcx.png">refunded</a> anyone who spent real money. The bug was temporarily fixed by reverting the patch note which caused the entire mess.</p>

<p>Let this be a lesson on what happens when you include an untested change at the last minute. You could break an entire economy. Eh, no big deal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Blog Comment System That Steals Comments From Facebook]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/comments-everywhere/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-04T21:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/05/comments-everywhere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not a fan of the LiveFyre comments system for blogs. As I&rsquo;ve talked about before, LiveFyre is difficult to use, and actually hurts blogs more than it helps. But more and more blogs, such as CNet and AllThingsD, have switched to LiveFyre.</p>

<p>AllThingsD&rsquo;s <a href="http://allthingsd.com/20130330/introducing-livefyre-commenting-at-allthingsd/?mod=atd-desktop">reasons</a> for switching to LiveFyre from the widely-used Disqus are interesting. Under LiveFyre, users can &ldquo;more readily share comments to Facebook and Twitter&rdquo; which Disqus already did; &ldquo;tag friends and draw them into the stream&rdquo; which increases clutter; and &ldquo;accurately flag other comments as spam or offensive&rdquo; which flat-out doesn&rsquo;t work, if the spam on TechCrunch is any indication. Additionally, they can &ldquo;follow conversations across multiple platforms,&rdquo; which the post doesn&rsquo;t elaborate upon. Does it aggregate social media which links to the parent post, a la Disqus?</p>

<p>No, it&rsquo;s something much more important.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Comments From Everywhere!</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/liveFyreSync.png"></p>

<p>Recently, LiveFyre implemented a <a href="http://www.livefyre.com/comments/">comment feature</a> called SocialSync:</p>

<p>With Livefyre SocialSync, the conversation happening on Facebook and Twitter automatically syncs directly to your content, where it belongs. SocialSync comments can be replied to and interacted with just like any other comment, including being automatically posted back to Twitter or Facebook.</p>

<p>Currently, this feature is enabled for TechCrunch and Mashable.* Let&rsquo;s say a Facebook user comments on one of TechCrunch&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10151659746677952&amp;set=a.114456157951.118433.8062627951&amp;type=1">Facebook posts</a>. Those comments are synchronized to the LiveFyre comments for the <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/05/02/smartphonetographers/">linked post</a>.</p>

<p>Those comments become LiveFyre comments. And the Facebook user has no input, nor any notification that their comments are being used this way.</p>

<h2>SocialSync&rsquo;s Flat-Out Lie</h2>

<p>In LiveFyre&rsquo;s own words, the conversations &ldquo;sync&rdquo; across platforms. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synchronization">Synchronization</a> implies a two-way interation, i.e. actions on one platform affect the other. In this example, there are four use cases for the interaction to be called &ldquo;sync&rdquo;:</p>

<ol>
<li>Comments on Facebook should appear on LiveFyre.</li>
<li>Comments on LiveFyre should appear on Facebook.</li>
<li>Replies and Likes on comments on Facebook should appear on the corresponding comment in LiveFyre.</li>
<li>Replies and Likes on comments on LiveFyre should appear on the corresponding comment in Facebook.</li>
</ol>


<p>Out of those four scenarios, only #1 is true, and even more importantly, #2, #3, and #4 are impossible to implement.</p>

<p>LiveFyre doesn&rsquo;t know what your Facebook account is and cannot perform actions on your behalf on Facebook unless you register solely with that account. Therefore, your comments won&rsquo;t sync to the Facebook comment thread if you use any other login type. (the ability to use multiple types of logins being another touted feature of LiveFyre, of course). Likewise, Likes on Facebook Comments can&rsquo;t translate to LiveFyre Likes if the users don&rsquo;t have a LiveFyre account.</p>

<p>The lack of connection also breaks notifications of replies. Since there&rsquo;s no way to ensure the two accounts are linked, there&rsquo;s no way to notify a Facebook user when their synced comment on LiveFyre has a reply. This has two effects: a) the Facebook user won&rsquo;t continue the discussion and b) the replier is wasting his time making a comment to a person who likely won&rsquo;t ever read it. Both result in less fruitful discussions.</p>

<p>SocialSync is broken and impossible to fix. Also, the lag from when comments are synced from Facebook to LiveFyre takes about 10-20 minutes, making sync worthless on highly-discussed event blogs posts anyways..</p>

<h2>Who Owns Your Facebook Comments?</h2>

<p>When I said that LiveFyre &ldquo;steals&rdquo; Facebook comments in the headline, I wasn&rsquo;t being facetious. It&rsquo;s not obvious that this feature even exists in the first place, especially if you&rsquo;re not a comment addict (I sent a <a href="https://twitter.com/minimaxir/status/311959448694435840">tweet</a> to the TechCrunch head editor to confirm that this was intended behavior). How is the typical person supposed to know what their comments are being used for?</p>

<p>Yes, your comments on TechCrunch&rsquo;s Facebook wall post that are synced to LiveFyre are Public to everyone, and there is no expectation of privacy. But who owns those comments?</p>

<p>The comments appear in LiveFyre matching the style and functionality of any other LiveFyre comment, except with a &ldquo;from Facebook&rdquo; designation. For all intents and purposes, it&rsquo;s a LiveFyre comment that you have no controll over. It&rsquo;s worth noting that since LiveFyre doesn&rsquo;t know your Facebook account, you can&rsquo;t even delete the syndicated comment in LiveFyre . LiveFyre comments on the post have greater SEO than Facebook comments, so hopefully you don&rsquo;t say anything embarrassing on the Facebook page. LiveFyre is in control of your destiny.</p>

<p>What are the benefits to SocialSync anyways, when it barely works? Bigger numbers for the comment count of a post? That&rsquo;s irrelevant when the comments on the Facebook posts are made spur-of-the-moment, and are usually very low quality.</p>

<p>The idea of sync between isn&rsquo;t terrible in itself. Facebook Comments and the recently announced Google%2B Comment System essentially does sync by blurring the lines between a Google%2B post and a comment, but unlike LiveFyre, the user still retains control over the comment, receives reply notifications, and can delete their comment when necessary.</p>

<p>At the least, I&rsquo;ve stopped posting on TechCrunch&rsquo;s Facebook page. That&rsquo;s not a good thing for either TechCrunch or LiveFyre.</p>

<ul>
<li>Interestingly, SocialSync is not enabled on CNet or AllThingsD&rsquo;s implementations of LiveFyre.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook Outage: All Webpage Likes and Comments Reset]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/03/facebook-outage/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-25T21:47:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/03/facebook-outage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>UPDATE: The issue was resolved about 11 hours after the post was published. Like counts and comment counts are back. See <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/03/25/facebook-comments-bug/">TechCrunch&rsquo;s post</a>.</strong></p>

<p>Today (3/25/13), Facebook appears to have made a change that has nuked all existing Facebook Like counts and Facebook Comments. I can verify that on this particular blog, my non-cached Like counts and my Comments are gone, even after checking Facebook&rsquo;s Graph API directly. This can be verified on older blog posts, such as <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/05/19/day-after-ipo-mark-zuckerberg-marries-longtime-girlfriend-priscilla-chan/">this one</a>.  It is also <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/15623582/facebook-like-count-for-articles-reset-to-zero">being tracked on Stack Overflow</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/Zuck.png"></p>

<p>Note the lack of comments and Likes, on what was the article with the second-most pageviews on TC (and one I can testify that had hundreds of comments.) A quick glance at multiple blogs and other old posts confirms that Likes were reset. New posts have several likes, but all old posts have 0 likes.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure the lost Likes/Comments temporary, but this is an error of incredible magnitude, especially given on how many sites rely on Facebook&rsquo;s data.</p>

<p>Because comments here may be broken, you can comment on the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5439712">Hacker News thread</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Super Mario World "Completed" in Under 3 Minutes by Corrupting the RAM]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/03/127-yoshis-in-slot-6/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-24T21:44:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/03/127-yoshis-in-slot-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Syo5sI-iOgY "></iframe></div>


<p>Watch the video above, you won&rsquo;t regret it. (the fun part starts at 1:12)</p>

<p>This is a <a href="http://tasvideos.org/">Tool-Assisted Speed Run</a>  (TAS) of the Super Nintendo classic Super Mario World. TASes use an emulator to perform optimal game actions with frame-by-frame precision in order to complete the game in the lowest amount of time, and can use &ldquo;save states&rdquo;  to reverse any gameplay mistakes. Games on older consoles frequently have glitches that require such precision that consequently are very difficult to perform on a console consistently, making TASes more of an art form than actual gameplay advice.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So, what the heck is happening in this speedrun? curtmack on Reddit <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1aldvz/major_glitch_discovered_in_luigis_mansion_that/c8yk3g3">explains it succinctly</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>So, for those who are wondering just what the f- happened&hellip; there&rsquo;s a glitch that&rsquo;s been known for a while, where Yoshi can end up in the &ldquo;I have an item in my mouth&rdquo; state, but not actually have an item in his mouth. When he spits out this nothingness, the game crashes. That&rsquo;s all we knew about the glitch&hellip; until recently.</p>

<p>Somebody decided to take a debugging emulator and step through the crash. He discovered that the crash occurred because the game tried to jump to a specific address in memory, and execute code there. That address did not contain code, and so the system crashed.</p>

<p>But wait a second. What if, by some sheer coincidence, that address <em>did</em> contain code? The specific address dropped him in somewhere amongst various data for the game&rsquo;s internal random number generator, and the random number generator can be manipulated in a TAS. Could the game be coerced into running arbitrary code?</p>

<p>Well, as it turns out, it&rsquo;s extremely limited. You have the RNG state and a few sprite positions that can be manipulated, but after that is some internal game stuff that can&rsquo;t be. So the length of the &ldquo;program&rdquo; is extremely limited, but as it turns out, it&rsquo;s just long enough to send the signal to the game to switch to the &ldquo;The End&rdquo; screen.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a related glitch where you can spawn a bouncing fish by doing certain odd things as you spit out an item as Yoshi, and every time a fish bounces, it uses up a randomly-generated number (since it bounces in a random direction). So, putting it all together, you have to spawn a billion fish and have them all bounce a f-jillion times to get the RNG in just the right spot, leave the area, and then fiddle around with some objects to get the last few bits you need in the right place, all while setting up the original spit-nothing glitch in the first place.</p></blockquote>

<p>Crazy, isn&rsquo;t it?</p>

<h2>I Call Hax!</h2>

<p>This <a href="http://tasvideos.org/1945M.html">SMW TAS</a>, posted in 2011, was so crazy that it inspired the creation of a new category of speed runs: &ldquo;Corrupts Memory.&rdquo; The <a href="http://tasvideos.org/forum/viewtopic.php?t=12215">discussion on the speed run</a> provides a technical explanation of of the glitch, which started a debate: &ldquo;does this <em>count</em> as a speed run?&rdquo; (96% of voters said yes.)</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/smw.png"></p>

<p>To be fair, this is far from the first time where manipulated RAM has been used to complete a game. The classic Nintendo 64 title Legend of Zelda: Ocarina of Time has the infamous <a href="http://zeldaspeedruns.com/oot/ba/reverse-bottle-adventure">Reverse Bottle glitch</a> that allows players to transform items into others, and a <a href="http://youtu.be/PaUCFrW_mEE?t=13m44s">memory glitch</a> that teleports you from the first dungeon to the final cutscene, In <em>Pokemon</em> on the GameBoy, players discovered how to reprogram the game to <a href="http://tasvideos.org/forum/viewtopic.php?p=332488&amp;sid=1d8670bd80327418d202b6608e5cd2a9#332488">run arbitrary code</a>, but many gamers may remember the classic <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Missingno.">Missingno glitch</a>, which was very easy to reproduce on an actual console and provided many beneficial effects.</p>

<p>Still, it&rsquo;s not every day that spawning a ton of fishes out of mid-air = victory.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How To Kill The Reader Comments Of A Popular Tech Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/its-a-metaphor-maybe/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-23T21:38:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/its-a-metaphor-maybe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In March of 2011, <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2011/03/01/facebook-rolls-out-overhauled-comments-system-try-them-now-on-techcrunch/">TechCrunch implemented</a> the just-announced Facebook Comments functionality on their blog. The <a href="http://developers.facebook.com/docs/reference/plugins/comments/">Facebook Comments Box</a> is an official plugin from Facebook which allows users who are logged into Facebook to instantly comment on a blog post or article; no registration needed. Adding a Facebook Comments Box to a website is simple, it provides a visual style that can work with any blog design, and it can have users share their posts on Facebook, which leverages the commenter&rsquo;s friends to drive more traffic to the blog.</p>

<p>I first began commenting on TechCrunch in July of the same year, mostly to test out the full functionality of Facebook Comments, after having spent a lot of time experimenting with <a href="http://disqus.com/">Disqus</a> and Gawker&rsquo;s custom comment system (I talk about it <a href="http://www.quora.com/Online-Commenting/Whats-the-deal-with-Max-Woolf-on-TechCrunch-AOL-comments">here</a>). During that time, my comments began to make me rather infamous, both in good ways, and surprisingly bad. (once, a well-respected entrepreneur messaged me saying &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve talked to VCs and they&rsquo;ve said they will never invest in you because of your comments. FYI.&rdquo;)</p>

<p>Fast forward to 2012. Other blogs on the Aol blogging network, such as Engadget, Joystiq, and TechCrunch itself, have <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2012/10/11/engadget-livefyre-commenting-system/">decided</a> to <a href="http://www.joystiq.com/2012/04/04/joystiqs-new-commenting-system-is-live/">migrate</a> to <a href="http://www.livefyre.com/">LiveFyre</a>, another blog commenting system which allows readers to comment using their social identities, in addition to a few flashy Web 2.0 features. I figured it was a matter of time until TechCrunch implemented it themselves. And in January 2013, <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/22/we-want-you-back/">they did</a>.</p>

<p>At first, I thought I would like the change. Facebook Comments has their own problems that a switch to Livefyre could solve. I was wrong. The stated reasons for the change were &ldquo;we want more comments,&rdquo; but a large amount of low-value comments (and images), with no way to identify good ones, along with the increased hassle of commenting, will end up backfiring. I&rsquo;m honestly afraid that the switch from Facebook Comments could kill quality comments on TechCrunch completely.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Pros and Cons of Facebook Comments</h2>

<p>As said earlier, Facebook comments excel in their ease of implementation, light aesthetic, and zero-click registration. More importantly, it lends a lot of credibility to the comments, as they have (usually) been authenticated as a real person. Whenever a <em>real</em> person likes or comments on your own comment, it is very satisfying.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/alexia.png"></p>

<p>That said, there are a few unobvious nuances:</p>

<ul>
<li>For most blog systems, you receive a notification whenever someone replies to your post. In the original implementation of FB Comments, you receive one whenever someone likes or replies to your comment, in the same manner you&rsquo;re notified on a typical Facebook status. This has changed recently: now, you don&rsquo;t receive notification for likes/replies on your comment, and instead you <strong><em>only receive notifications when other people comment on the same post</em></strong>. I haven&rsquo;t figured out if this is a bug or a feature.</li>
<li><strong>There is no spam filter.</strong> As many can attest, Facebook has been terrible at combating spam both on the main website and off. All spam cleaning must be done <em>ad hoc</em>, which can be time-consuming.</li>
<li><strong>Virtually no customization for the comments</strong>. On the administrative side, the only significant options you have for commenting are how many comments appear initially, and the default sort order. It makes sense for Facebook to limit customization to protect their own branding, but it&rsquo;s frustrating for both the admin and readers.</li>
<li><strong>Commenters do not have access to a list of comments that they&rsquo;ve made.</strong> This one in particular upset me, which is one of the reasons I&rsquo;ve aggregated all my comments <a href="http://minimaxir.com/category/blog-comments/">here</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Facebook&rsquo;s count of comments lies. </strong>The count provided by Facebook does <em>not</em> include replies to comments, unlike every blog comment system since the beginning of time.</li>
</ul>


<p>There have been zero improvements to Facebook Comments since 2011. It&rsquo;s disappointing, but there&rsquo;s not much that can be done&hellip; except considing competitors.</p>

<h2>LiveFyre Makes Comments BURN!</h2>

<p>LiveFyre, on a typical blog like this one, has quite a few perks that Facebook Comments does not. It allows users to comment just by linking a social identity, such as Facebook or Twitter. Or you can remain anonymous. You receive notifications by email. Images and video are embedded into posts. Posts appear in real time, increasing the interaction for live events. And, you have a profile which lists all the comments you&rsquo;ve ever made.</p>

<p>LiveFyre also has comment editing and an indicator of how many users are viewing the current blog post, but for some reason, the implementation of LiveFyre on TechCrunch disabled these features. Hmm.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/comments2.png"></p>

<p>The core features good on paper. The problem is with the implementation. <a href="http://fyre.it/u2jnrP">This comment</a> does a good summary, but here&rsquo;s the gist when compared to Facebook Comments:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Anonymous comments are <em>usually</em> low-quality comments. </strong>With Facebook Comments, rational people will not make stupid comments that are tied with their real name. With anonymous comments, people can troll as much as they want without any repercussions.  Yes, with more accessible to comments leads to a higher chance of quality comments by the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_large_numbers">law of large numbers</a>, but that is completely irrelevant because&hellip;</li>
<li><strong>There is no way to sort by high-quality comments</strong>. Facebook Comments, by default, sorts comments by the number of likes that they have received: more likes, the higher up they are in the comment thread. LiveFyre only allows sorting in chronological order and reverse chronological order. No exception. This strongly reduces the <em>motivation</em> for high-quality posts.</li>
<li><strong>New comments that are loaded live forcibly scroll down all comments.</strong> Imagine: you&rsquo;re reading a good comment, and a new comment loads and <em>pushes</em> the comment away. With spam. You&rsquo;ll become frustrated very quickly. This may not be a concern for blogs with low user-bases, but for popular blogs, this can become irritating very quickly.</li>
<li><strong>Images and video appear in-line, and are very large.</strong> This makes them more visible, which is a good thing, <em>unless</em> they&rsquo;re memes and spam. Then it&rsquo;s terrible. And since people can comment anonymously, there&rsquo;s a significant risk factor. Images/video, due to their size, cause comment scrolling even faster!</li>
</ul>


<h2>The impact of LiveFyre on TechCrunch</h2>

<p><img class="pull-right" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/ToKillACommentsSection.png"></p>

<p>LiveFyre works on a typical WordPress blog, but when applied to large sites such as Engadget and TechCrunch, whose size attracts trolls, it can be crippling. It&rsquo;s like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar's_number">Dunbar&rsquo;s Number</a> on a macro scale: there&rsquo;s a mathematical limit on the number of people who visit one place on the internet until it degenerates into madness and memes.</p>

<p>Even with the criticisms above, I still prefer Facebook Comments, and I implement it on my own site, as zero-click registration and real name validation is paramount. It&rsquo;s definitely the lesser of two evils.</p>

<p>The main argument TechCrunch used to justify the switch from Facebook Comments to LiveFyre is that users aren&rsquo;t commenting as much. That&rsquo;s a given, since you can&rsquo;t comment anonymously. It&rsquo;s the old debate of quantity vs. quality: in the case of comments, however, it&rsquo;s <em>always</em> in favor of quality. I&rsquo;d rather read a comments section with one or two comments than a comments section consisting of 90% anonymous spammers who make me lose faith in humanity. Losing faith in humanity is not healthy.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll probably be toning down my comments on TechCrunch even moreso. My <a href="http://www.quora.com/Online-Commenting/Whats-the-deal-with-Max-Woolf-on-TechCrunch-AOL-comments">primary motivation for commenting</a> was, and still is, making people laugh and smile. But if other readers have to dig through anonymous spam just to find my comments, then there&rsquo;s not much point. I could spam my comments to my Facebook profile every time I make one, but that would cause the <em>opposite</em> issue.*<br/>
*</p>

<p>I realize that this is a first-world problem. Even more of a first world problem than <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness/">auto-downloading pictures of cute puppies</a>. I&rsquo;m not mad.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m just sad. :(</p>

<hr>


<p><strong>EDIT (May 2013)</strong>: When this article was published, this blog was using Facebook Comments, however I switched the comments system to Disqus just to try it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let Myspace's Justin Timberlake Bring Sexy To The Entire Internet]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/sexy-will-haunt-your-dreams/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-15T21:36:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/sexy-will-haunt-your-dreams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>TechCrunch writer Sarah Perez recently wrote <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/15/lost-on-new-myspace-cant-escape-justin-send-help/">an incredibly hilarious article</a> about <a href="https://new.myspace.com/">Myspace</a>&rsquo;s recent redesign, and the&hellip;overemphasis of a certain former N&#8217;Sync band member. Justin Timberlake, the spearhead of Myspace&rsquo;s music-oriented redesign, stresses his clean-shaven image with a handsome yet somber black-and-white portrait that always seems to follow you where you go.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m OK with this. There are certainly far <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/03/ethics-self-promotion/"><em>worse</em></a> ways to promote a startup.</p>

<p>His moody yet charmful face adds a touch of class to any website. But why does he have to stay constrained to Myspace? Why not let Justin Timberlake dominate the world?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>No Such Thing As Too Much Sexy</h2>

<p>If you are reading this post on a desktop or laptop, you&rsquo;ll see a handsome fellow in the lower-right corner. This is Justin Timberlake of the Mickey Mouse Club. Say hi.</p>

<p>Using the power of the Stylish extension for Chrome and Firefox, Mr. Timberlake has already made his mark on many startups around the internet.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/justintest3.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/justintest2.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/justintest9.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/justintest8.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/justintest7.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/justintest5.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/justintest4.png"></p>

<p>To accomplish this magic, I use the Stylish browser extension, which can be used with either <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en">Chrome</a> or <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/stylish/">Firefox</a>. I have used Stylish <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/">before, with browser filters</a>, and it worked very well. If you want your own moody Justin, follow these steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Install the Stylish extension for your browser.</li>
<li>In the extension preferences, go to &ldquo;Managed Installed Styles&rdquo; and select &ldquo;Write New Style&rdquo;</li>
<li><p>Paste this CSS code in the &ldquo;Code&rdquo; textbox:</p>

<pre><code>body, ._li, .main {
background-image: url(http://i.imgur.com/UN5HE.png) !important;
background-position: right bottom !important;
background-repeat: no-repeat !important;
background-attachment: fixed !important;
}
</code></pre></li>
</ol>


<p>And you&rsquo;re done! Justin will appear pretty much everywhere. Yes, there are a lot of <em>!important</em> declarations, but Justin Timberlake is an important man.</p>

<p>In fact, by using the HTML snippet in this <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/display-justin-timberlake-sexiness">GitHub repository</a>, you can add Justin to your own site!</p>

<p>Feel free to narrow down the domains where Justin appears by using Stylish as necessary. Although, why would you do such a thing!?</p>

<h2>Taking Justin To The Next Level</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/816440400_1965379.gif"></p>

<p>Now that we can make Justin appear anywhere, let&rsquo;s put his power to good use. TechCrunch writer Alexia Tsostis recently made a post about the <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/16/were-bringing-techcrunch-back/">upcoming redesign of TechCrunch</a>, which, I admit, is long overdue.</p>

<p>In the post, Alexia spoils that the redesign will include lots of sparkles. And a picture of the Justin-man himself. Above is a mockup made by Chris Velazco, another TechCrunch writer, and it is indeed marvelous. (except for the lack of a comments section!)</p>

<p>But why wait for the redesign? We have Timberlake Technology. We can do it <em>now</em>.</p>

<p>Using the power of Stylish, I present to you, a sneak peek into TechCrunch&rsquo;s 2013 redesign.</p>

<p>I made a <em>few</em> stylistic additions as well. It&rsquo;s magic.</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/j6m2pjjhnuU "></iframe></div>


<p>You can find a copy of the CSS I used to emulate this wonderful layout in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/techcrunch-1999">this GitHub repository</a>.</p>

<p>Will you let Timberlake enrich <em>your</em> life? He&rsquo;s waiting. In the lower-right corner of your screen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Auto-Save Images From Reddit To Computer Without Visiting The Site (Using IFTTT)]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T21:32:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/if-cute-then-happiness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>TL;DR: Use this <a href="https://ifttt.com/recipes/74285">IFTTT recipe</a>, and change the subreddit value in the parameter of the Feed URL as needed.</em></strong></p>

<p>In <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">a previous post</a>, I joked about a hypothetical social media strategy in which an automated script does Facebook brand management by stealing the top cute images from <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a> &ndash; an aggregator of trending topics and images &ndash;  and reposting them on the Facebook page, additionally adding a cute message encouraging users to LIKE, SHARE, and COMMENT!  We get easy social media fame for no monetary cost.</p>

<p>Out of curiosity, I wanted to see if it was feasible to create such a script. Both Reddit and Facebook indeed have APIs that make it easy. But then I have to set up a server to check Reddit periodically, ensure that no images are duplicated, etc., and that can take time to implement and ensure that it works correctly (<em>all</em> the images must be cute!). I looked into <a href="https://ifttt.com/">IFTTT</a>, a relatively new startup that talks between different popular web services to automate simple tasks, like posting to Twitter whenever you post to Facebook.</p>

<p>As it turns out, yes, this is possible, and you can also save the top images on Reddit to your computer via any cloud storage service without ever visiting the website too! Just use <a href="https://ifttt.com/recipes/74285">this IFTTT recipe</a>! There are a few interesting caveats, though&hellip;</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Really Simple Syndication is&hellip;Really Simple?</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/redditrss2.png"></p>

<p>IFTTT allows users to extract information from RSS feeds, which one might typically be used to read blogs and news articles. The RSS feed typically provides the title, author, date, and content of a post: the important things. However, RSS has more applications: it can distribute other data, such as weather and desktop wallpapers. IFTTT allows other apps to load image and audio files from an RSS feed, but only if the RSS feed link links to the content itself.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this won&rsquo;t work on Reddit by default, as its RSS feeds do not contain a direct link to the photo and instead link to the Reddit comments on the image. Image-based websites, such as <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/">BuzzFeed</a> and <a href="http://interfacelift.com/wallpaper/downloads/date/any/">InterfaceLift</a> also implement a similar system because they don&rsquo;t want their users just to use a script to download images and bypass the website and its lovely revenue-generating advertisements. Therefore, the RSS feed alone won&rsquo;t work with IFTTT.</p>

<p>During my research into my social media exploitation hypothesis, I found a <a href="http://blog.stevemould.com/rss-feed-reddit-stories-score-threshold/">blog post by Steve Mould</a> that provides a way to translate data from Reddit&rsquo;s JSON API to an RSS feed using a service called <a href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/">Yahoo Pipes</a>. This modified RSS feed, when given a subreddit and a score threshold, obtains the top Reddit posts in that subreddit above that karma threshold (upvotes &ndash; downvotes), and returns a feed item which contains direct link to the referenced URL.</p>

<p>Here is <a href="http://bit.ly/W1ypdf">my variation of his Reddit Pipe</a>. My script to process the API has a few changes (such as using Reddit&rsquo;s &ldquo;hot&rdquo; posts, instead of the top posts; hot posts update much more frequently). Testing it with r/aww and a threshold of 50 karma, I received 177 very cute pictures on my computer in a week.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/redditcute.png"></p>

<p>From that Pipe, you can get the data in a RSS feed URL. Right-click and copy that feed URL into a IFTTT recipe as the source. For the action, use the **** variable to retrieve the image URL.</p>

<h2>With Great Power Comes Great Cuteness</h2>

<p>Yes, you can save the Reddit images to your computer automatically using <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</a>. Or <a href="https://drive.google.com">Google Drive</a>. Or <a href="https://skydrive.live.com/">SkyDrive</a>. Or even get a cute email every hour!</p>

<p>Thanks to IFTTT, there are many other creative things you can do with the feed that you can include in a recipe:</p>

<ul>
<li>Auto-post the image to your Tumblr or WordPress blog. Easy cuteness, and you&rsquo;ll be the source!</li>
<li>Auto-curate the cute photos to your Facebook or Twitter account. All your friends will love you!</li>
<li>Get social media fame for no additional monetary cost by publishing the cute images to your Facebook Page, with an encouragement to LIKE SHARE and COMMENT! My original hypothesis was correct!</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/redditnega.png"></p>

<h2>Caveats</h2>

<p>One caveat in using Yahoo Pipes is that it is rate limited to 200 runs in a 10 minute interval, meaning that the IFTTT recipe provided will likely fail if more than 200 people use the feed. If that does happen, just clone my pipe, and use the RSS feed from the clone for your own personal recipe.</p>

<p>Also, there&rsquo;s no rate limiting on when recipes are triggered and images are posted/downloaded. You can trigger multiple images simultaneously, which may be considered spammy if you are posting to social media. In that case, increase the karma threshold to reduce the frequency of the postings and to maintain a high quality of the images.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/iftttrecipe.png"></p>

<p>Getting socially-vetted photos on your computer without any effort is a useful timesaver. A solution to a first world problem, perhaps, but it&rsquo;s the little things that count!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Do Many Tweets Begin With A Period?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/prefixed-period/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-04T21:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/01/prefixed-period</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not a Twitter fanatic. Although I do have <a href="https://twitter.com/minimaxir">a Twitter account</a> with about 300 followers,  Facebook&rsquo;s Subscribe feature <a href="http://www.facebook.com/max.woolf">on my Facebook profile</a> has met my use case for publishing sarcastic quips and cool links for a broad audience over the internet. I mostly use my Twitter account to read tweets from tech columnists, yet I don&rsquo;t even comment on their tweets because <strong>tweets that are replies to someone are not visible in the home timeline of my followers</strong>. I can understand the intuition behind this behavior: Twitter conversations can contain a lot of low-content tweets, and Twitter doesn&rsquo;t want its users to be spammed.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve noticed that many tweets from actual Twitter fanatics begin with a prefixed period, such as <em>&ldquo;.@minimaxir wow funny joke!&rdquo; </em>and <em>&ldquo;.@minimaxir is a huge dork!&rdquo;</em>. I thought the dot was a typo, until I noticed many people also prefixing the period, seemingly randomly, in their own tweets. All of those tweets seemed like witty replies that begged for mass exposure, and so I eventually realized that beginning your reply Tweet with a period (.) allows it to be seen by all your followers. **Otherwise, only the replyee will receive notification of the reply.</p>

<p>Having your reply tweets appear to your followers only if you begin them with a prefixed period is not intuitive at all. And this particular behavior and its workaround are not documented in <a href="https://support.twitter.com/groups/31-twitter-basics/topics/109-tweets-messages/articles/14023-what-are-replies-and-mentions">Twitter&rsquo;s help docs</a>. And replying to tweets is a core feature of Twitter. How many users would be able to deduce this behavior? How many brands, who rely on user engagement, are even aware of this behavior?</p>

<p>As it turns out, I was only partially correct. It&rsquo;s even <em>less</em> intuitive.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>XY = @(Z)</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/twitter2.png"></p>

<p>I recently saw <a href="https://twitter.com/ScottyLabs/status/286921265514700801">a tweet</a> in my timeline that had a prefixed period, but clearly was not a reply to anyone. Confused, I pointed out that prefixed periods aren&rsquo;t necessary if the tweet is not a reply. <a href="https://twitter.com/amyquispe">Amy Quispe</a>, founder of ScottyLabs and a CS senior at Carnegie Mellon University with much more startup knowledge than myself, pointed out that I was wrong, and <strong>if the tweet begins with a @, it will not appear in your follower&rsquo;s timelines, regardless of whether it&rsquo;s a reply or a mention</strong>.</p>

<p>Anyone who tweets, for example, &ldquo;<em>@SHO_Dexter is my favorite television show! Season 7 was AWESOME!!!</em>&rdquo;, will likely not have that tweet seen by any of their followers. Therefore, it&rsquo;s incredibly easy, and incredibly likely, for that behavior to unintentionally trigger a false positive for spam. Again, would a person notice that one of his/her tweets is not being seen? It&rsquo;s bad for the user, and it&rsquo;s even bad for @SHO_Dexter, who misses out on the free advertising.</p>

<p>As it turns out, <em>that</em> <em>correction** was still only partially correct</em>, as there&rsquo;s one more important caveat:<strong> if a tweet by X begins a tweet with an @ mention of Y, and if Z is a follower of <em>both</em> X and Y, then Z will see the tweet. If the second condition is not true, then Z will not see the tweet.</strong></p>

<p>Twitter is apparently a course in deductive reasoning. To be fair, this caveat is clearly stated in the help docs, and this behavior makes sense in the context of mutual friends among users. Nevertheless, it&rsquo;s not intuitive at all, and it&rsquo;s mostly irrelevant: a prefixed period tweet reaches all of your followers, 100% of the time.</p>

<h2>The Pestilent Prefixed Period Problem</h2>

<p>Twitter users want maximum reach. Brands want maximum reach. Therefore, everyone will use the prefixed period for replies and mentions. Those who don&rsquo;t use prefixed periods on Twitter will be left behind in this cutthroat game of social media.</p>

<p>There are two problems with encouraging prefixed periods:</p>

<ol>
<li>It alienates newcomers to Twitter. Some online communities do have unwritten behaviors: <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a>, for example, invokes &ldquo;vote fuzzing&rdquo; on popular posts, which disguises the true amount of upvotes and downvotes on any particular post by adding fake upvotes/downvotes. You won&rsquo;t find that in any Reddit documentation, which leads to the frequent outbursts of &ldquo;WHO THE HELL WOULD DOWNVOTE THIS PUPPY?&rdquo; Quirks like these don&rsquo;t make communities exclusive: it makes them insular.</li>
<li><strong>It looks tacky and ugly</strong>. That&rsquo;s not a trivial complaint. Every @mention tweet looks like someone made a typo. I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s the brand image Twitter wants.</li>
</ol>


<p>How could Twitter address this? An option would be to adopt a system similar to Facebook&rsquo;s <em>ad hoc</em> post visibility settings, and allow users to set the reach of an individual tweet as necessary. Another option is to have an <em>All your replies and @mentions are shown to all your followers</em> account option that is opt-in, and let the user&rsquo;s followers determine whether the content is spam.</p>

<p>Twitter, with an impending IPO, needs to help potential newcomers out in any way possible. Eliminating the need for prefixed periods is a great start to increasing accessibility.</p>

<p><em>PS: I am not a huge dork.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Startup Promo Video Using... PowerPoint?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-29T21:28:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I noticed deep in the documentation for PowerPoint 2010 that it <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/powerpoint-help/turn-your-presentation-into-a-video-HA010336763.aspx">supports video output</a> for presentations. Like a good nerd, I experimented to see what it could actually do. My first test of the functionality was a humor video about pitching a <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">hypothetical startup named NegaCycl</a>, complete with animation and narration, which I trashed and eventually retooled because I&rsquo;m bad at verbal comedic delivery. Interestingly, the output video was a 1:1 comparison to what was displayed on my own computer screen during the presentation. Naturally, I decided to test it even harder.</p>

<p>What I have here is another hypothetical, non-real startup named Filtrzzz (based on a <a href="http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10151356495205450&amp;set=a.432190050449.225968.582270449&amp;type=1">popular Facebook post</a> I made), animated and rendered using PowerPoint, with more complicated objects such as embedded audio and video, and an attempt to sync the presentation timing with the audio for dramatic effect. Plus sarcastic humor, of course.</p>

<p>PowerPoint video creation is feasible if you don&rsquo;t have or can&rsquo;t afford dedicated video software and need a promo video in a pinch, as may be the case with an actual startup.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/filtrzzz-ppt.png?resize=625%2C288" alt="filtrzzz ppt" /></p>

<p>The Filtrzzz video relies heavily on slide transitions (the &ldquo;zoom&rdquo; effects at the beginning), text animations (the fade in/fade out on the text at the end), and embedding of media (the background song and the product demos), all of which are very easy to implement, although as with any video, a little trial-and-error is necessary to get a good &ldquo;feel&rdquo; for effect duration, effect intensity, etc.</p>

<p>PowerPoint has the native ability to record timings (i.e. when to progress to the next slide/animation) and voice narrations on a per-slide basis in the Slide Show tab. You can either record the timings while running through a presentation normally (good for maintaining a consistent pace through animations), or record <em>ad hoc</em> per slide (good for voice narration, which is independent from other slides). If timings and narrations are present, when the presentation runs, it will use those timings and play in auto-pilot. When the presentation is exported as a video, it will follow these timings and include the spoken narrations.</p>

<p>The maximum quality output for video through PowerPoint is 720p WMV, which is sufficient for a startup video since users likely are watching the video YouTube-embedded in a webpage. For comparison, I video-captured the presentation using Camtasia at 1080p and rendered the final video as a high-bit rate MP4: the visual quality between the two versions is indistinguishable at non-full screen resolutions. (when watching a video in 1080p at small sizes, the quality is actually even worse!)</p>

<p>You can see the 1080p MP4 version of the Filtrzzz video <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s2ZajsuPomg">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re developing a startup promo video where you narrate a description of your product, include a few pictures, and add a few animations/transitions for added flare, PowerPoint videos might be an option to consider. At the least, it&rsquo;s a good introduction to those looking to break into organized video production.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>By the way, Filterzzz would never work as a real product (nor would I ever publicly post hypothetical startups that could actually be feasible business ideas) for a few reasons:</em></p>

<ol>
<li><em>The way the filters work depends on the internal design of the webpage. Since many websites have highly maverick designs, the filter isn&rsquo;t guaranteed to work 100% on all websites.</em></li>
<li><em>As you saw in the video, the performance impact of the filters on browser speed varies, at least with my implementation. The performance would need to be consistent among all websites in order to avoid user outrage.</em></li>
<li><em>The biggest point: reading text on a filtered background for long periods of time <strong>hurts eyes</strong>. Any startup which tried to promote this business idea would be sued into bankruptcy within a month.</em></li>
</ol>


<p><em>Per #3 and the personal liability it poses, I won&rsquo;t be releasing my source code for the filters, but you can easily create your own by using the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en">Stylish extension for Chrome</a> and implementing <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/filters/understanding-css/">CSS filters</a> into a style.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Totally-Real Totally-Serious Startup Pitch For Venture Capital]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-26T21:26:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Here are presentation slides and a transcript from a totally-real totally-serious startup pitch I did recently for a group of<strong> </strong></em>totally-real totally-serious venture capitalists for <em>totally-real totally-serious venture capital.</em>**</p>

<p><em>This presentation is totally-real totally-serious and not fabricated in any way whatsoever for the purpose of humor. The business and technical terminologies used in this presentation are totally-real totally-serious representations of my own knowledge. I </em>totally-real totally-serious <em>pinky-swear!</em></p>

<p><em>[This isn&rsquo;t real.]</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<h2><strong>Introduction</strong></h2>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide1.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide1" /></p>

<p>Good afternoon, and thank you all for giving me the opportunity to present my startup proposal. I&rsquo;m Max Woolf, I&rsquo;m here with NegaCycl, and I&rsquo;m going to make you a billion dollars, no problem.</p>

<p>Today, I&rsquo;ll be talking about NegaCycl, and I hope that by end of the presentation, you&rsquo;ll agree that this startup is timeless. First, I&rsquo;ll be discussing the inspiring, book-and-movie-deal-worthy events that led toward this business idea. I&rsquo;ll tell you a bit about NegaCycl and how it works, and lastly, you&rsquo;ll see a few cool ways we plan to market the business.</p>

<p>Our mission at NegaCycl is simple: <strong>we are a web application that allows us to provide our users the quickest routes &ndash; regardless of where and <em>when</em> they want to go to.</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide4.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide4" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m here today to formally ask you for $2.01 million in seed money for NegaCycl. Yes, that $0.01 million is significant.</p>

<h2><strong>The Eureka Moment</strong></h2>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide6.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide6" /></p>

<p>On a cold Monday night in November after work, I turned on my TV and began to watch the pilot episode of Start-Ups: Silicon Valley: a reality TV show on Bravo that captures the entrepreneurial essence of the Bay Area&hellip; which apparently involves a lot of dating and partying. Huh, you learn something new every day.</p>

<p>During the episode, the cast members throw an extremely classy toga party to celebrate the launch of some fitness startup no one really cares about.</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide7.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide7" /></p>

<p>After becoming incredibly inebriated at the party, the cast members played <em>the</em> most popular party game for nerds: Drunk Computer Science Trivia.</p>

<p>One question asked to a cast member was<em> &ldquo;How do you solve negative cycles?&rdquo;</em> I thought that was weird; I personally had never heard of the term &ldquo;negative cycle&rdquo; before, and the question didn&rsquo;t seem scripted like a typical Bravo show. What the heck are negative cycles, and how do you solve them?</p>

<p>After a few vicious Google searches, I discovered what negative cycles were. More importantly, I made a startling realization: people in the real world actually care about these negative cycles! And just think, if negative cycles are relevant to those who are incredibly drunk, imagine how important they&rsquo;ll be to those who are sober! Clearly, this market has been vali &ndash; <em>wait for it</em> &ndash;</p>

<p>dated! Yes, reality shows on Bravo are heavily edited for added drama, but no one can edit&hellip; inspiration.</p>

<h2><strong>What is NegaCycl?</strong></h2>

<p>Now, you may be asking &ldquo;What is NegaCycl?&rdquo; Yes, as you&rsquo;ve likely figured out, it&rsquo;s a portmanteau of &ldquo;negative&rdquo; and &ldquo;cycle&rdquo;, but there&rsquo;s a lot more to it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/gxfgcfg.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide10" /></p>

<p>Cycles are a part of a branch of computer science known as Graph Theory. In Graph Theory, graphs are networks which connect<em> blah blah blah</em>&hellip;</p>

<p>&hellip;this slide is boring. Moving on.</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide11.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide11" /></p>

<p>On this map are arbitrary numbers for each path which represent the amount of time it takes to go between each city. Let&rsquo;s say, for example, a person wants to go from Boston to New York. What&rsquo;s the route that will take the shortest total amount of time? Do you go Boston &ndash; San Diego &ndash; New York, or Boston &ndash; Atlanta &ndash; New York, or even Boston &ndash; Atlanta &ndash; St. Louis &ndash; New York? Solving it through brute force by calculating every possible route and their respective total times is not sexy.</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/jchjghjghj.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide12" /></p>

<p>In the previous slide, we made the implicit assumption that time always moves forward. That isn&rsquo;t necessarily true. Maybe in the future, some startup offering particle-accelerators-as-a-service gets too popular, their users accidently form a few black holes, and boom, time and space crack. Oops! It could happen to anyone, and once it does, time can move backward. In this example, you could go back and forth, or &ldquo;cycle&rdquo;, between Atlanta and St. Louis to go further and further back in time. In that case, the math to find the shortest route between Boston and New York becomes even less sexy.</p>

<p>We can&rsquo;t have unsexiness. We&rsquo;re a startup. We&rsquo;re sexy. And we know it.</p>

<p>Back to the Drunk Computer Science Trivia on Bravo: how do you solve negative cycles anyways? The cast member replied with<em> &ldquo;Are we talking Bellman&rsquo;s algorithm or Dijkstra&rsquo;s algorithm?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>And after a few more vicious Google searches, I discovered that the answer is&hellip; neither of those two algorithms because the show&rsquo;s cast members are dum-dums.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide14.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide14" /></p>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s get to the meat of the pitch: what<em> is</em> NegaCycl? It&rsquo;s simply a web app that calculates the route of the shortest amount of time for travel using the Bellman-Ford algorithm. The Bellman-Ford algorithm solves graphs containing these negative cycles, and thus in the context of travel, it can account for time moving backwards, as with Atlanta and St. Louis. Easy peasy lemon squeezy.</p>

<p>Currently, NegaCycl is the <em>only</em> startup that accounts for fractures in the space-time continuum. Sure, startups might use APIs from Facebook and Twitter in their own code, but no other startup uses the API&hellip; of the universe. Since the underlying 12 lines of pseudocode are so elegant and efficient, we&rsquo;ll be able to scale without breaking a sweat. We&rsquo;re going to do PHP, because Facebook uses PHP for their server language and Facebook has over 1 billion users, so it&rsquo;s legit. Lastly, this time-routing technology would be very useful for enterprise shipping companies, such as UPS and FedEx, and we could potentially license it to them. Imagine: you could receive your delivery from an online order&hellip;before you even order it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide15.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide15" /></p>

<p>Unfortunately, I don&rsquo;t have a working demo of the app to show you today, but here&rsquo;s a screenshot of the prototype. We&rsquo;re using Twitter Bootstrap as the core framework for our front-end interface, as it looks cool and it&rsquo;s free, and that&rsquo;s good enough for me!</p>

<h2><strong>How will we market NegaCycl?</strong></h2>

<p>There are a lot of players in the travel space. How will we market NegaCycl so that it stands out from the crowd? You&rsquo;ll see that we have that very well planned.</p>

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide18.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide18" /></p>

<p>With startups, one of the key drivers of success is who you know, and who <em>they</em> know. That&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;ve decided to utilize two very influential tech celebrities to help publicize NegaCycl: Michael Arrington, the founder and former head editor of TechCrunch, and Robert Scoble, a popular journalist with hundreds of thousands of social media followers,</p>

<p>I, personally, am Facebook friends with both of them. They&rsquo;re my biffles, my best friends for life!</p>

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide19.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide19" /></p>

<p>During my time as a business major at Carnegie Mellon University, I&rsquo;ve learnt that brand identity is one of the most important assets for a business. Between two otherwise equal startups, the one whose logo is cleanest and whose web pages are shiniest will be the winner.</p>

<p>The name &ldquo;NegaCycl&rdquo; is very catchy. Note how there&rsquo;s no vowels in Cycl! Poor literacy is kewl nowadays, and the blatant deliberate typographical mistake will make our grammar-obsessed potential users much more likely to remember our name and curse us out on public forums. Hey, free advertising!</p>

<p>Additionally,  I&rsquo;ve taken great care in designing a unique logo myself for NegaCycl, one that will be remembered forever. Do you know how long it took me to align all the vectors to create this excellent logo? Like, 20 minutes. 20 minutes! Have you noticed that the logo looks like a bicycle? That&rsquo;s completely intentional. Have you noticed that the face is negative? That&rsquo;s also completely intentional. The visual subtext in this logo is quite clearly indicative of a logo for a future Fortune 500 company: a company named NegaCycl!</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide22.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide22" /></p>

<p>And now, my plan for social media promotion with NegaCycl. I&rsquo;ve developed a automated script that does community management for our Facebook brand page by using a proven effective strategy. At no additional cost. Trust me, I read <em>The Lean Startup</em> by Eric Ries, I&rsquo;m an expert at being lean.*<br/>
*</p>

<p>We start by finding cute pictures, which are statistically proven to have a greater response rate than boring startup press announcements <em>ugh</em>. The automated script parses Reddit, a link and image aggregator, and its API for the top cute pictures of the day. Then, the script applies a NegaCycl watermark in the lower-right corner of the image, and posts the image on our Facebook page for our fans to see. When our users inevitably share the image, we get <strong>all</strong> the credit. Everyone on Facebook will see NegaCycl as the harbinger of happiness and cuddles.</p>

<p>In the post message, we will ask questions to users, as they also make people more likely to respond. &ldquo;What do you think of this picture?&rdquo; &ldquo;What are you doing today?&rdquo; &ldquo;What is the answer to life, the universe, and everything?&rdquo; Things like that. The automated script does not spend time reading the user responses to the question because it&rsquo;s an asshole.</p>

<p>Lastly, we will encourage the users to Like, Share, and Comment on our pictures. Whenever a Facebook user does any of those three things on a NegaCycl post, the NegaCycl post then appears on the News Feeds of that user&rsquo;s friends, and the cycle repeats until Facebook is <em>ours. </em>And once we conquer Facebook, we&rsquo;ll conquer Twitter as well, and I guess we&rsquo;ll also conquer Google%2B because why not it&rsquo;s not hard.</p>

<p>We become a successful travel startup, or we pivot into a generic image regurgitator. Either works for me, really.</p>

<h2><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>

<p>You&rsquo;ve seen how we came up with the idea. You&rsquo;ve seen how we&rsquo;re going to execute the idea. You&rsquo;ve seen how we&rsquo;re going to promote the idea. NegaCycl will indeed change the way you use travel apps: you no longer have to ask &ldquo;where do I want to go to&rdquo;, but <em>when</em> do I want to go to.</p>

<p>NegaCycl may be a crazy idea for a startup, sure. We don&rsquo;t use any photo filters! However, it&rsquo;s the crazy ideas that are the most disruptive in Silicon Valley, and not only will we disrupt the travel space, but we will also disrupt the travel time.</p>

<p>As we said earlier, we ask you for $2.01 million, and we&rsquo;ll use this couple of millions to make a couple of billions. Piece of cake. Chocolate cake.</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide25.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide25" /></p>

<p>We will put your money to very good use.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re going to spend $1 million for a waterfront office in San Francisco. I want to look outside the window and be able to see the Golden Gate Bridge and Alcatraz. Alcatraz is so much fun!</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll use another $1 million to throw the most epic toga launch party ever. Bravo had a good one, and we&rsquo;re to going to top that. One word: Lions. Gladiatorial combat, anyone? We&rsquo;ll get so much press and word-of-mouth advertising, especially if someone gets killed!</p>

<p>Lastly, we&rsquo;ll use the remaining $0.01 million to hire a programmer to make the damn app.</p>

<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/Slide26.png?resize=625%2C352" alt="Slide1" /></p>

<p>In all, I hope that you&rsquo;ll invest your money in our startup. So, what did you think of this presentation? Do you think you&rsquo;ll invest in NegaCycl? Like, share, and comment!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Electronic Arts "Gives Away" Thousands Of Free Games Due To No Server-Side Validation]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/client-side-validation-is-hard-mode/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-14T21:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/client-side-validation-is-hard-mode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Early Saturday morning, <a href="http://www.gamefaqs.com/boards/916373-pc/64312901">various gaming forums</a> (and, more importantly, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/GameDeals/comments/11ewb0/use_the_code_os3874xvc_to_get_20_off_origin/">Reddit</a>) obtained a promotional code from mega gaming company Electronic Arts for their Origin gaming distribution service. This code entitled the user to purchase any EA published or developed game for $20 off, and if the game was less than $20, the game was free. <a href="http://www.gamers-association.com/2012/10/free-game-from-eas-origin/">Games that were made free</a> using this coupon included hit series such as Dead Space, Mass Effect, Dragon Age, and Battlefield, so the rewards for the coupon were actually pretty worthwhile. Best of all, there are no catches and no gimmicks; input promo code OS3874XVC, get game.</p>

<p>The code was apparently rewarded after taking a survey regarding Origin, with the reward being one free game. The operative word being &ldquo;one.&rdquo; Some gamers, out of curiosity, discovered that by entering the code via both the store browser-interface and the store client-interface, they could get a free game twice. Gamers inferred the logical technical conclusion; EA was not checking server-side that the code was only being used once. Later, gamers noted that <a href="http://www.overclock.net/t/1315674/free-20-in-origin-code/410#post_18359737">simply inputting the code while logged-out</a> allows them to use the promo code an <em>unlimited</em> amount of times.</p>

<p>Needless to say, hilarity ensued.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What Went Wrong</h2>

<p><a href="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/origin2.png"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/origin2.png" alt="A picture of the Origin desktop client. Not as pretty as a startup website." /></a></p>

<p>Even the most amateur web developer knows to follow three important rules for data validation:</p>

<ol>
<li>Never trust the client.</li>
<li>Never trust the client.</li>
<li><strong>Never trust the damn client!</strong></li>
</ol>


<p>The proper way to implement a promo code is logical: when the user attempts to apply a promo code, the server checks, <em>has the user used this promo code before?</em> by querying<em> SELECT FROM transactions WHERE user_id = current_user AND promo_code = &ldquo;OS3874XVC&rdquo;</em>. If the result set is empty, then the user hasn&rsquo;t used the code, and everything&rsquo;s good to go. Otherwise, then that user has used the promo code before, and an appropriate error should be thrown are displayed to the user. This would be repeated at the checkout phase when the server actually charges the credit card, to ensure that the correct amount is charged and that the user has not committed and shenanigans in the meantime. All would be well. *****</p>

<p>For some reason, inputting the code in different clients (which should validate against the same backend database) still allowed the code to be input twice. And, for a very confusing reason, a workflow exists that allows the user to input a promo code while logged out, with presumably the intention of it being validated when the user eventually logs in (which it isn&rsquo;t).</p>

<h2>Aftermath</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2012/04/09/why-ea-won-the-worst-company-in-america-award/"><img src="http://www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2012/04/09/why-ea-won-the-worst-company-in-america-award/" alt="Two wrongs make a right...?" /></a></p>

<p>The exploit was closed at around 1AM PST, 18 hours after its discovery (which, to be honest, it pretty embarrassing for an exploit that causes a significant amount of lost potential revenue). Here&rsquo;s where it gets interesting.</p>

<p>A little background: in the gaming community, EA is not the most liked company; in fact, it was voted <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2012/04/09/why-ea-won-the-worst-company-in-america-award/">the worst company in America</a> due to a very large number of privacy, security, and ethical debacles. Last year, EA launched its own digital distribution service, Origin, which would compete with Valve&rsquo;s Steam service by being the sole provider of high-profile EA-published games, including Battlefield 3 and Mass Effect 3. (the former being the only reason I downloaded Origin). Speaking from experience, Origin is very buggy and unpolished compared to Steam, and actually drains system resources when idle.</p>

<p>According to <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/gaming/comments/11ggi2/reddit_during_the_recent_origin_discount_coupon/">another Reddit thread</a>, when news of this exploit hit, many gamers went on a downloading spree, and downloaded nearly every free game possible for two reasons. One, if EA is technically incompetent enough to allow such a severe bug to exist, they won&rsquo;t have the technical skills to discern who used the promo code more than once. Two, <em>it is retribution for EA being a terrible company</em>.</p>

<p>What will EA do to punish people who exploited? Are the users at fault here since it&rsquo;s very possible to accidently use the code twice? If so, is it fair to ban <em>ever</em>y<em>one</em> who has used multiple promo codes if innocent people might be banned?</p>

<p>UPDATE (10/15 1:14AM): EA will <a href="http://forum.ea.com/eaforum/posts/list/60/9040620.page">&ldquo;honor all sales made with the coupon code,&rdquo;</a>  implying that they will <strong>not</strong> ban people who utilized the exploit.</p>

<p>If the promo was a marketing tactic from Electronic Arts to promote Origin usage, it failed immensely on their end, due to a trivial amount missing lines of code on their server.</p>

<p>-Max</p>

<p><em>PS: I downloaded exactly one game through the promo code as was intended and stated by a <a href="http://i.imgur.com/4zg7X.jpg">forum user&rsquo;s chat log with Origin Support</a>; I did not attempt to reproduce the exploit itself for verification purposes due to the potential consequences. I like my Battlefield 3!</em></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>I admit that the SQL pseudocode provided here is an oversimplified, general </strong>solution for the validation issue<strong>, since that I do not have knowledge of EA&rsquo;s database structure and scale.</strong></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>** Discussion on Hacker News <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4652129">here</a>!</strong></p>

<p><strong>*</strong>| Discussion on Reddit <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/technology/comments/11hem0/electronic_arts_gives_away_thousands_of_free/">here</a> and <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/11h9nj/electronic_arts_gives_away_thousands_of_free/">here</a>.**</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
