<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/rss.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-29T08:38:32-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Probabilistically Generating GitHub Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/innovation-rng/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-29T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/innovation-rng</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Grant Slatton made an amusing post on Hacker News yesterday titled &ldquo;<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6815282">Show HN: Probabilistically Generating HN Post Titles</a>&rdquo;. By using the statistical principle of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain">Markov chains</a>, Slatton was able to <a href="http://grantslatton.com/hngen/">generate eerily-realistic Hacker News headlines</a> such as &ldquo;Facebook detects if you are not a pilot&rdquo; and &ldquo;The No. 1 Habit of Highly Effective Mediocre Entrepreneurs.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Could Markov chains be applied to any other data sets for hilarious effect? By using Slatton&rsquo;s <a href="https://gist.github.com/grantslatton/7694811">Python implementation of Markov chains</a> plus 300,000 descriptions of public GitHub repositories retrieved from their API, I discovered that statistical randomness can indeed create funny innovation.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/github-wordcloud-mac.png"></p>

<p>You can download a list of 1,000 Markov chain-generated projects <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/github_markov.txt">here</a>. Here are a few interesting ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>MaNGOS is a free, Open Source implementation of a tag at relatively random intervals.</li>
<li>A Warhammer 40k simulator to teach myself both OpenGL and Clojure</li>
<li>Perl interface to Git repositories via Ruby.</li>
<li>A windows live messenger network client written in Erlang</li>
<li>Rails plugin which allows to talk anonymously and use tripcodes if you want.</li>
<li>A Firebug extension for displaying the latest from Hacker News</li>
<li>Sinatra-inspired JavaScript node.js web development framework for lua. Inspired by rspec</li>
<li>Inverted Index on top of Tornado</li>
<li>Android LED interface library for various wave propagation techniques.</li>
<li>CatchAPI is a Java API to remove the need for boring project setup.</li>
<li>Adds basic social networking capabilities to your lighting system based on the concept of the Working with Rails</li>
<li>Brute force your OpenERP data integration with flatfiles</li>
<li>Culerity integrates Cucumber and Celerity in order to shutdown the computer.</li>
<li>Parses ANSI color codes and converts them to iphone compatible mp4s using HandBrake</li>
<li>A simple OFX (Open Financial Exchange) parser built on top of WordPress. Rolopress core theme</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>The code used to get the project descriptions from the GitHub API is available in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/get-github-repo-descriptions">this GitHub repository</a>, and you can download the ~300k repo descriptions <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/github_repo_desc.zip">here</a>. [5MB .zip]</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reddit is Growing Slowly, but Surely]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-18T07:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reddit has certainty received more attention in the mainstream media with its involvement in such events as the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/business/media/bombings-trip-up-reddit-in-its-turn-in-spotlight.html?_r=0">Boston Marathon Bombings</a> and <a href="hhttp://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/z1c9z/i_am_barack_obama_president_of_the_united_states/">President Obama&rsquo;s AMA</a>. But has this publicity led to increase in overall activity on the site?</p>

<p>I analyzed the daily number of submissions from over two years, August 6th, 2011 to September 25, 2013 (41 million submissions total), to see which events, if any, have affected Reddit&rsquo;s growth rate. As it turns out, Reddit grows by itself.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/reddit_daily-mac.png"></p>

<p>Reddit&rsquo;s growth over the past two years has been almost entirely <strong>linear</strong>, with no notable acceleration in submission activity at any point in time.</p>

<p>Running a linear regression on daily number of submissions vs. number of days since the first date (8/6/11) reveals that the expected increase in number of submissions each successive day on average is <strong>66.48 submissions</strong>  (+1,948 submissions each successive month, +24,259 submissions each successive year)</p>

<p>This growth rate alone explains <strong>86.83%</strong> of the variation in number of submissions, indicating that external factors such as media publicity explain the remaining 13% of the variation.</p>

<p>From a business perspective, it&rsquo;s impressive that Reddit still continues to grow for being such a mature internet business, but prospective investors for a rumored <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/06/reddit-rumored-to-be-raising-money-at-a-400-million-valuation/">fundraising at a $400 Million valuation</a> might be weary that Reddit&rsquo;s growth is only linear, in contrast to the <strong>exponential</strong> growth of other startups such as Snapchat. (In fairness, submission activity may not necessarily correlate with revenue-driving content consumption activity)</p>

<p>A couple stray observations:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>On January 18th, 2012, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the minimum among the two-year period due to Reddit&rsquo;s participation in the Internet blackout in protest of SOPA. (Reddit&rsquo;s blackout was only from 8AM to 8PM EST, which is why there are a nonzero number of submissions for that day).</p></li>
<li><p>On April 1st, 2013, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the maximum among the two-year period due to April Fool&rsquo;s Day, and the numerous amount of submissions for <em>X</em> brand/website&rsquo;s well-timed joke. However, I&rsquo;m not entirely sure why there&rsquo;s a spike for April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2013, but not April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2012.</p></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data used to create the time-series chart at <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGZ2Zkk1MGF3SjZxdC1sRzV5SW9zRWc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Subreddits on Reddit are the Largest?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/subreddit-size/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T07:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/subreddit-size</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit&rsquo;s</a> subreddits cover, quite literally, an infinite amount of different topics. But which of its subreddits are the biggest?</p>

<p>Sure, Reddit is known for subreddits such as /r/pics and /r/aww, but in actuality, many of the lesser-known subreddits are much bigger than you think.</p>

<p>By tabulating the data of 37,561,369 total sitewide Link submissions, from 12/18/2011 to 9/26/2013, I created a tree map of the Top 100 subreddits by the number of Link submissions to that subreddit.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/subreddit-treemap.png" title="" ></p>

<p>In the tree map, the size of the rectangle and the saturation of the blue color indicate the relative size of the subreddit.</p>

<p>Unsurprisingly, the <a href="http://blog.reddit.com/2013/07/new-default-subreddits-omgomgomg.html">default subreddits</a>, which all new users are subscribed to, are ranked mostly at the top. However, subreddits such as /r/POLITICO, /r/leagueoflegends, and /r/trees are higher (no pun intended) than most of the default subreddits.</p>

<p>And then you have the meta subreddits such as /r/ModerationLog and /r/reportthespammers, showing that people spend a considerable amount of time talking about Reddit itself.</p>

<p>Gaming has a very significant presence as well, with /r/Minecraft, /r/DotA2, and /r/tf2. (notably for the latter two, the trading subreddits for the respective games have significantly more link submissions than the subreddits themselves.)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth nothing that these Top 100 subreddits only account for <strong>46.3% of all Reddit link submissions</strong>. Even the Top 500 subreddits only account for 66.2% of all Reddit submissions. The density of link submissions clearly follows a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_tail">long-tail</a> distribution, where most of the content is centralized from the top subreddits. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to see if Reddit is able to utilize that treasure trove of links in the future.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data for the Top 500 subreddits in  <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGQzd0dIQkk1aXRRRkxEY3g0ZmQtWGc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>, and you can see the code use to create the tree map in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/treemap-of-reddit-top-subreddits">this GitHub repository</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do startups with short names containing few vowels raise more money?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/10/wrds-and-vwls/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-14T07:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/10/wrds-and-vwls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One reason startups use crazy and bizarre names like <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">NegaCycl</a> and <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/">Filtrzzz</a> is to ensure that their name is unique, making it easier to acquire the .com domain name and Twitter handle for their startup. Another reason is to make their startup sound <em>kewl</em> and theoretically make the name more memorable in the minds of users and potential investors.</p>

<p>Dakwak, Wibki, Zeef, Funifi. These aren&rsquo;t random words: these are funded startups which were featured at <a href="http://startupalley.techcrunch.com/">TechCrunch Disrupt Startup Alley 2013</a>. And then you have startups such as Lyft, SCVNGR, and Fastly, which have all raised <em>tens of millions of dollars</em> in venture capital.</p>

<p>Do startups with these short, low-vowel names actually raise more money than startups with traditional names?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First, let&rsquo;s take a look at the association between the length of words in the English language and the number of vowels that they contain:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/english-words.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>In the English language, the majority of the words have 8 letters, with 3 of those letters being vowels. (8,3) is also the center of the density distribution for the heat map, spreading outward.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s compare the vowel distribution of normal English words to the distribution of the names of startups that have successfully raised venture capital, in order to identify just how many funded startups have quirky names:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/count-startups.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>Wait, the two distributions are nearly identical! Both graphs are centered at about (8,3), radiating outward. This implies that the number of startups with uniquely-constructed names are outliers and not the typical names for startups.</p>

<p>But that doesn&rsquo;t answer the core question: sure, fewer funded startups have weird names relative to the amount of total funded startups, but do they raise more money on average than startups with typical names?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/mean-startups-fund.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>Nope.</p>

<p>There is no discernible pattern for the average amount raised, unlike with the previous two charts. For the vast majority of the possible combinations of name length and $ vowels, the range of capital raised is between $5M and $25M. There are higher values at the lower-end of the graph (low length, low vowels), but that can be attributed to the relatively low amount of startup data for those combinations to smooth out the average. (e.g. the $78M spike at 3 length, 2 vowels is due to the always-lovely <a href="http://www.crunchbase.com/company/aol">AOL</a> and a <a href="http://googlepress.blogspot.com/2005/12/time-warners-aol-and-google-to-expand_20.html">$1 billion investment from Google</a>, and there are only 15 other startups in the segment.)</p>

<p>In fact, the statistical correlation between name length and funding, number of vowels and funding, and ratio of length to vowels and funding, are all effectively <strong>zero</strong>.</p>

<p>Sure, quirky startup names may make it easier to find a domain name, but it won&rsquo;t necessarily give an edge in the investment process.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Data for English words from <a href="http://wordlist.sourceforge.net/">Kevin&rsquo;s Word List Page</a>, and data for the startup names/funding from <a href="http://info.crunchbase.com/about/crunchbase-data-exports/">CrunchBase&rsquo;s September Data Export</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[1 in 3 Links Submitted To Reddit Go To Imgur Or YouTube]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/09/reddit-imgur-youtube/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-29T10:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/09/reddit-imgur-youtube</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;ve been on <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a>, you may have noticed that many link submissions go to &ldquo;imgur.com&rdquo;. <a href="http://imgur.com/">Imgur</a>, an image hosting service that launched on Reddit a few years ago and has seen outstanding growth ever since, even <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2013/09/26/imgur-traffic-milestone-100m-uniques/">surpassing Reddit itself</a>.</p>

<p>But how many of Reddit&rsquo;s many, many links are actually links to Imgur? As it turns out, Imgur, along with YouTube, account for <em>32%</em> of the links submitted to Reddit.</p>

<p>Using Reddit&rsquo;s API, I have downloaded about 5 million link submissions from Reddit, accounting for nearly two months of activity from July 22nd to September 26th. I complied a list of the most-frequent link destination domains for the links submitted anywhere on Reddit. The results were interesting.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/links722_926.png"></p>

<p>The imgur domains (i.imgur.com and imgur.com) account for <strong>23.7%</strong> of all links submitted to Reddit, and the YouTube domains (youtube.com and youtu.be) account for <strong>8.2%</strong> of all links.</p>

<p>Two websites account for <strong>32%</strong> of all links submitted to Reddit (i.e. 1 in every 3 submitted links go to Imgur or YouTube), and no other website is remotely close. Not the meme sites, not the music sites, not the news sites, not the <em>porn</em> sites: Reddit is images and video.</p>

<p>But <em>where</em> on Reddit are the Imgur and YouTube links most prominent?</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a chart of the top subreddits, by percentage of all  Imgur links submitted on Reddit:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/imgur722_926.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting to note how the <em>funny</em> subreddit has more Imgur links than the <em>pics</em> subreddit.</p>

<p>For YouTube, and the percentage of all YouTube links submitted on Reddit by subreddit:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/youtube722_926.png"></p>

<p><em>Videos</em> wins as you might expect, but <em>Music</em> is in second place. Along with <em>listentothis</em>,
<em>Metal</em>, and <em>hiphopheads</em>, YouTube is the de facto website for <em>music</em> as well as video. Gaming is also  very popular with YouTube links, with <em>gaming</em>, <em>leagueoflegends</em>, and <em>Minecraft</em>.</p>

<p>Images and video are the backbone of Reddit, and both Imgur and YouTube are the primary sources. Although, there appears to be a nontrivial demand for pure music websites such as <a href="https://soundcloud.com/">SoundCloud</a> and gaming video websites such as <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/">Twitch.tv</a> &hellip;could there be another big success story in the making?</p>

<hr />

<p><em>The tabulated data used to create each of the three charts is located at <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGxoVGFyX19hV2paMk5lOFRvNXlkcnc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a> for your perusal.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Universities Produce the Most Successful Startup Founders?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/alma-mater-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-20T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/alma-mater-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you read startup funding announcements on tech blogs frequently, you&rsquo;ve may have noticed that these startup founders have often attended prestigious universities. Founders who have graduated from Ivy League schools, such as Harvard, Yale and Princeton, unsurprisingly raise millions for their startups. Of course, top tier tech schools such as Stanford, MIT, and Carnegie Mellon foster a strong technical and entrepreneurial background: attributes which venture capitalists seek when investing in a startup founder. <em>(Disclosure: I&rsquo;m a Carnegie Mellon alumnus)</em></p>

<p>Do the tech universities produce more funded graduates than the Ivy League universities? Do the founders from Ivy League Universities receive more funding than those from the top tier tech universities?</p>

<p>Using TechCrunch&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.crunchbase.com/">CrunchBase</a> API, I obtained the data of about 2,500 startup founders in the United States who have created a startup which has received investment from venture capitalists.</p>

<p>With that data, I found some rather interesting trends.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Which universities produced the most amount of graduates who have received funding?</h1>

<p>Thousands of university graduates attempt to make a startup, but most will not succeed. Are the graduates of some universities more frequently successful?</p>

<p>Here are the Top 16 universities with the most number of successfully-funded graduates:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/founder-colleges.png"></p>

<p>Stanford has the most amount of funded graduates, which is unsurprising as it&rsquo;s located in the Silicon Valley heart of venture capital.</p>

<p>Seven out of the eight Ivy League Universities (colored green on the chart) are present, but most of the Ivies are  in the middle of the chart. MIT and UC Berkeley each have nearly <em>double</em> the amount of successful graduates from Yale and Columbia.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth noting that Tel Aviv University, an Israeli university, ties Duke University at 21.</p>

<h1>Which university&rsquo;s graduates have cumulatively raised the most amount of total funding?</h1>

<p>Another way to measure success is through the success of the founders&#8217; subsequent startups and the amount of venture capital they have raised.</p>

<p>Here are the Top 8 universities whose graduates have received the most amount of funding:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/sum-funding.png"></p>

<p>Harvard and Stanford graduates are very close in terms of total funding raised. However, there&rsquo;s a clear <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law">Power Law</a> in effect, as those two along with UC Berkeley, have  produced founders who&rsquo;ve generated much, much more venture funding than those of the other universities.</p>

<h1>Which university&rsquo;s graduates raise the most amount of money in their first round of funding on average?</h1>

<p>Startup founders with big, world changing ideas need lots of venture capital. Only the founders with <em>good</em> ideas will actually receive it.</p>

<p>Here are the average amount of first-round funding for the top 16 universities with the most number of successfully-funded graduates:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/avg-first-raised.png"></p>

<p>Carnegie Mellon and Princeton, which had a relatively low number of funded founders and a relatively low number of total capital raised, instead have a <em>significantly</em> higher amount of average first funding. UCLA also placed. Perhaps the students from these three universities tend to have more ambitious startup ideas?</p>

<p>At first glance, Stanford and Harvard appear to be the kings of startups. They have the most amount of graduates, and the most amount of total venture capital raised. The tech blogs would surely consider that a success, but could the greater funding for CMU/Princeton lead to the creation of the next billion-dollar startup? We can only wait and see.</p>

<p><em>UPDATE: As pointed out by robotcookies on the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6075862">corresponding Hacker News thread</a>, I missed UCLA in the first draft, which had 29 funded graduates. The charts have been updated.</em></p>

<hr />

<p>You are welcome to use the founder data from CrunchBase by <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddEV1LUpaQUVsdmJYcERoM0FNU3lPcVE&amp;usp=sharing">viewing the data on Google Drive</a>, or by <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/3jz2wsr4d6fc4t6/founders_w_college.csv">downloading the raw CSV</a>.</p>

<p><em>Notes:</em></p>

<ul>
<li><em>University data was standardized to make analysis easier (e.g. for Carnegie Mellon, the founders who listed their institution as &ldquo;Carnegie Mellon University&rdquo;, &ldquo;Carnegie Mellon,&rdquo; and &ldquo;CMU,&rdquo; all had their institution changed to be &ldquo;CMU&rdquo;.)</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #1 measures unique founders, so it does not double-count a founder who has founded more than one  funded startup.</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #2 assumes equal contribution of each founder to the funding: if a startup has a total funding of $100,000 with 2 founders, the amount used for the chart will be $50,000 for each founder.</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #3 ignores startup data for the chart which has a Series B, Series C, or Series D listed as their first round on CrunchBase, or if the amount raised was not provided.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Statistical Analysis of Medium.com Submissions to Hacker News]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/medium-normal/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-02T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/medium-normal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://medium.com/">Medium</a>, a relatively new startup by Twitter cofounder Evan Williams, is a blog network that emphasizes simplicity and quality above everything else. Writers on the invite-only platform typically post stories about deeply personal topics, such as fighting adversity, never giving up your dreams, changing flawed systems, and other things that make the readers feel happy. One of my favorite articles on Medium, <a href="https://medium.com/editors-picks/57a0128b53c9">Choosing Minecraft Over Disney</a>, describe how a parent&rsquo;s children chose technology over television.</p>

<p>As of recently, the frequency of links to Medium posts on the popular tech-oriented link aggregator <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news">Hacker News</a> has been increasing at an alarming rate. Since Medium&rsquo;s tales of triumph appeal to the ambitious entrepreneurs and startup founders of HN, the submissions are usually rapidly upvoted and easily make the front page, with  muted text helpfully noting that the link goes to medium.com. As a result, there has been <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5968593">cognitive</a> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5974209">dissonance</a> on Hacker News whether Medium has too strong a presence on the aggregator, or worse,  potentially gaming the system.</p>

<p>Using the <a href="https://www.hnsearch.com/api">HNSearch API</a>, I analyzed the submissions of links under the medium.com domain to Hacker News to see just how Medium keeps surging in popularity. The results, as always, are very revealing.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The collected data is a sample of 1,000 links (out of 1,355 total) submitted to Hacker News under the medium.com domain.  Each data point contains the Title of the article, the HN user who submitted it, the amount of upvotes it received, the time it was posted (in PST), and links to both the article and the HN comments thread for reference. You can view the <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddDBPNFlMQUYyX1FhUkVVY2g1TmVLM1E&amp;usp=sharing">data on Google Drive</a>, or download <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/xnktwi9kheyqf6v/medium.csv">the raw CSV</a> and play with the data yourself.</p>

<p>What does the data tell us about Medium?</p>

<hr />

<h1>How quickly has medium.com grown in popularity in the past few months?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-month.png"></p>

<p>Medium was launched <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/08/01/medium-obvious/">in August 2012</a>, and received relatively little attention as evidenced by the graph. But 8 months later, the frequency of medium.com submissions hockey-sticked, receiving almost 5x growth from March 2013 to April 2013. That certainly explains one of the reasons why the rise in medium.com links is just being noticed now.</p>

<hr />

<h1>When are medium.com posts being written and submitted to HN?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-by-hour.png"></p>

<p>The time of day a blog post is submitted makes all the difference in the world, especially if your blog platform targets readers in a specific region. Medium links are frequently posted and submitted around 10am PST / 1pm EST, which is smart as it&rsquo;s relatively early in the day for those living in the United States, and your potential readers would be more likely to read your post, and HN users are more likely to upvote.</p>

<hr />

<h1>Who are the Hacker News users who most frequently submit medium.com articles?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-top-submitters.png"></p>

<p>Of the 1,000 submissions, there were only 622 unique submitters of medium.com links, each submitting an average of 1.61 posts. Most only post their own articles, but others, like <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=rpsubhub">rpsubhub</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=mrbird">mrbird</a>, and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=nvk">nvk</a> submit Medium.com links more often. However, none of those users appear to be associated with Medium; they just submit links rather frequently.</p>

<hr />

<h1>What are the types of articles on medium.com submitted to Hacker News?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-wordcloud.png"></p>

<p>Medium&rsquo;s category system is somewhat obtuse, so I parsed the keywords from the titles of the submissions (using a method similar to <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data/">my last post</a>) in order to get an idea what type of content is submitted most from Medium. There are lots of posts that ask rhetorical questions (<strong>What?</strong>, <strong>How?</strong>, <strong>Why?</strong>), and even more posts about the personal self with <strong>I</strong>. Not only is Medium using the right language to facilitate interaction, it&rsquo;s also hitting the interests of HNers with keywords such as <strong>Design</strong> and <strong>Facebook</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h1>How successful <em>are</em> medium.com articles on Hacker News?</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/medium-front-page.png"></p>

<p>Out of the 1,000 submissions, only 158 had atleast 10 upvotes, which is enough to get the link to the front page, but not necessarily enough to keep it there. The graph is heavily right-skewed, with only 38 submissions getting above 100 points. It shows that medium.com links so not guarantee success, and even if you hit the front page, you have a low chance of hitting the coveted #1 ranking.</p>

<hr />

<p>Medium is definitely growing. HN is receiving more and more submissions which appeal to the average HN user, and posts are being submitted at all hours of the day. However, having a post at medium.com is not a panacea that will make your blog post be seen by thousands of people; you still need to write something interesting.</p>

<p>Time will tell. But if HN does indeed get bored of Medium, I believe the problem will correct itself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Predicting the Number of Likes on a Facebook Status With Statistical Keyword Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What makes people click the Like button on Facebook Statuses? Does the status say something funny? Does it contain a cool link or a funny photo? Does the status actively engage its readers?</p>

<p>Needless to say, brands on Facebook want to know the answers to these questions. The more people that Like their statuses on their Facebook Pages, the more exposure they gain, and the more money they earn. Many, many companies have been created for the sole purpose of maximizing the number of Facebook Likes.</p>

<p>By 2013, most brands have realized that photo posts and statuses that ask a question <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/questions-equals-reponses/">will generate <em>much</em> higher numbers</a> of Likes. Personally, that&rsquo;s not why <em>I</em> like a given Facebook status: I Like statuses that contain new and exciting things that are relevant to my interests. The first thing I read in a status is the Message: if the message is boring and uninteresting, then there&rsquo;s no reason for me to Like the status needlessly.</p>

<p>Can the keywords and language in a Facebook Status predict the number of Likes the status receives?</p>

<p>Running multivariate regressions on keywords from thousands of Facebook statuses, I&rsquo;ve discovered that the language used in a status <em>does</em> help predict the number of Likes a status receives, and actually could help brands learn much more about their fans.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Setup</h1>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/rdataset.png"></p>

<p>In order to draw accurate conclusions from the analysis, large amounts of data are needed (and there&rsquo;s no such thing as too much data).</p>

<p>I decided to analyze the Facebook Pages of 3 extremely popular News sources: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cnn">CNN</a>, the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/nytimes">New York Times</a>, and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/bbcworldnews">BBC World News</a>. All three Pages have millions of fans, post the same types of Facebook statuses, and post statuses extremely frequently to Facebook (around 8-9 times a day). The statuses analyzed will be from June 1st 2012 to June 1st 2013, in order to both gather a large sample size (~3,000  statuses from each Page) and a ensure a consistent apples-to-apples comparison between the three sources.</p>

<p>The raw data, code, and a detailed technical explanation of the statistical techniques used to process the data can be found in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-keyword-regression-analysis">this GitHub repository</a>. (tl;dr, it&rsquo;s an optimized <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Least_squares">least squares</a> regression)</p>

<p><em>Can the keywords and language in a Facebook Status predict the number of Likes the status receives?</em> We&rsquo;re ready to test this hypothesis.</p>

<hr />

<h1>CNN</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/cnn_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Bourdain        1962.98         0
NEWS            1272.64         0
Photo           1154.6          0
Barack          1002.45         0
City            851.82          0
Monday          705.42          0
Obama           632.2           0
United          578.77          0
Mitt            562.29          0.01
South           508.43          0.03
America         505.83          0.01
Watch           470.51          0
Boston          398.13          0.05
New             326.74          0.03
ET              -433.96         0
North           -467.05         0.02
Check           -503.5          0
Travel          -988.99         0.02
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for CNN are political keywords.</li>
<li><strong>NEWS</strong> (&ldquo;BREAKING NEWS&rdquo;) predicts more Likes than <strong>Photo</strong> (i.e. <a href="http://www.facebook.com/5550296508/posts/10151626042186509">Travel Photo of the Day</a>).</li>
<li><strong>Bourdain</strong> refers to Anthony Bourdain, who very recently began <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Bourdain:_Parts_Unknown">a food and travel show</a> on CNN. I assume that targets CNN&rsquo;s primary demographic.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Barack</strong> (Barack Obama) predicts more likes than just <strong>Obama</strong>.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Monday</strong> predicts more likes most other keywords. Garfield would be disappointed.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>North</strong> (North Korea) predicts a <em>decrease</em> in Likes from the average. Is North Korea boring?</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Check</strong> (&ldquo;Check this out!&rdquo;) also predicts a decrease in Likes from the average. This is interesting because this call-to-action is usually associated with the other keywords. Perhaps it&rsquo;s not necessary?</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h1>NYTimes</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/nytimes_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Mills           1022.9          0
Democratic      496.32          0
Krugman         456.31          0
Senate          431.05          0
London          373.67          0.01
Oscar           367.64          0.01
Sandy           364.61          0
Olympics        339.15          0.01
Sunday          317             0
Clinton         314.64          0.02
You             247.07          0
Obama           237.98          0
Opinion         221             0
Michael         204.2           0.03
Credit          191.92          0.05
Tuesday         187.22          0.03
Times           178.69          0
See             160.12          0.01
Romney          157.66          0.04
Ed              140.86          0.01
Read            -101.23         0.05
Here            -182.72         0.04
Facebook        -187.75         0.02
Are             -216.3          0.01
While           -293.77         0.04
Quotation       -322.29         0.02
House           -362.1          0.01
Thanksgiving    -369.88         0.05
Convention      -448.34         0.01
Jersey          -505.98         0
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for NYTimes are political keywords and current events, such as Hurricane <strong>Sandy</strong> and the <strong>London</strong> <strong>Olympics</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Mills</strong> refers to Doug Mills, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/5281959998/posts/10150252479219999">photographer</a> for the New York Times. The power of photos!</li>
<li><strong>You</strong> and <strong>See</strong> are impactful call-to-action keywords, even though they don&rsquo;t ask any questions. (Interestingly, <strong>Are</strong>, which implicitly asks a question, predicts a decrease in Likes. Maybe people don&rsquo;t Like questions?)</li>
<li><strong>Clinton</strong> has a bigger impact than <strong>Obama</strong>.</li>
<li>No one likes <strong>Jersey</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h1>BBC World News</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="http://minimaxir.com/img/bbcworldnews_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Malala          488.1           0
Japan           186.32          0
Britain         167.25          0.01
That            155.01          0.01
AFP             154.97          0.02
Travel          153.41          0
Now             148.39          0.02
Would           146.45          0.03
Delhi           137.85          0.04
Let             134.93          0.03
Future          127.49          0.02
Barack          125.79          0.02
An              122.18          0.03
David           111.78          0.04
Do              111.13          0
Israel          101.31          0.04
Impact          87.94           0.05
South           78.62           0.03
It              62.7            0.01
The             55.7            0
US              -47.84          0.02
On              -86.22          0.04
BBC             -103.58         0
Sunday          -117.01         0.03
After           -122.38         0.05
Thursday        -143.91         0.03
Twitter         -144.55         0
City            -147.16         0.02
Hi              -149.85         0.03
BBCNewsUS       -150.48         0.03
House           -176.86         0.01
California      -187.57         0
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for BBC World News are keywords describing news around the world. Unlike CNN and NYTimes, there are very few impactful keywords related to domestic politics (such as Prime Minister <strong>David</strong> Cameron, and even <strong>Barack</strong> is more impactful than him.)</li>
<li><strong>Malala</strong> refers to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malala_Yousafzai">Malala Youdsfzai</a>, a Pakistani activist who survived an assassination attempt.</li>
<li>Implicit question keywords such as <strong>Let</strong>, <strong>Do</strong>, and <strong>Would</strong> are all very effective.</li>
<li>The simple salutation of <strong>Hi</strong> predicts a decrease in Likes. There&rsquo;s a British joke here somewhere.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p>The language used in Facebook Statuses can be very useful in identifying what words Fans like, and what words will be most useful in generating the most exposure. While my analysis can&rsquo;t predict the <em>exact</em> number of Likes a Status receives, and I likely <a href="http://xkcd.com/882/">broke a few rules of statistics</a> in the process of making this post, the impact of language and specific keywords on social media interaction is an endeavor worth pursuing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook Hashtags Are Fundamentally Broken]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/hashtag-hashtag/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-14T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/hashtag-hashtag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/">Facebook</a> added <a href="http://newsroom.fb.com/News/633/Public-Conversations-on-Facebook">searchable hashtags</a> to all status updates and user comments. As with <a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a>, whenever a Facebook user posts an status with a #hashtag, that hashtag becomes clickable and leads to a News Feed of all other publically-visible posts with that hashtag.</p>

<p>The implementation of hashtags in Facebook is an obvious move. Advertisements and television shows display hashtags all the time to encourage users to Tweet about them: it&rsquo;s free marketing, after all. Facebook can piggy-back off those already-existing hashtags and grow user adoption <em>very</em> quickly, especially with Facebook-owned <a href="http://instagram.com/">Instagram</a> already supporting hashtags.</p>

<p>However, Facebook is a fundamentally different social network than Twitter. While Twitter uses hashtags to quickly categorize a feed of 140-character thoughts, Facebook&rsquo;s content feeds  typically consist of long posts and large images. Additionally, while posts on Twitter are explicitly public or private, Facebook&rsquo;s privacy settings are more granular: if users don&rsquo;t make their posts Public, the hashtag is essentially useless. And the brands are going to <em>love</em> hashtags. Maybe too much.</p>

<p>The magic of Facebook is flat-out incompatible with the magic of hashtags.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Too Long; Didn&rsquo;t Read</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/facebooktwitter.png"></p>

<p>Since Twitter posts have a length limit, they&rsquo;re short and occupy a consistent amount of space on the webpage. Facebook posts can be near-unlimited length, utilize a large amount of a white space between posts, and also potentially contain an equally-long comment section. As a result, 5 Twitter posts can use the same amount of screen real-estate as 2 Facebook posts. Given the already incredibly low signal-to-noise quality ratio of #hashtag feeds (as evident above), this makes reading hashtag feeds on Facebook a chore.</p>

<h2>A Thousand Words Takes A Lot Of Space</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/bieber-twitter.png"></p>

<p>Facebook displays pictures embedded in posts natively in the feed, while Twitter requires the user to click the Tweet to see the photo. In this case, the ratio of Twitter:Facebook posts can be even worse, in this case 6 Twitter posts for 1 Facebook post.</p>

<h2>If A Hashtag Isn&rsquo;t Seen, Was It Posted?</h2>

<p>Twitter is opt-in private posting. Facebook is opt-<em>out</em> private posting. That&rsquo;s a big usability problem.</p>

<p>The Facebook hashtag feeds only show posts that are explicitly  made Public (or posts from your Friends which are set to a privacy of Friends Only). If the user is unaware that their posts are not Public by default, then their posts containing the hashtag will never be seen and the user won&rsquo;t be able to participate in social hashtag feeds.  Although Facebook has made improvements in helping users set the intended privacy level of a post, it makes the process of posting much more deliberate and much less impulsive than Twitter.</p>

<h2>#brand #branding #marketing #yolo #swag</h2>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hashtagabuse.png"></p>

<p>Brands love hashtags. The more hashtags included in a Tweet, the more exposure the Tweet receives, right?</p>

<p>With Twitter, there&rsquo;s a limit on the number of hashtags in a Tweet due to the delicate balance between the number of hashtags, the length of the hashtags, and the length of the Tweet itself. On Facebook, you can include <strong>25</strong> hashtags in any post!</p>

<p>Since there&rsquo;s no consequence for abusing hashtags, expect to see more Facebook brands taking advantage this new free source of marketing. Expect to see Facebook get much more cluttered.</p>

<h2>Explicit Image Bombing</h2>

<p>A malicious user could theoretically insert shock images into popular hashtag feeds. During my testing of Facebook hashtags, there was a surprising amount of nudity in the seemingly-innocuous #many hashtag.</p>

<p>On Twitter, the volume of Tweets is much higher and the images are hidden by default, so the odds of such an attack working on Facebook are much higher than on Twitter.</p>

<h2>Comment Hashtags Different From Post Hashtags</h2>

<p>You can hashtag comments on Facebook posts like you can hashtag Facebook posts themselves. But hashtagged comments won&rsquo;t appear in the hashtag News Feed. Whereas on Twitter, Replies are also Tweets and can be hashtagged accordingly. This behavior isn&rsquo;t surprising, but it&rsquo;s still a big inconsistency.</p>

<hr />

<p>Will Facebook Hashtags fail due to the massive differences between Facebook and Twitter? It&rsquo;s hard to say, but I&rsquo;m skeptical that Facebook will be able to capture the hashtag magic.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When Uninstalling A PC Game Erases the Entire Hard Drive]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/working-as-intended/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/working-as-intended</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are many legitimate reasons for users to uninstall programs on their computer, such as freeing hard-disk space and lowering CPU overhead. A decade ago, when excessive hard-drive space was a luxury, avid PC gamers would frequently uninstall large, multi-gigabyte games that they were no longer playing in order to make space for new games.</p>

<p>Obviously, developers would prefer that their users not uninstall the software that they spent years creating.  Regardless, developers should ensure that the uninstall process works properly.</p>

<p>Otherwise, a poorly coded PC game uninstaller could delete not just the game, but the <em>entire hard drive</em>. That would be a problem.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Ragnarok</h1>

<p><span class="pull-right" style="padding: 20px"><a href="http://www.penny-arcade.com/comic/1999/01/06"><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/pennyarcademyth2.jpg" alt="" /></a></span></p>

<p>In late 1998, Bungie (which would later create the <a href="http://www.halowaypoint.com/en-us/">Halo</a> series) released <a href="http://mythipedia.wikia.com/wiki/Myth_II:_Soulblighter">Myth II: Soulblighter</a> for Windows. Myth II, a real-time tactics game, was received with great reception and highly-positive reviews.</p>

<p>But before the worldwide release, a Bungie employee <a href="http://halo.bungie.net/inside/history.aspx?link=juggernougat">uninstalled version 1.0</a> of Myth II, and afterwards, her PC refused to reboot:</p>

<blockquote><p>It was discovered by a very nice young lady in a Japanese office as she worked on the Asian versions of Myth – just as she was trying out the final build. She attempted to uninstall it from the main root folder of her hard drive – not brilliant, but pretty common practice – and perfectly fine for most games. The game proceeded to eat her hard drive like a fresh Bento Box.</p></blockquote>

<p>The Myth II Uninstaller worked by deleting the folder which contained the game files. However, this implementation assumed that the user installed Myth II in the default directory. (i.e. C:\Program Files\Myth II). If the user installed Myth II in a <em>different</em> directory, such as the <em>system root C:\</em>, then when the user uninstalled the game, <strong>all the files in the C drive were deleted.</strong> Boom.</p>

<p>As Bungie later explained <a href="http://www.macobserver.com/news/98/december/981229/bungierecall.html">in a press release</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>In certain unusual cases, using the Uninstaller can cause problems. If a user chooses an installation directory other than the default directory, they should NOT use the Uninstaller but should manually drag the Myth II folder into the Recycle bin and delete it.</p>

<p>Anyone who has the game but has not yet installed it is asked to wait for a new version of the Installer which we will release shortly. If you have already installed the game, there is no harm in playing it, but players should be careful not to use the Uninstall executable. If you have already Uninstalled and not experienced obvious problems, there is nothing to worry about.</p></blockquote>

<p>Calling the potential obliteration of an operating system a &ldquo;problem&rdquo; is an understatement.</p>

<p>Although the issue was not widespread, Bungie decided to do a recall of all Myth II CDs and redistribute a version 1.1, eliminating most of the game&rsquo;s profits in the process.</p>

<p>You could say that the Myth II version 1.0 uninstaller worked exactly as intended: it did indeed uninstall the game. It just worked <em>too</em> well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
