<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/rss.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-15T08:31:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Wikipedia Entries Which Are Most-Edited by Members of the U.S. Congress]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/caucus-needed/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-15T08:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/caucus-needed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, the Twitter account <a href="https://twitter.com/congressedits">@congressedits</a> launched. This account is a bot that tweets edits to Wikipedia that were made by members of the U.S. Congress, in order to help <a href="http://inkdroid.org/journal/2014/07/10/why-congressedits/">facilitate transparency</a>. The account <a href="https://github.com/edsu/anon">works</a> by automatically tweeting any Wikipedia edits made by anonymous contributors with IP addresses between the known IP address blocks of the <a href="http://whois.arin.net/rest/org/USSAA/nets">U.S. Senate</a> or the <a href="http://whois.arin.net/rest/org/ISUHR/nets">House of Representatives</a>.</p>

<p>Google&rsquo;s <a href="https://developers.google.com/bigquery/">BigQuery</a> tool has a <a href="https://developers.google.com/bigquery/docs/dataset-wikipedia">sample dataset</a> of Wikipedia data, representing the data on 314 million article edits up to April 2010. Out of curiosity, I wrote a query which returns the top 100 pages with the most amount of edits by Wikipedia contributors in the U.S. Senate&rsquo;s IP block.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/caucus-needed/senate-query.png"></p>

<p>Using this query for the Senate&rsquo;s IP block, and a similar one for the House of Representatives IP blocks, I retrieved the most-edited entries for both entities. You can access the spreadsheet of this data by <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/Congress_Wikipedia_Edits.pdf">downloading a .pdf</a> or by viewing the data online with <a href="https://www.icloud.com/iw/#numbers/BALY8siqBP4jYZq5E2OB20P-wlPpyXdycqqF/Congress_Wikipedia_Edits">Numbers for iCloud</a>, both of which contain high-resolution charts and clickable Wikipedia links. A <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qfFEwzNzc4KL4gqe2i4IoMO0ksmoYndCK0O0m46n37I/edit?usp=sharing">Google Sheets</a> version is also available.</p>

<p>Here are the Top 10 Wikipedia entries with the most amount of edits by members of the Senate:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/caucus-needed/senate-wikipedia.png"></p>

<p>Wait a minute. Hawk from G.I. Joe?!</p>

<p>Saying that the query results were surprising would be the understatement of the century.</p>

<p>Two of the top-edited entries are directly pertaining to the U.S. Senate, which helps prove that the IP block is indeed the Senate&rsquo;s IP block. Both Kappa Upsilon Chi and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beta_Upsilon_Chi">Beta Upsilon Chi</a> are Christian fraternities. (however, the Kappa Upsilon Chi Wikipedia entry no longer exists for some reason)</p>

<p>The edits corresponding to actual people are ones which are the most interesting. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Swain_Lee">William Swain Lee</a> is a Delaware politician whose entry was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=William_Swain_Lee&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=31202175">created and edited</a> by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/156.33.148.107">user in the Senate IP block</a>. OrangePie is  a user who, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=7319910">according to his talk page</a>, was criticized for repeatedly recreating an entry for &ldquo;Michael Hardaway&rdquo; after deletion, who coincidentally worked for the Senate <a href="https://twitter.com/michaelhardaway">according to his Twitter bio</a>. In journalist <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=8593106">Paul D. Thacker&rsquo;s</a> entry, one Senate editor <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Paul_D._Thacker&amp;diff=311839513&amp;oldid=311689066">replaced a paragraph</a> of Thacker&rsquo;s biography with the word &ldquo;anus?&rdquo;. Jay Rockefeller is an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=337026">actual U.S. Senator</a>, so the edits are definitely a conflict of interest. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/156.33.96.28">user who made the edits</a> apparently also removed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jay_Rockefeller&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=33857327">information about a government investigation</a> into the Senator.</p>

<p>I have nothing to add for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=2814171">Hawk from G.I. Joe</a>.</p>

<p>Other interesting frequently-edited Wikipedia entries from members of the U.S. Senate are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=3626593">Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actor – Comedy Series</a> (11 edits), <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1226609">Wikipedia:Introduction</a> (5 edits) and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1749535">Crash (2004 film)</a> (5 edits)</p>

<p>The Wikipedia entries with the most amount of edits by members of the House of Representatives are somehow even <em>weirder</em>, and that&rsquo;s quite an accomplishment.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/caucus-needed/house-wikipedia.png"></p>

<p>Well, if <em>anyone</em> in the entire United States would be experts on the topics of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=2352587">cleft chins</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1924543">dimples</a>, it would be the members of the House of Representatives.</p>

<p>Again, one of the most-edited entries corresponds to a House of Representatives topic, which helps validate the IP blocks. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=107610">Cerritos, California</a> location had <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Cerritos,_California&amp;diff=21384826&amp;oldid=21363395">neutral edits</a> made by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.231.249.141">rather dedicated Wikiuser</a>. Wynne, Arkansas and Michelle Ye&rsquo;s edits were made by the same dedicated Wikiuser. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1143590">Waverly, Pennsylvania</a> was edited by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/137.18.255.33">user</a> who&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Waverly,_Pennsylvania&amp;diff=7763793&amp;oldid=7761053">really passionate about Doc&rsquo;s Deli</a>. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1129560">Luis Fortuno</a>, former governor of Puerto Rico, had his <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Luis_Fortu%C3%B1o&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=134653411">history excised</a> by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.231.249.137">another user</a>. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=6260346">Betty Sutton</a>, however, is a actual Representative from Ohio, representing another conflict of interest, as another <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.228.129.9">user</a> constructed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Betty_Sutton&amp;diff=303743778&amp;oldid=296652449">most of her entry</a>.</p>

<p>I have nothing to add regarding <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=862471">effeminacy</a> in the House of Representatives.</p>

<p>Other interesting edits by members of the House include <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=18951054">Apocalypse Now</a> (10 edits), <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1161298">History of Italy as a monarchy and in the World Wars</a> (9 edits), and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=34071">Whitney Houston</a> (9 edits)</p>

<p>In the end, the members of the U.S. Congress have the same peculiar interests as typical Americans. However, when these people edit entries on topics in which they are directly involved, the potential bias threatens the integrity of all Wikipedia. And this is just the tip of the iceburg.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impact of the New Show HN Section on Show HN Submissions]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/show-hn/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T08:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/show-hn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hacker News, a tech-oriented link aggregator managed by Y Combinator, is a platform where software projects have launched to literally become multibillion-dollar companies. Submissions which contain the phrase &ldquo;Show HN&rdquo; usually designate a clever hack or weekend project. On <a href="http://blog.ycombinator.com/make-things-and-show-them">July 3rd 2014</a>, Hacker News <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/show">created a section of Hacker News</a> just for these Show HN projects.</p>

<p>Did this feature help or harm Show HN submissions as a whole?</p>

<p>Over the past few years, the average number of Show HN submissions per day has steadily risen. (this is strongly correlated with the <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/">growth of Hacker News as a whole</a>)</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-submissions.png"></p>

<p>More on that spike at the end later.</p>

<p>On Hacker News, users can upvote link submissions, which increases the point score of the submission; this point score is used as a rough proxy of link quality. The average amount of points per submission peaked in 2012, and has trended downward since then.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a chart of the points of Show HN submissions averaged by date of submission, then averaged across the previous 30-days to further smooth the variation and make the trend more apparent:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-points.png"></p>

<p>Users can also comment on these Show HN posts. The average amount of comments has trended downward over time, albeit only slightly.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-comments.png"></p>

<p>The combination of increased Show HN submissions and a decrease in point quality over time may imply that Show HN submissions have a low signal-to-noise ratio, i.e. a low amount of good submissions relative high amount of bad submissions.</p>

<p>Hitting the front page of Hacker News is the first step to virality. When users upvote submissions on Hacker News, those submissions can hit the front page after achieving enough points (combined with other factors, such as submission age and quantity of other submissions). At the least, if a submission has 10 points, it has most likely hit the front page sometime in its lifespan.</p>

<p>What proportion of the Show HN submissions hit the front page?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-perc-front.png"></p>

<p>Over time, the amount of good Show HNs relative to the amount of bad Show HNs has been steadily decreasing.</p>

<p>Has the new Show HN feature helped improve the signal-to-noise ratio?</p>

<h1>Show and Tell HN</h1>

<p>We can look at the immediate impact of the new Show HN section by comparing the behavior of submissions before and after the announcement. The red area in the following charts represents the daily behavior in the couple months before the release (with the red horizontal dotted line representing the statistical average for the corresponding measurement), and the blue area/blue line represents the behavior after the release.</p>

<p>When the Show HN feature was first announced, everyone rushed to make a submission to test it out, and it showed. In fact, the number of submissions for every day after the feature was added was greater than the average number of submissions from before the addition.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-submissions.png"></p>

<p>Average number of daily submissions before Show HN section is <strong>19.13</strong> submissions/day, average after is <strong>53.44</strong> submissions/day.</p>

<p>Average submission points and average submission comments (both aggregated by date of submission for smoothing) received a slight boost too.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-points.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-comments.png"></p>

<p>Average number of daily points before Show HN section is <strong>11.40</strong> points/submission/day, average after is <strong>12.12</strong> points/submission/day.</p>

<p>Average number of daily comments before Show HN section is <strong>6.57</strong> comments/submission/day, average after is <strong>7.16</strong> comments/submission/day.</p>

<p>The percentage of Show HN submissions that hit the front page, however, moves in a different direction.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-perc-front.png"></p>

<p>Average daily % of Show HN submissions which hit the front page before Show HN section is <strong>19.33%</strong>, average after is <strong>16.37%</strong>.</p>

<p>While the Show HN section gives more focus to Show HN submissions, the increased motivation for making Show HN submissions does not necessarily imply that the submissions will be better. It will take more time to see of the downward trend of Show HN quality continues over time.</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data was processed using R and all charts were made using ggplot2.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view the data of all the Show HN submissions and the derived moving averages <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1JHIlzYdsavWnw8Y5efHrOHCo3-WFGtIosJ2WqIV_Bn4/edit?usp=sharing">in this Google Sheet</a>.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view code necessary to reproduce these results  and reproduce all the charts in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/show-hn">this GitHub repository</a>. This repository also includes a .csv of all ~20,000 Show HNs obtained.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who Performs the Best in Online Classes?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/online-class-charts/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-10T08:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/online-class-charts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the end of May, <a href="http://www.harvard.edu/">Harvard</a> and <a href="http://web.mit.edu/">MIT</a> jointly <a href="http://newsoffice.mit.edu/2014/mit-and-harvard-release-de-identified-learning-data-open-online-courses">released a dataset</a> containing statistics about their online courses in the Academic Year of 2013. This <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7910/DVN/26147">Person-Course De-Identified dataset</a> contains 641,138 events, chronicling 476,532 students who have taken up to 13 unique courses from a variety of topics:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/gender-course/mit-harvard-courses.png"></p>

<p>However, this assortment of courses is not a substitution for a typical college education, as the vast majority of students only take one class.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/student-courses.png"></p>

<p>Very, very few students take more than one class (22% of all students).</p>

<p>Other interesting variables included with the data set are the level-of-education of the student, the birth date of the student, the gender of the student, and the geographical location of student.</p>

<p>Which types of student characteristics lead to the best performance in these online classes? That depends on how you define &ldquo;performance.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a look at the attendance of all the classes:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/class-attendance.png"></p>

<p>Harvard&rsquo;s Introduction to Computer Science is by far the most popular class, and that&rsquo;s only accounting for one semester. (it still beat MIT&rsquo;s Intro to CS/Programming, which had 2 semesters).</p>

<p>Each color bar indicates the level of student participation in the class. <strong>Registered</strong> means the student simply registered for the class; <strong>Viewed</strong> means that the student viewed some of the course material, <strong>Explored</strong> means that students viewed atleast half of the course material, and <strong>Certified</strong> means that students completed the course and received a certificate of accomplishment. For the chart, it&rsquo;s interesting to note that most classes have a high percentage of people in each class who simply register just for fun and <em>don&rsquo;t actually do anything.</em></p>

<p>One metric of course success is the completion rate of each course, i.e. how many people actually complete the course after starting it. A frequent criticism of free online classes is that this number is very low, but what are the actual completion rates of these 13 classes?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/class-perc-finished.png"></p>

<p>Completion rates are low across the board, from 0.8% to 7.5%. A <a href="http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2013/05/10/new-study-low-mooc-completion-rates">2013 study</a> found that completion rate is less than 7%, which this data follows. Apparently, Challenges of Global Poverty is a very interesting course.</p>

<p>After the student completes a class, he or she receives a final grade, and if the grade is above the cutoff point (usually 50% &ndash; 80%), they will complete the class and receive the certificate. Here&rsquo;s the distribution of the average grades for students in each class, given that the student has successfully completed the class:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/class-perc-grade.png"></p>

<p>The grades vary significantly between classes. This doesn&rsquo;t necessarily imply that some classes are harder than others; it&rsquo;s possible some classes had lower cutoffs and therefore the effort put in by the students is lower. However, the perfect 100% average for Harvard&rsquo;s Intro to CS course implies that the class is pass/fail and that students can&rsquo;t get a final grade less than 100%. (as a result, we&rsquo;ll need to remove that class from future grade analyses in order to prevent bias due to the lack of score variance)</p>

<h1>Age</h1>

<p>Online classes are marketed toward college-age students.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/student-age.png"></p>

<p>The mean age is about <strong>27.7</strong>, with a standard deviation of 8.89. The shape skews right and resembles a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_distribution">gamma distribution</a>. There are even plenty of teenagers taking these classes too.</p>

<p>The proportion of students who take more than one class for each age group has a slightly flatter distribution, although more centralized at students in their 20&rsquo;s.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/student-num-classes.png"></p>

<p>What about completion rate?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/student-fulfillment.png"></p>

<p>Completion rate is a little more evenly distributed between the ages, indicating that the two metrics are  likely uncorrelated. However, the older students have nearly double the completion rate of classes. (more on this later)</p>

<h1>Education</h1>

<p>One of the student-provided attributes is his or her highest level of education. These values are &ldquo;Less than Secondary,&rdquo; &ldquo;Secondary&rdquo;, &ldquo;Bachelor&rsquo;s&rdquo;, &ldquo;Master&rsquo;s&rdquo;, and &ldquo;Doctorate.&rdquo; Here&rsquo;s the distribution of the 409,601 students who provided their LoE:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/education-count.png"></p>

<p>This shows that the majority of students who are taking these online classes have already finished college and already obtained a degree, and therefore are likely taking the course as supplemental material.</p>

<p>We can correlate the levels of education with the average age for each LoE as a double-check.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/education-age.png"></p>

<p>Indeed, each LoE average age is above the minimum expected threshold of time needed for each degree (~18 years for Secondary, ~22 years for Bachelor&rsquo;s, etc.)</p>

<p>How does the completion rate vary?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/education-fulfillment.png"></p>

<p>Interestingly, those with Less than Secondary education have a much higher completion rate than those with Secondary educations and Bachelor&rsquo;s Degrees.</p>

<p>But are Doctorate smarter than those with lower education levels? Do they get higher grades on average?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/education-grade.png"></p>

<p>As it turns out, yes. The education level of a student is very relevant to a his or her academic performance in online classes.</p>

<h1>Gender</h1>

<p>I previously <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/gender-course/">made a blog post</a> discussing the genders of students and the proportion of students by course. As it turns out, gender is a very important part of the student body composition.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/gender-count.png"></p>

<p>425,108 students have a gender on record, with 311,534 male students (73.3%) and 113,571 female students (26.7%). The fact that it&rsquo;s not even close to 50:50 is surprising.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/gender-age.png"></p>

<p>Age wise, there&rsquo;s not much difference between the genders. Female students are about a year older than male students on average.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/gender-completion.png"></p>

<p>Completion rate varies a bit more. Female students finish classes more frequently than male students.</p>

<p>Now to answer the age-old question: who get better grades: men or women?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/gender-grade.png"></p>

<p>Ok, it&rsquo;s a tie.</p>

<h1>Country</h1>

<p>The home location of the students is, in my opinion, the most interesting student attribute in the data set. There are 24 different countries which were specified among 325,012 different students.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/country-count.png"></p>

<p>The United States, as one of the more technologically-savvy countries, accounts for nearly 1/3rd of all online students. India has a very strong presence as well due to  the combination of population and accessibility of materials. All the other countries have significantly fewer students.</p>

<p>Given such accessibility of online classes, students in some countries take more classes than others.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/country-more-than-one.png"></p>

<p>India&rsquo;s students also take the most classes on average.</p>

<p>The United States also has the oldest students on average among all the countries.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/country-age.png"></p>

<p>Completion rate by country, however, is very, very significant.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/country-completion.png"></p>

<p>The top seven countries with the highest rate of completion are <strong>all European countries</strong>, with Spain and Poland in particular having a higher rate of completion than all the other countries, and nearly <strong>four times</strong> the completion rate of the United States.</p>

<p>But which country has the students which get the best grades?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/online-class-charts/country-grade.png"></p>

<p>China is at the top with 86%, but otherwise the distribution is fairly flat with no outliers, and no economic or demographical pattern to the top or bottom of the ranks. It&rsquo;s possible that the more structured format of the classes make it harder to skew.</p>

<p>This Person-Course dataset has helped reveal many interesting insights about online classes at Harvard and MIT. Whether you measure performance by % of classes completed or a % score received at the end of the class, it&rsquo;s clear that age, country, and level of education all have a statistically significant impact on performance. The impact of the student&rsquo;s gender on performance, however, is more ambiguous and could use further analysis.</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data was processed using R and all charts were made using ggplot2.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view code necessary to reproduce these results  AND reproduce all the charts in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/online-class-charts">this GitHub repository</a>. Since MIT/Harvard prevent redistribution of the dataset, you&rsquo;ll have to <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7910/DVN/26147">download the dataset</a> yourself.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Interesting Percentages of Female Students in MIT and Harvard Online Courses]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/gender-course/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-04T10:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/gender-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the end of May, <a href="http://www.harvard.edu/">Harvard</a> and <a href="http://web.mit.edu/">MIT</a> jointly <a href="http://newsoffice.mit.edu/2014/mit-and-harvard-release-de-identified-learning-data-open-online-courses">released a dataset</a> containing statistics about their online courses in the Academic Year of 2013. This <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7910/DVN/26147">Person-Course De-Identified dataset</a> contains 476,532 students who have taken up to 13 unique courses from a variety of topics:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/gender-course/mit-harvard-courses.png"></p>

<p>About half of the courses involve subjects in the humanities, while the other half involve computer science and electrical engineering.</p>

<p>One of the statistics I wanted to analyze was the gender ratio of students of online courses. In the data set, 425,105 students have a gender on record, with 311,534 male students (73.3%) and 113,571 female students (26.7%). This population proportion of female students is surprisingly low, especially since the male/female ratio is <a href="http://colleges.findthebest.com/q/1929/1270/What-is-the-male-to-female-ratio-at-Harvard-University">about 50:50</a> at MIT and Harvard themselves.</p>

<p>Therefore, I took a looked at the gender distribution of each of the 13 unique courses. Is the gender ratio similar across all classes, or is there a huge difference between classes?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/gender-course/course-female.png"></p>

<p>Yeah, there&rsquo;s a huge difference.</p>

<p>The proportion of female students in each of Harvard and MIT&rsquo;s online courses range from <strong>5% to 49%</strong>.</p>

<p>The top half of the gender ratios are all well above the 26.7%  threshold. All six of these courses are in the humanities or in the life sciences. The bottom half of the gender ratio are all well below the 26.7% threshold. All seven are these courses are engineering or computer science courses with a strong focus on mathematics. (for clarification, the <a href="https://www.edx.org/course/mitx/mitx-2-01x-elements-structures-1759#.U7ZfKvldV8F">Elements of Structures</a> course at MIT is a physics course with linear algebra programming)</p>

<p>Is there a correlation? As it turns out, the reason that the average proportion of female students is so low is that both Harvard&rsquo;s Introduction to Computer Science I  (where 169,621 students took the class; about 40% of all students) and MIT&rsquo;s Introduction to CS/Programming (124,446 students total across both semesters) are so popular that the low percentage of women in those particular classes is drastically affecting the average.</p>

<p>The presence and interest of <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/eop/ostp/women">women in STEM fields</a> (science, technology, engineering, and mathematics) has been a topic of <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/stella-kasdagli/should-women-avoid-jobs-in-stem_b_5549016.html">controversy</a> for a very long time. However, the chart shows that indeed the percentage of women interested in STEM classes is measurably lower than other fields, and hopefully awareness of this issue will help cause changes in the future.</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data was processed using R and the chart was made using ggplot2. (w/ a few annotations added using a photo editor)</em></li>
<li><em>You can view code necessary to reproduce these results in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/gender-course">this GitHub repository</a>. Since MIT/Harvard prevent redistribution of the dataset, you&rsquo;ll have to <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7910/DVN/26147">download the dataset</a> yourself.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Statistical Analysis of 1.2 Million Amazon Reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/06/reviewing-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T08:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/06/reviewing-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When buying the latest products on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/">Amazon</a>, reading reviews is an important part of the purchasing process.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/ore.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amazon-review.png"></p>

<p>Customer reviews from customers who have actually purchased and used the product in question can give you more context to the product itself. Each reviewer rates the product from 1 to 5 stars, and provides a text summary of their experiences and opinions about the product. The ratings for each product are averaged together in order to get an overall product rating.</p>

<p>The number of reviews on Amazon has grown over the years.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-basic-time-count.png"></p>

<p>But how do people write reviews? What types of ratings do reviewers give? How many of these reviews are considered helpful?</p>

<p>Stanford researchers Julian McAuley and Jure Leskovec collected <a href="https://snap.stanford.edu/data/web-Amazon.html">all Amazon reviews </a>from the service&rsquo;s online debut in 1995 to 2013. Analyzing the dataset of 1.2 million Amazon reviews of products in the Electronics section, I found some interesting statistical trends; some are intuitive and obvious, but others give insight to how Amazon&rsquo;s review system actually works.</p>

<h1>Describing the Data</h1>

<p>First, let&rsquo;s see how the user ratings are distributed among the reviews.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-basic-score.png"></p>

<p>More than half of the reviews give a 5-star rating. Aside from perfect reviews, most reviewers give 4-star or 1-star ratings, with <em>very</em> few giving 2-stars or 3-stars relatively.</p>

<p>As as result, the statistical average for all review ratings is on the high-end of the scale at about <strong>3.90</strong>.  In fact, the average review rating for newly-written reviews has varied from 3.4 to 4.2 over time.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-basic-time-rating.png"></p>

<p>Another metric used to measure reviews is review helpfulness. Other Amazon reviewers can rate a particular review as &ldquo;helpful&rdquo; or &ldquo;not helpful.&rdquo; A &ldquo;review helpfulness&rdquo; statistic can be calculated by taking the number of &ldquo;is-helpful&rdquo; indicators divided by the total number of is-helpful/is-not-helpful indicators (in the example at the beginning of the article, 639/665 people found the review helpful, so the helpfulness rating would be 96%). This gives an indication of review quality to a prospective buyer. Only 10% of the reviews had atleast 10 is-helpful/is-not-helpful data points, and of those reviews, the vast majority of the reviews had perfect helpfulness scores.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-basic-helpful.png"></p>

<p>That would make sense; if you&rsquo;re writing a review (especially a 5 star review), you&rsquo;re writing with the intent to help other prospective buyers.</p>

<p>Another consideration is review length. Do reviews frequently write essays, or do reviews typically write a single paragraph?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-basic-length.png"></p>

<p>Most reviews are 100-150 characters, but the average amount of characters in a review is about <strong>582</strong> (there are some outlier reviews with 30,000+ characters!). Assuming that the average amount of characters in a paragraph <a href="http://wiki.answers.com/Q/How_many_characters_does_the_average_paragraph_have">is 352</a>, reviewers typically write about half a paragraph. Interestingly, reviews are rarely less than a sentence. (the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/community-help/customer-reviews-guidelines">Review Guidelines</a> suggest a minimum of 20 words in a review, so this discrepancy could be attributed to moderator removal of short, one-liner reviews)</p>

<h1>Particularizing the Products</h1>

<p>The 1.2 million reviews in the Electronics data set address about 82,003 distinct products. However, most of those entries represent different SKUs of the same product (e.g. different colors of headphones). Of those products, only 30,577 products have pricing information which identify them as the source product.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-product-price.png"></p>

<p>Over 2/3rds of Amazon Electronics are priced between $0 and $50, which makes sense as popular electronics such as television remotes and phone cases are not extremely expensive. However, there&rsquo;s no statistical correlation between the price of a product and the number of reviews it receives.</p>

<p>For the overall rating of a particular product, which is the average rating of all reviews for that product, the ratings are no longer limited to discrete numbers between 1 and 5, and can take decimal values between those numbers as well. The distribution of product ratings is similar to the distribution of review ratings.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-product-rating.png"></p>

<p>Again, the perfect rating of 5 is most popular for products. This distribution resembles the distribution of scores of all reviews for the discrete rating values, but this view reveals local maxima at the midpoint between each discrete value. (i.e. 3-and-a-half stars and 4-and-a-half stars are surprisingly common ratings)</p>

<p>What happens when you plot product rating and product price together?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-product-score-price.png"></p>

<p>The most expensive products have 4-star and 5-star overall ratings, but not 1-star and 2-star ratings. However, the correlation is very weak. (r = 0.04)</p>

<p>In contrast, the relationship between product price and the average <em>length</em> of reviews for the product is surprising.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-product-price-length.png"></p>

<p>This relationship is logarithmic with a relatively good correlation (r = 0.29), and it shows that reviewers put more time and effort into reviewing products which are worth more.</p>

<h1>Reviewing the Reviewers</h1>

<p>As you might expect, most people leave only 1 or 2 reviews on Amazon, but some have left <em>hundreds</em> of reviews. Out of 1.2 Million reviews, there are 510,434 distinct reviewers.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-count.png"></p>

<p>Over 80% of the reviewers of Amazon electronics left only 1 review. Analyzing reviewers who have left only 1 review is not helpful statistically, so for the rest of the analysis, only reviews who have made 5 or more reviews (which have received atleast 1 is-helpful/is-not-helpful indicator) will be considered. This makes it much easier to get the overall profile of a reviewer. 11,676 reviewers fit this criteria.</p>

<p>Do repeat Amazon users tend to give 5-star reviews?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-score.png"></p>

<p>Distribution of review ratings when averaged across is similar to the other distributions of review ratings. However, this distribution is less skewed toward 5-stars and is more uniform between 4-stars and 5-stars.</p>

<p>What about the average helpfulness of the reviews written by a single reviewer? If a reviewer has enjoyed Amazon enough such that they make 5 or more reviews, chances are that their reviews are high quality.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-helpfulness.png"></p>

<p>Again, the data is slightly skewed. 8% of the reviewers have perfect helpfulness scores on all their reviews, and the average helpfulness score for all repeat reviews is 80%. Interestingly, a few repeat reviewers have average helpfulness scores of 0.</p>

<p>If you plot <em>both</em> average score and average helpfulness in a single chart, the picture becomes much more clear:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-count-score.png"></p>

<p>As the chart shows, there&rsquo;s a good positive correlation (r = 0.27) between rating and helpfulness, with a discernible cluster at the top. However, I don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s a causal relationship. Reviewers who give a product a 4 &ndash; 5 star rating are more passionate about the product and likely to write better reviews than someone who writes a 1 &ndash; 2 star &ldquo;this product sucks and you suck too!&rdquo; review.</p>

<p>Another interesting bivariate relationship is the relationship between the helpfulness of a review and the length of a review). Stereotypically, you might think that longer reviews are more helpful reviews. And in the case of Amazon&rsquo;s Electronics reviews, you&rsquo;d be correct.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-helpful-length.png"></p>

<p>Again, there&rsquo;s a good positive correlation (r = 0.26) between average helpfulness and average length, which the trend line supports. (the dip at the end is caused by the high amount of low-character reviews). All the longer reviews have high helpfulness; there are very, very few unhelpful reviews that are also long.</p>

<h1>Completing the Conclusion</h1>

<p>The reviews on Amazon&rsquo;s Electronics products very frequently rate the product 4 or 5 stars, and such reviews are almost always considered helpful. 1-stars are used to signify disapproval, and 2-star and 3-stars reviews have no significant impact at all. If that&rsquo;s the case, then what&rsquo;s the point of having a 5 star ranking system at all if the vast majority of reviewers favor the product? Would Amazon benefit if they made review ratings a binary like/dislike?</p>

<p>Having a 5-star system can allow the prospective customer to make more informed comparisons between two products: a customer may be more likely to buy a product that&rsquo;s rated 4.2 stars than a product that is rated 3.8 stars, which is a subtlety that can&rsquo;t easily be emulated with a like/dislike system. Likewise, if products are truly bad, the propensity toward 5-star reviews can help obfuscate the low quality of the product when a like/dislike system would make the low quality more apparent.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, only Amazon has the data that would answer all these questions.</p>

<p>Of course, there are many other secrets to be uncovered from Amazon reviews. The Stanford professors who collected the initial data used <a href="http://i.stanford.edu/~julian/pdfs/recsys13.pdf">machine learning techniques on the review text</a> to predict the rating given by a review from just the review text itself. Other potential topics for analysis are comparisons between <em>types</em> of Electronics (e.g. MP3 players, headphones) or using natural language processing to determine the common syntax in reviews.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/amazon/amzn-word-review-start.png"></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a topic for another blog post. :)</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data analysis was performed using R, and all charts were made using ggplot2.</em></li>
<li><em>You can download a ZIP file containing CSVs of the time series, the aggregate product data, and the anonymized aggregate reviewer data <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/amazon_data.zip">here</a>.</em></li>
<li><em>No, I have no relation to &ldquo;<a href="http://www.amazon.com/review/R1KHEP16MXXWCN/ref=cm_cr_rdp_perm?ie=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B000796XXM">M. Wolff</a>&rdquo;.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mapping San Francisco Locations Using Facebook Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/04/san-francisco/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-08T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/04/san-francisco</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Statisticians like to use data from the <a href="https://www.census.gov/">United States Census</a> to plot interesting trends such as unemployment and population of regions across the country. However, such data is typically historical and not very robust.</p>

<p>Facebook, on the other hand, has collected a large amount of data though its <a href="https://www.facebook.com/about/location">Places product</a>. Facebook Places allows users to &ldquo;check-in&rdquo; a place such as <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Dolores-Park/105687759464007">Dolores Park</a> in a manner similar to <a href="https://foursquare.com/">Foursquare</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/dolores.png"></p>

<p>Through clever use of Facebook&rsquo;s Graph API and FQL, I was able to retrieve the data on all Facebook Places in and around San Francisco, along with the # of check-ins at each Place. With the data on approximately 8,000 Facebook Places in San Francisco, we can map where San Franciscans are checking-in, and determine what types of locations they like to visit.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First, let&rsquo;s look at the distribution of check-ins among Places in San Francisco:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/sf-checkin-distribution.png"></p>

<p>On a logarithmic scale, the shape resembles a bell curve with a center at about 800 check-ins; however, the sample average of check-ins for the data set is <strong>3,241 check-ins</strong>, indicating that the data may be heavily skewed to the right. Some Places don&rsquo;t have many check-ins, while some Places have an incredibly large number of check-ins.</p>

<p>What are the Places with hundreds of thousands of check-ins? What does the city look like with all these Places plotted on a map of San Francisco?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/sf-checkin.png"></p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/cykofhlyus8atgw/sf-bubble.pdf">(PDF of Map)</a></em></p>

<p>The most checked-in Places are, unsurprisingly, the famous tourist attractions of San Francisco, such as <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/ATT-Park/116440731717551">AT&amp;T Park</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/UnionSquareSF">Union Square</a>. These Top Places are spread all over the city.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also clear where the most dense areas are located in San Francisco. There are plainly-visible lines of Places along southern Mission Street and Outer Sunset. SOMA and Richmond have a large number of Places as well.</p>

<p>And yes, 155,000 people really did check-into <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/The-Cheesecake-Factory/107178672654937">The Cheesecake Factory</a>.</p>

<h1>What types of locations do people in San Francisco  frequently check-into?</h1>

<p>Facebook also records the category of its Places, such as &ldquo;Bar&rdquo; and &ldquo;Restaurant&rdquo;. What are the most numerous types of locations in San Francisco?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/sf-checkin-distribution-count.png"></p>

<p>Local businesses are by far the most frequent, as it&rsquo;s a more generic classifier for a Place and can be applied to anything that does not have an explicit classifier (such as startups). I find it interesting that non-profit organizations are more numerous than shopping centers.</p>

<p>However, the quantity of a specific type of business does not necessarily mean that San Franciscians will check-into that type of Place more often. Which type of Place, on average, receives the greatest number of check-ins?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/sf-checkin-distribution-avg.png"></p>

<p>People are more likely to check-into memorable Places and events, instead of Places they frequently visit like Bars and Restaurants (Twice as many people check-into Attractions than Clubs). Again, tourist attractions are the most popular, which is due to both the relatively low number of Places and the extremely high number of check-ins into Places such as AT&amp;T Park.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;Lake&rdquo; corresponds to <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Lake-Merced/113785468632283">Lake Merced</a>, if you&rsquo;re curious.</p>

<h1>Which San Francisco neighborhoods are the most popular?</h1>

<p>You saw earlier that the Facebook Places are concentrated in specific areas. Here&rsquo;s a map of San Francisco&rsquo;s neighborhoods, highlighted by the number of Places within:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/sf-places-count.png"></p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/63fgvcucvk9n9v3/sf-sum.pdf">(PDF of Map)</a></em></p>

<p>The neighborhoods with the most Places are unsurprisingly where the trendy areas are, such as the Mission and SOMA. Additionally, those types of neighborhoods are larger in square area than others, which may bias the results in their favor.</p>

<p>But are these large neighborhoods also the most active neighborhoods? Which neighborhoods have the most check-ins on average per Place within the neighborhood?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/sf-places-avg.png"></p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/u613oh4fskjrkny/sf-avg.pdf">(PDF of Map)</a></em></p>

<p>The Embarcadero has by far the most check-ins on average, again, due to both its small size and AT&amp;T Park. Other neighborhoods, however, have more similar averages to each other. It&rsquo;s worth noting that the average number of check-ins is higher in neighborhoods adjacent to the San Francisco Bay, such as North Beach and Fisherman&rsquo;s Wharf: perhaps people check-in more frequently when they have a good view.</p>

<p>Can this data and conclusions about San Francisco Facebook Places be extrapolated to other cities? I&rsquo;d argue yes: it makes logical sense that people check-in more frequently to Places that are more significant, and it also makes sense that people frequently check-into Places with large amounts of tourist attractions. Facebook data shows us cool trends that the United States Census data cannot.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>All charts and maps were made using R, ggplot2, and ggmaps.</em></p>

<p><em>You can download a copy of the Facebook Places data set <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/6g6ap4poz1b2trs/sf-public.csv">here</a>. The place_id column corresponds to the San Francisco neighborhood where the Place is located.</em></p>

<p><em>Maps are from <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/">Google Maps</a>. San Francisco shape files for city neighborhoods are from <a href="https://data.sfgov.org/Service-Requests-311-/Neighborhoods/ejmn-jyk6">data.sf.gov</a>. Additionally, thanks to <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/dataisbeautiful/comments/223ubt/map_of_places_in_san_francisco_by_of_facebook/">/r/dataisbeautiful</a> for offering ideas for improvements to the maps.</em></p>

<p><em>You may notice that the Check-In Counts on some of the official Facebook Place Pages strongly disagree with the Count reported in my charts. The Count reported on affected page is nearly double the value reported via the API in each instance. I believe this is a bug on Facebook&rsquo;s end: see <a href="http://i.imgur.com/I1syBhR.png">this image</a>, in which the Graph Search autocomplete reports a different value of check-ins than the Place Page itself. In this case, I trust the data from the API.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Does Adding Many Tags to an Instagram Photo Maximize the Number of Likes?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/03/hashtag-tag/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/03/hashtag-tag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://instagram.com/">Instagram</a> uses hashtags as a method of categorizing images and videos. A user can tag an image with, for example, #snowy, and all other Instagram app users can see a mosaic of photos from all users which have that tag. Many less-than-honest  Instagram users <a href="http://instagram.com/p/l5J7iXQGX6/">spam tags</a> which are not particularly relevant to their photo in order to maximize the potential exposure.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/instatags2.png"></p>

<p>At a maximum of 30 tags per image, spamming large numbers of tags should theoretically have a huge impact on the image&rsquo;s reach. In fact, there are sketchy websites that provide premade lists of popular hashtags for you to spam. But does spamming #tags in an Instagram image <em>actually</em> lead to a increase in the number of Likes on an image?</p>

<p>Using the <a href="http://instagram.com/developer/">Instagram API</a>, I&rsquo;ve retrieved about 120,000  images, split evenly between pictures tagged with #sunny, #rainy, and #snowy, to get a good range of neutral picture types. Here&rsquo;s the distribution of the number of tags on photos from that data set:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/instagram-tags.png"></p>

<p>The majority of Instagram photos have around 5 tags, which is a reasonable amount for a user quickly classifying a photo within the photo caption. However, it&rsquo;s clear that there are many tag abusers, with a noticeable spike of  the number of Instagram photos which have the maximum of 30 #tags. (the statistical average is <strong>11.45 tags</strong>, with a standard deviation of 8.01)</p>

<p>The distribution of Likes as heavily skewed as you would expect when viewed normally, but when the distribution is viewed on a logarithmic scale, the shape becomes closer to a bell curve:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/instagram-likes.png"></p>

<p>The statistical average of Likes on Instagram photos is <strong>26.19 Likes</strong>, with a standard deviation of 154.07; the high standard deviation is caused by the few photos with thousands of Likes.</p>

<p>If you analyze the distribution of Likes for each discrete number of tags, the results are more telling.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/instagram-likes-facet.png"></p>

<p>As the number of tags increases, the distribution of Likes shifts toward right, with very, very few photos with less than 10 likes. However, due to the logarithmic scaling, it&rsquo;s hard to tell if the center of the distibution (where the average number of Likes is approximately located) is shifting significantly.</p>

<h1>Regression Analysis</h1>

<p>A simple linear regression of log(Likes) on tags can tell us of the if an increase in the number of tags corresponds to an increase in the number of Likes.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/instagram-tags-scatterplot.png"></p>

<p>There is indeed a <strong>very strong positive relationship between Tags and Likes</strong>, with a p-value &lt; 2e-16 for the tag regression coefficient. But tags alone doesn&rsquo;t explain the variance of Likes particularly well (R<sup>2</sup> = 15.47%) due to the heavy variance of Likes in the raw data, even after using a logarithmic transformation. However, due to the logarithmic transformation, it&rsquo;s difficult to easily determine the relative difference in the amount of Likes between using 1 tag on an Instagram photo and using 30 tags.</p>

<p>Using the raw, untransformed data, this is a chart of the average number of Likes on photos from the sample data for each discrete number of tags, with 95% confidence intervals* for each measure:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/instagram-tag-average.png"></p>

<p>Instagram photos which have the maximum of 30 #tags receive, on average, about <strong>three times</strong> as many Likes than photos with only a few tags. Most of the averages are well-bounded, too, which indicate that the per-tag-Like-averages are well-representative of all Instagram photos.</p>

<p>The strong deviations from the trend (and larger confidence intervals) at 1, 5, and 9 tags are due to large outliers which skew the average. Indeed, there are many other factors in determining the expected number of Likes for an Instagram photo (e.g. the popularity of the person who posted the photo), some of which I hope to cover in a future blog post. :)</p>

<p>In the meantime, if you want more Likes on your filtered photos, spam those hashtags. You won&rsquo;t be guaranteed to gets lots of Likes, but the odds will greatly be in your favor.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>All charts were created using R and ggplot2.</em></p>

<p><em>You can download a copy of the Instagram data set <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/zpyv6p6yskdy43j/instagram-data-analysis.csv.zip">here</a>. [2MB zipped CSV]</em></p>

<p><em>*95% confidence intervals for each per-tag-Like-average were generated using bootstrap resampling of the raw data, and recalculating each average on the resampled data. This was repeated 5,000 times to generate upper and lower bounds.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Statistical Analysis of All Hacker News Submissions]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news">Hacker News</a> is a very popular link aggregator for the technology and startup community. Officially titled <a href="http://ycombinator.com/hackernews.html">by Paul Graham in 2007</a>, Hacker News began mostly as a place where the very computational-savvy could submit stories around the internet and discuss the latest computing trends.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-wordcloud-2007i.png"></p>

<p>Back then, people were talking about networking, software users, and a little up-and-coming startup known as &ldquo;<a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a>.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Six years later, during the new renaissance of computing accessibility and startup entrepreneurship, not much has changed.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-wordcloud-2013i.png"></p>

<p>Hacker News, from 2007 to 2014, always illustrates what&rsquo;s &ldquo;new&rdquo; in technology. After downloading all 1,265,114 Hacker News submissions from the official <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/api">Hacker News API</a>, I gathered a few interesting statistics which show the true impact of Hacker News.</p>

<h1>How many stories are submitted to Hacker News?</h1>

<p>In the past few years, Hacker News has had an interesting growth pattern.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-monthly-submissions.png"></p>

<p>From the beginning of 2010 with 12k monthly submissions to to the end of 2011 with 31k monthly submissions, the amount of monthly submissions to Hacker News nearly tripled. It&rsquo;s a similar growth rate to that of the startups that Y Combinator typically funds.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s <em>really</em> interesting is that the end of 2011 is the peak: since then, the amount of submissions has been trending downward. Is Hacker News dying?</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think so. Hacker News implements a proprietary anti-spam algorithm which &ldquo;kills&rdquo; submissions, and moderators can kill submissions manually if necessary. Killed articles do not appear in the submission count, so a change in policy would cause the discrepancy. At the least, it helps improve the quality of discussion.</p>

<p><em>UPDATE (2/28): Paul Graham, in the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7291531">corresponding HN thread</a>,  made a <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7292094">comment</a> that the anti-spam algorithm did indeed increase spam detection and number of article killed at the end of 2011.</em></p>

<h1>How many submissions receive large amounts of points?</h1>

<p>On Hacker News, users are able to upvote submissions. The more upvotes a submission has, the higher the position that it appears on the front page of the main site. A simple heuristic for calculating exposure from a Hacker News front page submission is 100 page views per point minimum, which means a submission that earns hundreds of points can go viral very quickly!</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hntop.png"></p>

<p>But how many submissions actually make it to the front page, and how many actually make it to the top?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-points-hist.png"></p>

<p>On a logarithmic scale, it&rsquo;s evident that the vast majority of Hacker News submissions don&rsquo;t even hit 10 points. (the average amount of points for a submission is 9.51). Usually, hitting 10 points is the sign that you&rsquo;ve appeared on the front page atleast briefly; there, the submission either receives voting momentum or dies quickly due to other rising stars.</p>

<p>But how many submissions <em>do</em> receive hundreds of points? Here&rsquo;s a chart of submissions by month which have received more than 100 points:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-monthly-submissions-front.png"></p>

<p>The growth rate of top-scoring submissions is correlated with the growth rate of Hacker News submissions themselves, which is not surprising. The number of points a post receives is also dependent on the number of users; as Hacker News grows, the number of users grows as well. Even though the front page cycles frequently, there is still room for great content.</p>

<h1>When is the best time to submit to Hacker News?</h1>

<p>The age old question. What is the best time to post such that your post makes it to the front page?</p>

<p>First, let&rsquo;s see when Hacker News has the most activity by observing the average number of submissions for each combination of submission hour and weekday:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-submissions.png"></p>

<p>Hacker News activity is most active at around 12 PM EST / 9 AM PST at about 40 submissions per hour, when hackers on the East Coast submit just before eating lunch, and hackers on the West Coast submit just after getting to work. Weekends, unsurprisingly, are completely dead.</p>

<p>If you submitted your link at 12 PM, you&rsquo;d have a lot competition, but it would be easier to get upvotes since there would be more people visiting the site. If you submitted your post on the weekend, there would be no competition, but would be harder to make the front page.</p>

<p>What is the best weekday + hour to submit such that your submission goes viral? An easy way to estimate the best time is to analyze the times of submission of previous posts with large amounts of points; with enough data (we have enough), it&rsquo;ll provide a strong guess.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-front-page.png"></p>

<p>As it turns out, the submission times of posts are <em>uncorrelated</em> with the number of viral posts. There are <em>slightly</em> more when submitting at peak activity (weekdays at 12 PM EST / 9 AM PST), but it won&rsquo;t make-or-break an article&rsquo;s success on HN.</p>

<p>Having good content is more important to having a post get to the top of Hacker News. Although you probably shouldn&rsquo;t submit an article when there&rsquo;s a major tech event. (e.g. Facebook&rsquo;s WhatsApp Purchase)</p>

<p><em>UPDATE (2/28): It&rsquo;s been pointed out that measuring the proportion of viral posts (number of viral submissions / number of total submissions) would be a better indicator of odds of article success. Since the number of viral submissions is similar across all time zones, the proportion of viral posts would be greatest on the weekends, since there are dramatically fewer total submissions. However, this logic isn&rsquo;t perfectly correct due to how the article discovery and upvoting system works. I may cover this in a future post.</em></p>

<h1>Do Y Combinator startup announcements score better on HN?</h1>

<p>One of the main benefits of Hacker News is to showcase the startups which Y Combinator has funded. Links about YC Startups contain the YC class name of that startup in their title, such as &ldquo;<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6103506">Watsi (YC W13) raises $1.2M first-of-its-kind philanthropic seed round</a>.&rdquo; Do these links perform better than the typical links submitted to Hacker News?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-points-class-hist.png"></p>

<p>As it turns out, yes. For normal posts, the average number of points is 9.5 points, but for YC class announcements, the average is 41.7 points (from 1,745 submissions analyzed).</p>

<p>For fun, which YC classes perform the best on Hacker News?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-top-class.png"></p>

<p>W06 placed first because of <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2481576">two</a> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2481610">announcements</a> about Wufoo, and S11 placed second because of <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6585071">CryptoSeal</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2846725">Parse</a>.</p>

<h1>Who are the best submitters on Hacker News?</h1>

<p>Like all popular link aggregators, Hacker News has many spammers who submit large amounts of low quality content. Who are the users who submit quality content?</p>

<p>Calculating the average points of a user&rsquo;s submitted content isn&rsquo;t an accurate measurement, since that can be heavily skewed by one viral post. Therefore, I created a Hacker News &ldquo;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batting_average">batting average</a>&rdquo; statistic: which posters have the highest proportion of posts that make it to the front page vs. the total number submitted? (for posts since 2010 and number of submitted posts >= 10)</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-top-submitters.png"></p>

<p>It should be no surprise that most of the people on the list are startup founders. It&rsquo;s also not surprising that most of those founders, such as <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=mwseibel">mwseibel</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=rahulvohra">rahulvohra</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=tikhon">tikhon</a> also founded a Y Combinator startup. (although Paul Graham <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=pg">himself</a> only has a 0.856 average).</p>

<h1>What are Hacker News&#8217; favorite programming languages?</h1>

<p>One of the infamous memes about Hacker News is programming language elitism, with favoritism for languages such as Lisp and Erlang.</p>

<p>But what programming languages are indeed the most popular on Hacker News?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-lang-num-submissions.png"></p>

<p>Javascript is very popular, especially with the rising popularity of node.js. Go is unexpectedly frequently submitted for being such a new language. (although it&rsquo;s possible for &ldquo;go&rdquo; to be used in a context outside of a programing language.) Lisp and Erlang are indeed obscure, which might discredit the meme.</p>

<p>Which programming languages are most well-liked on HN?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-lang-avg-submissions.png"></p>

<p>&hellip;so Lisp and Erlang <em>are</em> well-liked on HN.</p>

<p>At the least, in both cases, no one on Hacker News likes PHP.</p>

<h1>Snowden and Bitcoin</h1>

<p>Edward Snowden&rsquo;s leaks in June 2013 about the NSA and PRISM affected the entire tech industry, including Hacker News. How did Hacker News react to the leaks?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-snowden.png"></p>

<p>Strongly.</p>

<p>But after the June spike, discussion about the NSA decreased significantly, but it&rsquo;s still a popular topic.</p>

<p>Bitcoin is more interesting since it has had three distinct surges:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/hn-bitcoin.png"></p>

<p>The June 2011 spike was due to the theft of <a href="https://bitcointalk.org/index.php?topic=16457.0">25,000 Bitcoin</a>, the April 2013 spike happened during the first rise-and-fall from $200/BTC, and the November 2013 spike happened during the second rise-and-fall from $1,000/BTC.</p>

<p>Hacker News is a great model for a link aggregator.  It emphasizes more on quality content than the quantity of content, and it has paid off over the years.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Code for getting all the HN submissions is <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/hacker-news-download-all-stories">available on GitHub</a>. Unfortunately, the Hacker News data is too large to distribute freely. <a href="http://minimaxir.com/contact/">Contact me</a> if you want the raw data or any data to reproduce the charts.</em></p>

<p><em>Note: there appear to be <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Zdex42KE-8DFIHujhVWjJ3yqilJSws2EbT8VAARPYgE/edit?usp=sharing">some gaps in the data</a> for dates before 2010. This appears to be caused by the API server: for example, compare the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=liebke">number of submissions as reported by HN for top user liebke</a> (21) and the <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=story,author_liebke">number of submissions as reported by the API</a> for liebke (14, with the last 7 submitted stories missing relative to the HN output). Also, number of stories (1,265,114) in the output data and the <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/">server data</a> (~1,267,000 as of publishing) are very close, making the discrepancy unlikely caused by client error. As a result, any chart that is based on a time series does not start earlier than 2010.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Game Theory: How 70,000 Pokemon Players Sabotage Themselves]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/glory-to-the-helix/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-18T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/glory-to-the-helix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pok%C3%A9mon_Red_and_Blue_Versions">Pokemon Red and Pokemon Blue</a> remain as two of the most iconic games in video gaming history. They have retained a lot of nostalgia value for those who grew up playing the games (such as myself), and nowadays even adult gamers revisit such classics.</p>

<p>On the game live-streaming site <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/">Twitch.tv</a>, one user simply known as &ldquo;TwitchPlaysPokemon&rdquo; setup <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/twitchplayspokemon">a live-stream of Pokemon Red</a>, but with a twist: all game commands, such as &ldquo;up&rdquo;,&ldquo;down&rdquo;,&ldquo;left&rdquo;,&ldquo;right&rdquo;,&ldquo;b&rdquo;,&ldquo;a&rdquo;,&ldquo;select&rdquo;, and &ldquo;start&rdquo;, would be input by typing the appropriate command into the livestream chat. At first, this seems like a crazy idea: if thousands of people are inputting commands at the same time, could we accomplish <em>anything</em> in the game?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/AcXmBbM.png"></p>

<p>As it turns out, it was an idea that had gone horribly right. By the time gaming forum NeoGAF <a href="http://www.neogaf.com/forum/showthread.php?t=768965">found the stream</a>, the channel had made an unexpected amount of progress; a group of 3,000 viewes made it past the first Gym (out of eight) and continued to move forward. A few days later, after the channel was covered by <a href="http://www.polygon.com/2014/2/17/5420334/twitch-plays-pokemon-captivates-with-more-than-6-5m-total-views">major news outlets</a>, the channel had completed <em>four</em> gyms, inspired the creation of a large amount of <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Luwz9wr8XkoekzU4zv3duj9D2K5AoAyqnYMcbCHZKqc">hilarious fan art</a>, and also created a <a href="http://askhelixfossil.com/">new religion</a>. You can read a summary of the stream&rsquo;s status <a href="https://docs.google.com/a/minimaxir.com/document/d/1Ka89uCBeLl9VV5GPlAKuW7yF8FGtnVmdbPnIwG8FnQ4/preview?pli=1&amp;sle=true">here</a>.</p>

<p>That being said, it was neither a straight nor short path to success. In the end, the gaming community fought its greatest enemy: itself. Twitch Plays Pokemon isn&rsquo;t about winning. It&rsquo;s about trying not to fail spectacularly. And they still fail regardless. It&rsquo;s an irresistible train wreck that&rsquo;s hard to stop watching.</p>

<h1>The Adventure Begins</h1>

<p>The first areas of Pokemon Red are relatively linear up until <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Vermilion_City">Vermilion City</a>, where the third gym is located. Before that, Pokemon Trainer Red, the player character, had a few interesting encounters thanks to the bizarre overlords of the Twitch chat. Red chose <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Charmander">Charmander</a> (later evolved into <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Charmeleon_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Charmeleon</a>) as his starter Pokemon, which he nicknamed <strong>ABBBBBBK (</strong> or &ldquo;Abby&rdquo; for short. He caught a few more basic Pokemon, including a <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pidgey">Pidgey</a> (later evolved into <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pidgeotto_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Pidgeotto</a>) and <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pidgeot_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Pidgeot</a>), 2 <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Rattata">Rattata</a> (one nicknamed <strong>JLVWNNOOOO</strong>, i.e. &ldquo;Jay Leno&rdquo;), a <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Drowzee">Drowzee</a>, and a <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Spearow">Spearow</a> which was traded for a <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Farfetch%27d">Farfetch&rsquo;d</a>, all of which gave him a full party of Pokemon.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/MwarCER.png"></p>

<p>Since thousands of players are inputting commands at the same time, there is absolutely no strategy involved in Pokemon battles, which in most cases make the battles unwinnable. Thanks to the nature of RPG level-ups and a few lucky critical hits, Red can still persevere (although it will a few hours).</p>

<p>The Twitch channel was a very casual experience, until Red obtained HM 01 from the <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/S.S._Anne">S.S. Anne</a>, an item that requires a sequence of sequential button presses to operate.</p>

<p>Then things get complicated.</p>

<h1>Cutting A Thin Line</h1>

<p>HM 01 is an item that grants the Cut ability to a Pokemon, which is required to cut trees blocking progress; in this case, the tree in front of the Vermilion City Gym. In order to teach a Pokemon Cut, the player must:</p>

<ol>
<li>Bring up the Start menu.</li>
<li>Select &ldquo;Items.&rdquo;</li>
<li>Select HM 01.</li>
<li>Confirm that HM 01 is to be used.</li>
<li>Select a Pokemon to learn Cut.</li>
<li>Confirm that the selected Pokemon is to learn Cut.</li>
<li>Choose a move for Cut to replace.</li>
</ol>


<p>The kicker? Pressing the B button or choosing the wrong option during <em>any</em> of these 7 steps takes the process back a step.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/1XSdWPY.jpg"></p>

<p>At this point in the stream, the audience hit 30,000 viewers. The increased activity caused an input delay of about 20 seconds from when the Twitch user input the command in chat to when the game recognized the command. This can make navigating menus difficult when an &ldquo;up&rdquo; or a &ldquo;down&rdquo; command is applied to a menu that isn&rsquo;t even visible yet.</p>

<p>Additionally, as the number of viewers in a stream increases, the number of trolls increases. And those trolls loved to spam the B button command.</p>

<p>Thanks to these two factors, the channel had failed to teach any Pokemon Cut for over <em>4 hours</em>. The stream chat became a bloodbath of blame.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/p30F3g7.png"></p>

<p>Eventually, it happened. The Farfetch&rsquo;d was taught Cut. No one knows <em>how</em>, but it happened. But <em>that</em> was only one step towards progress.</p>

<p>The second step is actually Cutting the tree. In order to Cut:</p>

<ol>
<li>Face the tree.</li>
<li>Bring up the Start menu.</li>
<li>Select &ldquo;Pokemon&rdquo;</li>
<li>Select the Pokemon with Cut.</li>
<li>Select Cut.</li>
</ol>


<p>Same kickers as before, too. Facing the tree is even harder since the same up/down commands for navigating the menus can reorient Red away from the tree.</p>

<p>It took another 4 hours to cut down that tree. Later, when Red was defeated in the Gym, the tree respawned. Yeah.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/NCo5N3j.png"></p>

<p>HM 01 was a harsh reminder that the more people present, the higher the chance that your task will fail. Not necessarily due to incompetence and disorganization, but due to mischief.</p>

<h1>Fighting The Ledge Boss</h1>

<p>After the Vermilion City Gym was (eventually) completed, the Twitch stream progressed through <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Kanto_Route_9">Route 9</a> toward <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Lavender_Town">Lavender Town</a>. Sounds simple, until Red hit this obstacle.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/ledge.png"></p>

<p>Red must walk from the left to the right through the 1-character-wide path. If Red went down, the ledge is a one-way drop, and Red must walk back to the beginning to try again.</p>

<p>The Twitch chat must go &ldquo;right&rdquo; about 8 times <em>without going &ldquo;down&rdquo; at all</em>.</p>

<p>HM01 had input lag as a contributing factor to its failures. In this case, the trolls had <em>all</em> the power. One &ldquo;down&rdquo; ends the entire attempt. And the stream was even more popular with an audience of 50,000 people.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/h2sFCtt.png"></p>

<p>The result? Crossing the ledge took over <em>12 hours</em>. And then Red was defeated by the trainer at the end of the ledge and so getting back across the ledge took an equally absurd amount of time.</p>

<p>Lesson learned? If trolls have absolute power, <em>they will use it</em> and they will use it without mercy.</p>

<p><em>EDIT 2/19: The defeat of the ledge boss was due to the intervention of another Twitch channel which <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/twitchplayspokemon/comments/1y1ee8/the_meta_strat_or_how_we_beat_the_ledge/">executed a meta-strategy</a>: press &ldquo;right&rdquo; in sync with the input delay: with enough people, Red would move right enough times.</em></p>

<h1>Disregarding Decision Trees</h1>

<p>After the ledge incident, the fanbase became paranoid. What other gameplay aspects in this playthrough could be compromised by trolls in the future? One concern is the PC system used to store Pokemon; the same system can also <em>release</em> them, removing them from the game forever. The risk of losing a top Pokemon to the PC due to trolls was too great and would make the game nearly unwinnable, and therefore the stream decided to avoid using the PC unless necessary.</p>

<p>Red progressed through Lavender Town and arrived at <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Celadon_City">Celadon City</a>, where the Twitch channel defeated the Gym Leader for the fourth badge (it took awhile: there was a tree outside <em>and</em> inside the gym!)</p>

<p>At this point in Pokemon Red, the game becomes more nonlinear, which started a debate on what next to do in game. Many pointed out that the party lacked a Pokemon which could learn Surf, a skill, like Cut, which was required to progress in the game much later. Red will eventually earn such a Pokemon which could learn Surf (<a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Lapras">Lapras</a>) as a part of the plot, who&rsquo;s a decent combatant too.</p>

<p>On the other hand, the player can also collect <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Eevee">Eevee</a> as a free Pokemon. Eevee has three evolutions: the terrible <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Flareon_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Flareon</a>, the good <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Jolteon_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Jolteon</a>, and the great <a href="http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Vaporeon_(Pok%C3%A9mon)">Vaporeon</a> who can also learn Surf. But in order to evolve Vaporeon Eevee into , the party must a) buy a Water Stone, and not accidentally any other elemental stone instead and b) use the Stone <em>without accidentally tossing it</em> and destroying it. Both of which are difficult due to input lag and trolls.</p>

<p>The party had 5 Pokemon (after a Rattata was deposited  earlier into the PC), and so the stream only had the opportunity for get <em>one</em> Pokemon, since the stream did not want deposit any in the PC for fear of release. Which is the more rational path for getting a Pokemon with Surf: waiting to get a guaranteed Lapras, or getting the Eevee and hope the stream can evolve it into a Vaporeon? A guaranteed decent Pokemon or a chance at a great Pokemon?</p>

<p>As it turns out, when 70,000 people make a decision, they aren&rsquo;t exactly rational. Instead, hilarity ensued.</p>

<h1>Game Over Theory</h1>

<p>The stream obtained the Eevee (even after many said it was <a href="http://i.imgur.com/9cV06Yq.png">a bad idea</a>) and went to purchase a Water Stone. Due to input manipulation, they instead bought a Fire Stone, and later the Eevee evolved into the unhelpful Flareon. Chat becomes a bloodbath once again.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/QGiFYYu.jpg"></p>

<p>In order to make room for Lapras in the future, the stream attempted to use a PC to deposit Flareon.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/0ndYCF1.png"></p>

<p>Instead, both Abby and Jay Leno were permanently released.</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/tumblr_n157ldJl611rvlenbo1_1280.jpg"></p>

<p>The stream became completely derailed.</p>

<p>As of today, Twitch pushes on, but everyone who&rsquo;s participating in the stream has now learned a lesson: people act in their self interest and do what they think is best. Trolls have&hellip;different self-interests. And there will always be trolls. Knowing how to fail gracefully is always valuable.</p>

<p>At the least, the amount of progress the stream has made is still very, very impressive and unexpected.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Credit for all fan art goes to their respective artists: I&rsquo;m currently working on tracking them down.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Many #nofilter Instagram Photos Actually Have No Filter?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/the-filter-truth/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/the-filter-truth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most <a href="http://instagram.com/">Instagram</a> photos have filters applied to make them look more retro/cool. Instagram users are also able to apply tags to a photo to help categorize and promote them to the Instagram community. One such tag, #nofilter, is intended to emphasize such natural beauty that no filter is necessary to enhance the image. (or the photographer is just too lazy to decide on a filter)</p>

<p>But how many #nofilter images actually <em>have</em> no filter?</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/instagram_selfie.gif"></p>

<p>As it turns not, not all of them.</p>

<p>After retrieving about 50,000 images through the Instagram API (code <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/get-data-from-photos-from-instagram-tags">available on GitHub</a>), here is the breakdown of filters on #nofilter-tagged Instagram images:</p>

<p><img src="http://minimaxir.com/img/nofilter.png"></p>

<p>Only 83% of #nofilter images have no filter?! You had one job, Instagram! :(</p>

<hr />

<p><em>The actual reason that this is happening is because Instagram rewards #tagspamming. More on that in a future blog post.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
