<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Comedy | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//comedy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-10T07:24:45-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Many #nofilter Instagram Photos Actually Have No Filter?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/the-filter-truth/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/the-filter-truth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most <a href="http://instagram.com/">Instagram</a> photos have filters applied to make them look more retro/cool. Instagram users are also able to apply tags to a photo to help categorize and promote them to the Instagram community. One such tag, #nofilter, is intended to emphasize such natural beauty that no filter is necessary to enhance the image. (or the photographer is just too lazy to decide on a filter)</p>

<p>But how many #nofilter images actually <em>have</em> no filter?</p>

<p><img src="/img/instagram_selfie.gif"></p>

<p>As it turns not, not all of them.</p>

<p>After retrieving about 50,000 images through the Instagram API (code <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/get-data-from-photos-from-instagram-tags">available on GitHub</a>), here is the breakdown of filters on #nofilter-tagged Instagram images:</p>

<p><img src="/img/nofilter.png"></p>

<p>Only 83% of #nofilter images have no filter?! You had one job, Instagram! :(</p>

<hr />

<p><em>The actual reason that this is happening is because Instagram rewards #tagspamming. More on that in a future blog post.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Thoughtful Analysis of the Most Poorly-Designed Chart Ever]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/01/more-language-more-problems/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-20T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/01/more-language-more-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I was surfing Reddit and came across an <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ProgrammerHumor/comments/1ur3ny/unnecessary_graph_of_most_desired_skills_in_2013/">interesting infographic</a> within the <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ProgrammerHumor/">ProgrammerHumor subreddit</a>. The infographic, as compiled by tech blog <a href="http://readwrite.com/">ReadWrite</a>, depicts the Top 10 Most In-Demand Developer Skills of 2013, as compiled by <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/">Stack Overflow</a> through keyword searches.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/infographic-1.jpg"></p>

<p>Take a look at the chart. What’s good and bad about it?</p>

<h1>The Good</h1>

<p>The data is properly cited.</p>

<h1>The Bad</h1>

<p><strong>EVERYTHING ELSE.</strong></p>

<p>What’s terrible about the graph? Let me count the ways:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Using discrete values in the X-Axis for a continuous measurement (i.e. the percentage). And not only that, discrete values with two significant figures, which make the X-Axis unusually cluttered.</p></li>
<li><p>The Y-Axis is Language. This implies that some programming languages are more language than others.  (<a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10152166149970450&amp;set=a.432190050449.225968.582270449&amp;type=1&amp;stream_ref=10">to be fair</a>, Java is more language than Android)</p></li>
<li><p>Not all entries on the chart are programming languages. (Android, for example, is an operating system.)</p></li>
<li><p>The 45-degree line in the chart implies that the relationship between language and %-of-searches is perfectly linear, where in reality the data has an upward-parabolic shape.</p></li>
<li><p>No relative proportions between the programming languages. We can&rsquo;t accurately see the increase in language Java has relative to Android just by looking at the graph.</p></li>
<li><p>Cannot easily associate a language with the given X-Axis value. The logos representing the programming language oscillate around the line, and it&rsquo;s hard to see at a glance which percentage corresponds to which language.</p></li>
</ul>


<h1>Fixing the Chart</h1>

<p>This isn’t one of those blog posts that make snarky criticism without offering any constructive input. (those will be posted next week). How can we make the chart somewhat logical?</p>

<p>The easiest way to improve the chart is to convert the chart from a line chart to a column chart. Here’s a column chart that keeps the intended impression of the original chart:</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-1.png"></p>

<p>A much bigger improvement, although unfortunately without the cool hand-drawn logos. The axes are no longer illogical and it’s easy to determine the relative impact of each language (e.g. Java is clearly, clearly at the top). However, the large amount of text can clutter the bars, and it can be difficult to correlate the raw percentage with the scale at a glance.</p>

<p>Another option is to rotate the chart and use bars instead of columns:</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-2.png"></p>

<p>This fixes the text issue by giving more room for text with most of the factors, but the Java text clips outside the chart. The correlation issue between language and percent value persists.</p>

<p>A best-of-both-worlds approach is to display the language on the Y-Axis and the raw percent value on the corresponding bar itself, allowing us to forgo the percent metric axis entirely.</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-3.png"></p>

<p>There we go. Minimalist, fixes both the text and correlation issues, and gets the point across effectively.</p>

<p>All of these charts were created using R and ggplot2, and you can download the R code in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/developer-graphs">this GitHub repository</a>. I wish the <a href="http://readwrite.com/2014/01/08/in-demand-tech-skills-of-2013-java">orginal ReadWrite article</a> used a chart like the last one and…</p>

<p>Wait, they changed the infographic?</p>

<p><img src="/img/infographic-2.jpg"></p>

<p>Hey, they fixed the chart, and it’s using a similar design as mine! What a crazy random happenstance!</p>

<p>The article was appended with an update:</p>

<blockquote><p>An earlier version of the infographic in this story presented the StackOverflow data in a confusing and conceptually problematic fashion. It has been updated.</p></blockquote>

<p>&ldquo;Problematic&rdquo; is the world&rsquo;s biggest understatement.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
