<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Facebook | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//facebook/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-15T08:31:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Predicting the Number of Likes on a Facebook Status With Statistical Keyword Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What makes people click the Like button on Facebook Statuses? Does the status say something funny? Does it contain a cool link or a funny photo? Does the status actively engage its readers?</p>

<p>Needless to say, brands on Facebook want to know the answers to these questions. The more people that Like their statuses on their Facebook Pages, the more exposure they gain, and the more money they earn. Many, many companies have been created for the sole purpose of maximizing the number of Facebook Likes.</p>

<p>By 2013, most brands have realized that photo posts and statuses that ask a question <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/questions-equals-reponses/">will generate <em>much</em> higher numbers</a> of Likes. Personally, that&rsquo;s not why <em>I</em> like a given Facebook status: I Like statuses that contain new and exciting things that are relevant to my interests. The first thing I read in a status is the Message: if the message is boring and uninteresting, then there&rsquo;s no reason for me to Like the status needlessly.</p>

<p>Can the keywords and language in a Facebook Status predict the number of Likes the status receives?</p>

<p>Running multivariate regressions on keywords from thousands of Facebook statuses, I&rsquo;ve discovered that the language used in a status <em>does</em> help predict the number of Likes a status receives, and actually could help brands learn much more about their fans.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Setup</h1>

<p><img src="/img/rdataset.png"></p>

<p>In order to draw accurate conclusions from the analysis, large amounts of data are needed (and there&rsquo;s no such thing as too much data).</p>

<p>I decided to analyze the Facebook Pages of 3 extremely popular News sources: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cnn">CNN</a>, the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/nytimes">New York Times</a>, and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/bbcworldnews">BBC World News</a>. All three Pages have millions of fans, post the same types of Facebook statuses, and post statuses extremely frequently to Facebook (around 8-9 times a day). The statuses analyzed will be from June 1st 2012 to June 1st 2013, in order to both gather a large sample size (~3,000  statuses from each Page) and a ensure a consistent apples-to-apples comparison between the three sources.</p>

<p>The raw data, code, and a detailed technical explanation of the statistical techniques used to process the data can be found in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-keyword-regression-analysis">this GitHub repository</a>. (tl;dr, it&rsquo;s an optimized <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Least_squares">least squares</a> regression)</p>

<p><em>Can the keywords and language in a Facebook Status predict the number of Likes the status receives?</em> We&rsquo;re ready to test this hypothesis.</p>

<hr />

<h1>CNN</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="/img/cnn_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Bourdain        1962.98         0
NEWS            1272.64         0
Photo           1154.6          0
Barack          1002.45         0
City            851.82          0
Monday          705.42          0
Obama           632.2           0
United          578.77          0
Mitt            562.29          0.01
South           508.43          0.03
America         505.83          0.01
Watch           470.51          0
Boston          398.13          0.05
New             326.74          0.03
ET              -433.96         0
North           -467.05         0.02
Check           -503.5          0
Travel          -988.99         0.02
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for CNN are political keywords.</li>
<li><strong>NEWS</strong> (&ldquo;BREAKING NEWS&rdquo;) predicts more Likes than <strong>Photo</strong> (i.e. <a href="http://www.facebook.com/5550296508/posts/10151626042186509">Travel Photo of the Day</a>).</li>
<li><strong>Bourdain</strong> refers to Anthony Bourdain, who very recently began <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Bourdain:_Parts_Unknown">a food and travel show</a> on CNN. I assume that targets CNN&rsquo;s primary demographic.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Barack</strong> (Barack Obama) predicts more likes than just <strong>Obama</strong>.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Monday</strong> predicts more likes most other keywords. Garfield would be disappointed.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>North</strong> (North Korea) predicts a <em>decrease</em> in Likes from the average. Is North Korea boring?</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Check</strong> (&ldquo;Check this out!&rdquo;) also predicts a decrease in Likes from the average. This is interesting because this call-to-action is usually associated with the other keywords. Perhaps it&rsquo;s not necessary?</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h1>NYTimes</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="/img/nytimes_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Mills           1022.9          0
Democratic      496.32          0
Krugman         456.31          0
Senate          431.05          0
London          373.67          0.01
Oscar           367.64          0.01
Sandy           364.61          0
Olympics        339.15          0.01
Sunday          317             0
Clinton         314.64          0.02
You             247.07          0
Obama           237.98          0
Opinion         221             0
Michael         204.2           0.03
Credit          191.92          0.05
Tuesday         187.22          0.03
Times           178.69          0
See             160.12          0.01
Romney          157.66          0.04
Ed              140.86          0.01
Read            -101.23         0.05
Here            -182.72         0.04
Facebook        -187.75         0.02
Are             -216.3          0.01
While           -293.77         0.04
Quotation       -322.29         0.02
House           -362.1          0.01
Thanksgiving    -369.88         0.05
Convention      -448.34         0.01
Jersey          -505.98         0
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for NYTimes are political keywords and current events, such as Hurricane <strong>Sandy</strong> and the <strong>London</strong> <strong>Olympics</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Mills</strong> refers to Doug Mills, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/5281959998/posts/10150252479219999">photographer</a> for the New York Times. The power of photos!</li>
<li><strong>You</strong> and <strong>See</strong> are impactful call-to-action keywords, even though they don&rsquo;t ask any questions. (Interestingly, <strong>Are</strong>, which implicitly asks a question, predicts a decrease in Likes. Maybe people don&rsquo;t Like questions?)</li>
<li><strong>Clinton</strong> has a bigger impact than <strong>Obama</strong>.</li>
<li>No one likes <strong>Jersey</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h1>BBC World News</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="/img/bbcworldnews_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Malala          488.1           0
Japan           186.32          0
Britain         167.25          0.01
That            155.01          0.01
AFP             154.97          0.02
Travel          153.41          0
Now             148.39          0.02
Would           146.45          0.03
Delhi           137.85          0.04
Let             134.93          0.03
Future          127.49          0.02
Barack          125.79          0.02
An              122.18          0.03
David           111.78          0.04
Do              111.13          0
Israel          101.31          0.04
Impact          87.94           0.05
South           78.62           0.03
It              62.7            0.01
The             55.7            0
US              -47.84          0.02
On              -86.22          0.04
BBC             -103.58         0
Sunday          -117.01         0.03
After           -122.38         0.05
Thursday        -143.91         0.03
Twitter         -144.55         0
City            -147.16         0.02
Hi              -149.85         0.03
BBCNewsUS       -150.48         0.03
House           -176.86         0.01
California      -187.57         0
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for BBC World News are keywords describing news around the world. Unlike CNN and NYTimes, there are very few impactful keywords related to domestic politics (such as Prime Minister <strong>David</strong> Cameron, and even <strong>Barack</strong> is more impactful than him.)</li>
<li><strong>Malala</strong> refers to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malala_Yousafzai">Malala Youdsfzai</a>, a Pakistani activist who survived an assassination attempt.</li>
<li>Implicit question keywords such as <strong>Let</strong>, <strong>Do</strong>, and <strong>Would</strong> are all very effective.</li>
<li>The simple salutation of <strong>Hi</strong> predicts a decrease in Likes. There&rsquo;s a British joke here somewhere.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p>The language used in Facebook Statuses can be very useful in identifying what words Fans like, and what words will be most useful in generating the most exposure. While my analysis can&rsquo;t predict the <em>exact</em> number of Likes a Status receives, and I likely <a href="http://xkcd.com/882/">broke a few rules of statistics</a> in the process of making this post, the impact of language and specific keywords on social media interaction is an endeavor worth pursuing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook Hashtags Are Fundamentally Broken]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/hashtag-hashtag/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-14T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/hashtag-hashtag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/">Facebook</a> added <a href="http://newsroom.fb.com/News/633/Public-Conversations-on-Facebook">searchable hashtags</a> to all status updates and user comments. As with <a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a>, whenever a Facebook user posts an status with a #hashtag, that hashtag becomes clickable and leads to a News Feed of all other publically-visible posts with that hashtag.</p>

<p>The implementation of hashtags in Facebook is an obvious move. Advertisements and television shows display hashtags all the time to encourage users to Tweet about them: it&rsquo;s free marketing, after all. Facebook can piggy-back off those already-existing hashtags and grow user adoption <em>very</em> quickly, especially with Facebook-owned <a href="http://instagram.com/">Instagram</a> already supporting hashtags.</p>

<p>However, Facebook is a fundamentally different social network than Twitter. While Twitter uses hashtags to quickly categorize a feed of 140-character thoughts, Facebook&rsquo;s content feeds  typically consist of long posts and large images. Additionally, while posts on Twitter are explicitly public or private, Facebook&rsquo;s privacy settings are more granular: if users don&rsquo;t make their posts Public, the hashtag is essentially useless. And the brands are going to <em>love</em> hashtags. Maybe too much.</p>

<p>The magic of Facebook is flat-out incompatible with the magic of hashtags.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Too Long; Didn&rsquo;t Read</h2>

<p><img src="/img/facebooktwitter.png"></p>

<p>Since Twitter posts have a length limit, they&rsquo;re short and occupy a consistent amount of space on the webpage. Facebook posts can be near-unlimited length, utilize a large amount of a white space between posts, and also potentially contain an equally-long comment section. As a result, 5 Twitter posts can use the same amount of screen real-estate as 2 Facebook posts. Given the already incredibly low signal-to-noise quality ratio of #hashtag feeds (as evident above), this makes reading hashtag feeds on Facebook a chore.</p>

<h2>A Thousand Words Takes A Lot Of Space</h2>

<p><img src="/img/bieber-twitter.png"></p>

<p>Facebook displays pictures embedded in posts natively in the feed, while Twitter requires the user to click the Tweet to see the photo. In this case, the ratio of Twitter:Facebook posts can be even worse, in this case 6 Twitter posts for 1 Facebook post.</p>

<h2>If A Hashtag Isn&rsquo;t Seen, Was It Posted?</h2>

<p>Twitter is opt-in private posting. Facebook is opt-<em>out</em> private posting. That&rsquo;s a big usability problem.</p>

<p>The Facebook hashtag feeds only show posts that are explicitly  made Public (or posts from your Friends which are set to a privacy of Friends Only). If the user is unaware that their posts are not Public by default, then their posts containing the hashtag will never be seen and the user won&rsquo;t be able to participate in social hashtag feeds.  Although Facebook has made improvements in helping users set the intended privacy level of a post, it makes the process of posting much more deliberate and much less impulsive than Twitter.</p>

<h2>#brand #branding #marketing #yolo #swag</h2>

<p><img src="/img/hashtagabuse.png"></p>

<p>Brands love hashtags. The more hashtags included in a Tweet, the more exposure the Tweet receives, right?</p>

<p>With Twitter, there&rsquo;s a limit on the number of hashtags in a Tweet due to the delicate balance between the number of hashtags, the length of the hashtags, and the length of the Tweet itself. On Facebook, you can include <strong>25</strong> hashtags in any post!</p>

<p>Since there&rsquo;s no consequence for abusing hashtags, expect to see more Facebook brands taking advantage this new free source of marketing. Expect to see Facebook get much more cluttered.</p>

<h2>Explicit Image Bombing</h2>

<p>A malicious user could theoretically insert shock images into popular hashtag feeds. During my testing of Facebook hashtags, there was a surprising amount of nudity in the seemingly-innocuous #many hashtag.</p>

<p>On Twitter, the volume of Tweets is much higher and the images are hidden by default, so the odds of such an attack working on Facebook are much higher than on Twitter.</p>

<h2>Comment Hashtags Different From Post Hashtags</h2>

<p>You can hashtag comments on Facebook posts like you can hashtag Facebook posts themselves. But hashtagged comments won&rsquo;t appear in the hashtag News Feed. Whereas on Twitter, Replies are also Tweets and can be hashtagged accordingly. This behavior isn&rsquo;t surprising, but it&rsquo;s still a big inconsistency.</p>

<hr />

<p>Will Facebook Hashtags fail due to the massive differences between Facebook and Twitter? It&rsquo;s hard to say, but I&rsquo;m skeptical that Facebook will be able to capture the hashtag magic.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook Outage: All Webpage Likes and Comments Reset]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/03/facebook-outage/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-25T21:47:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/03/facebook-outage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>UPDATE: The issue was resolved about 11 hours after the post was published. Like counts and comment counts are back. See <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/03/25/facebook-comments-bug/">TechCrunch&rsquo;s post</a>.</strong></p>

<p>Today (3/25/13), Facebook appears to have made a change that has nuked all existing Facebook Like counts and Facebook Comments. I can verify that on this particular blog, my non-cached Like counts and my Comments are gone, even after checking Facebook&rsquo;s Graph API directly. This can be verified on older blog posts, such as <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/05/19/day-after-ipo-mark-zuckerberg-marries-longtime-girlfriend-priscilla-chan/">this one</a>.  It is also <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/15623582/facebook-like-count-for-articles-reset-to-zero">being tracked on Stack Overflow</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/Zuck.png"></p>

<p>Note the lack of comments and Likes, on what was the article with the second-most pageviews on TC (and one I can testify that had hundreds of comments.) A quick glance at multiple blogs and other old posts confirms that Likes were reset. New posts have several likes, but all old posts have 0 likes.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure the lost Likes/Comments temporary, but this is an error of incredible magnitude, especially given on how many sites rely on Facebook&rsquo;s data.</p>

<p>Because comments here may be broken, you can comment on the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5439712">Hacker News thread</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Does Asking Questions To Readers Increase Response Rate? - And Other TechCrunch Analyses]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/questions-equals-reponses/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-07T21:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/questions-equals-reponses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A long-standing trend in blogging is having the writer ask the readers what they think about your post and having the readers letting the writers know in the comments. Websites such as <a href="http://www.tvguide.com/">TVGuide</a> and <a href="http://mashable.com/">Mashable</a> have such requests in nearly <em>every</em> article. Reminding users to respond so frequently makes it seems insincere and deliberate, so I personally have been skeptical of the practice.</p>

<p>Recently, I&rsquo;ve noticed more and more brands on their Facebook posts asking their readers for their own opinions on news. Anecdotally, I&rsquo;ve also observed that those same posts have more comments than usual. This technique <strong>must</strong> increase the social response rate, I thought, otherwise media companies wouldn&rsquo;t do it.</p>

<p>Like any math nerd, I wasn&rsquo;t comfortable with simple circumstantial evidence. When I <a href="http://www.facebook.com/max.woolf/posts/10151223309670450">asked on Facebook</a> if there is any statistical data indicating that including a question to the community at the end of a blog post / Facebook post increases the response rate, TechCrunch writer and Facebook specialist Josh Constine responded and linked to<a href="http://www.facebook.com/notes/facebook-journalists/study-how-people-are-engaging-journalists-on-facebook-best-practices/245775148767840"> a Facebook report</a> stating that such posts have double the comments and significantly greater feedback.</p>

<p>I decided to put that to the test. I wrote a quick script in R that parses the Facebook page of a brand and extracts the number of likes for all of their posts, the number of comments on all posts, and whether or not each post contained a question. The brand I chose for my testing is none other than <a href="http://www.techcrunch.com/">TechCrunch</a>, because <a href="http://www.facebook.com/techcrunch">its Facebook page</a>, managed by the wonderful <a href="https://twitter.com/elinblesener">Elin Blesner</a>, has large sample sizes in terms of both unique postings and response rates on each post, ensuring that the analysis of the data is statistically significant. Additionally, having a<em>nother</em> perspective on TechCrunch to comment about certainly doesn&rsquo;t hurt either.</p>

<p>After collecting about 2,500 posts &ndash; 12 months of data &ndash; I analyzed the data conditional on whether or not the post was a question, among other things. The results surprised me.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>tl;dr: Asking a question to the readers in a Facebook post <em>does</em> increase the number of comments very significantly, but <em>decreases</em> the number of Likes!</strong></p>

<h2>How many Comments and Likes do TechCrunch posts receive?</h2>

<p>Since the data goes back a year, we can more easily detect seasonal trends in the data. First, let&rsquo;s see the real world numbers as a sanity check.</p>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb1.png" title="How many Comments and Likes do TechCrunch posts receive?" alt="It's much more than you may think." /></p>

<p>The number of Likes per month appears to be positively correlated with the number of comments, which is to be expected. Some months have significantly more activity than others; September 2012 had the most because of TechCrunch Disrupt SF. (interestingly, there wasn&rsquo;t such a spike in May 2012 with Disrupt NYC) The average number of likes/comments per post per month, as opposed to the sum, is a more consistent measurement, so we will be using that going forward.</p>

<h2>How many Comments and Likes do TechCrunch Facebook posts receive on average?</h2>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb2.png" title="How many Comments and Likes do TechCrunch posts receive on average?" alt="Triple-Digit Likes and double-digit Comments. Not too shabby." /></p>

<p>Overall average is 162 Likes and 30 Comments per post. The average number of Likes/Comments are consistent across the past year, with growth in the last few months. Nothing too surprising here. ## Does the time of day of a Facebook posting affect the number of Likes/Comments it receives?</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a fun measurement I decided to analyze. TechCrunch makes postings at all hours as it&rsquo;s a globally-targeted blog, but readers in the US may be asleep at the time. This could be a possible confounding variable (social activity may be correlated with geographic location), so it&rsquo;s best to see whether or not we can rule it out.</p>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb3.png" title="Does the time of day of a Facebook posting affect the number of Likes/Comments it receives?" alt="The spike in average comments at 4AM PST / 7AM EST is interesting. European workday?" /></p>

<p>As it turns out, time of day does <strong>not</strong> appear to have an effect on number of Likes/Comments received for TechCrunch!</p>

<h2>How many TechCrunch Facebook posts ask a question, relative to the ones that do not?</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the main question that began this entire investigation. Has the TechCrunch Facebook been writing posts that ask questions more frequently?</p>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb4.png" title="How many TechCrunch Facebook posts ask a question, relative to the ones that do not?" alt="TechCrunch-themed columns!" /></p>

<p>As it turns out, no, TechCrunch has asked the same proportion of questions on their Facebook page, as there is no change in trend. Overall average is 31.38% of TC&rsquo;s posts ask a question. (about a third of the posts)</p>

<h2>Does including a question to the community increase the number of Likes/Comments on the post?</h2>

<p>And here&rsquo;s the analysis of the main hypothesis. The results were quite surprising.</p>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb5.png" title="Does including a question to the community increase the number of Likes/Comments on the post?" alt="Now with more DROP SHADOWS!" /></p>

<p>The average amount of Likes for a post that asked a question is <em>lower</em> than a post that does not! (141 Likes for post that asks question, 172 for post that does not, a 18% decrease) That&rsquo;s unexpected!</p>

<p>For Comments, the average amount of Comments for a post that asked a question is significantly higher than a post that does not (45 Comments for a post that asks question, 23 comments for post that does not, a 97% increase). This is nearly double, which is what the Facebook report had stated.</p>

<p>What could explain this behavior? A quick theory is that Liking and Commenting on a brand post are mutually exclusive; asking a question in the post drives the user to comment, but not to Like the post, but since the user has already acknowledged the post socially, there&rsquo;s no need for the user to Like it. This follows my personal behavior on brands; if I comment, I usually do not like the post as it seems redundant.</p>

<p>Regardless, I will now admit that there are benefits to asking your users questions in your Facebook or blog posts. Although there appears to be a drop in Likes by asking users what their opinions are, the increase in comments more than counteracts it.</p>

<p>This data raises an interesting dilemma: let&rsquo;s say everyone catches on and <em>most</em> of the top brands start asking their users questions. It&rsquo;ll quickly become an cliche, as it is essentially a subliminal form of the infamous Facebook News Feed spam. Would that cause brands to stop asking questions? If so, how long would it take for the brands to switch back to asking their users questions?</p>

<p>Who knew that social media marketing involved game theory?</p>

<p>-Max</p>

<p><em>(Since all the data is public anyways, <a href="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/2017402/TechCrunch%20Facebook%20Data%20Analysis.xlsx">I am releasing my data and graphs</a> for your perusal. If you decide to use it and find something else interesting, please let me know!)</em></p>

<p>EDIT: One more.</p>

<h2>Do photo posts have greater response rates than posts without photos?</h2>

<p><img src="/img/tc-graph.png" alt="14" /></p>

<p>Yep. Not too surprising. It&rsquo;s why Facebook bought Instagram! (although I&rsquo;m curious what happened in April&hellip;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
