<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Facebook | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Internet Blog Thingy]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.github.io/blog/categories/facebook/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-09T22:27:39-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook Outage: All Webpage Likes and Comments Reset]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.github.io/2013/03/facebook-outage/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-25T21:47:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.github.io/2013/03/facebook-outage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>UPDATE: The issue was resolved about 11 hours after the post was published. Like counts and comment counts are back. See <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/03/25/facebook-comments-bug/">TechCrunch&rsquo;s post</a>.</strong></p>

<p>Today (3/25/13), Facebook appears to have made a change that has nuked all existing Facebook Like counts and Facebook Comments. I can verify that on this particular blog, my non-cached Like counts and my Comments are gone, even after checking Facebook&rsquo;s Graph API directly. This can be verified on older blog posts, such as <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/05/19/day-after-ipo-mark-zuckerberg-marries-longtime-girlfriend-priscilla-chan/">this one</a>.  It is also <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/15623582/facebook-like-count-for-articles-reset-to-zero">being tracked on Stack Overflow</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/minimaxir.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Zuck.png?resize=625%2C208" alt="Zuck" /></p>

<p>Note the lack of comments and Likes, on what was the article with the second-most pageviews on TC (and one I can testify that had hundreds of comments.) A quick glance at multiple blogs and other old posts confirms that Likes were reset. New posts have several likes, but all old posts have 0 likes.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure the lost Likes/Comments temporary, but this is an error of incredible magnitude, especially given on how many sites rely on Facebook&rsquo;s data.</p>

<p>Because comments here may be broken, you can comment on the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5439712">Hacker News thread</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
