<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: graphs | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//graphs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-13T07:52:00-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[max@minimaxir.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reddit Is Growing Slowly, but Surely]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-18T07:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reddit has certainty received more attention in the mainstream media with its involvement in such events as the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/business/media/bombings-trip-up-reddit-in-its-turn-in-spotlight.html?_r=0">Boston Marathon Bombings</a> and <a href="hhttp://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/z1c9z/i_am_barack_obama_president_of_the_united_states/">President Obama&rsquo;s AMA</a>. But has this publicity led to increase in overall activity on the site?</p>

<p>I analyzed the daily number of submissions from over two years, August 6th, 2011 to September 25, 2013 (41 million submissions total), to see which events, if any, have affected Reddit&rsquo;s growth rate. As it turns out, Reddit grows by itself.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/reddit_daily-mac.png"  ></p>

<p>Reddit&rsquo;s growth over the past two years has been almost entirely <strong>linear</strong>, with no notable acceleration in submission activity at any point in time.</p>

<p>Running a linear regression on daily number of submissions vs. number of days since the first date (8/6/11) reveals that the expected increase in number of submissions each successive day on average is <strong>66.48 submissions</strong>  (+1,948 submissions each successive month, +24,259 submissions each successive year)</p>

<p>This growth rate alone explains <strong>86.83%</strong> of the variation in number of submissions, indicating that external factors such as media publicity explain the remaining 13% of the variation.</p>

<p>From a business perspective, it&rsquo;s impressive that Reddit still continues to grow for being such a mature internet business, but prospective investors for a rumored <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/06/reddit-rumored-to-be-raising-money-at-a-400-million-valuation/">fundraising at a $400 Million valuation</a> might be weary that Reddit&rsquo;s growth is only linear, in contrast to the <strong>exponential</strong> growth of other startups such as Snapchat. (In fairness, submission activity may not necessarily correlate with revenue-driving content consumption activity)</p>

<p>A couple stray observations:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>On January 18th, 2012, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the minimum among the two-year period due to Reddit&rsquo;s participation in the Internet blackout in protest of SOPA. (Reddit&rsquo;s blackout was only from 8AM to 8PM EST, which is why there are a nonzero number of submissions for that day).</p></li>
<li><p>On April 1st, 2013, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the maximum among the two-year period due to April Fool&rsquo;s Day, and the numerous amount of submissions for <em>X</em> brand/website&rsquo;s well-timed joke. However, I&rsquo;m not entirely sure why there&rsquo;s a spike for April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2013, but not April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2012.</p></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data used to create the time-series chart at <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGZ2Zkk1MGF3SjZxdC1sRzV5SW9zRWc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Subreddits on Reddit Are the Largest?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/subreddit-size/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T07:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/subreddit-size</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit&rsquo;s</a> subreddits cover, quite literally, an infinite amount of different topics. But which of its subreddits are the biggest?</p>

<p>Sure, Reddit is known for subreddits such as /r/pics and /r/aww, but in actuality, many of the lesser-known subreddits are much bigger than you think.</p>

<p>By tabulating the data of 37,561,369 total sitewide Link submissions, from 12/18/2011 to 9/26/2013, I created a tree map of the Top 100 subreddits by the number of Link submissions to that subreddit.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/subreddit-treemap.png" alt="" ></p>

<p>In the tree map, the size of the rectangle and the saturation of the blue color indicate the relative size of the subreddit.</p>

<p>Unsurprisingly, the <a href="http://blog.reddit.com/2013/07/new-default-subreddits-omgomgomg.html">default subreddits</a>, which all new users are subscribed to, are ranked mostly at the top. However, subreddits such as /r/POLITICO, /r/leagueoflegends, and /r/trees are higher (no pun intended) than most of the default subreddits.</p>

<p>And then you have the meta subreddits such as /r/ModerationLog and /r/reportthespammers, showing that people spend a considerable amount of time talking about Reddit itself.</p>

<p>Gaming has a very significant presence as well, with /r/Minecraft, /r/DotA2, and /r/tf2. (notably for the latter two, the trading subreddits for the respective games have significantly more link submissions than the subreddits themselves.)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth nothing that these Top 100 subreddits only account for <strong>46.3% of all Reddit link submissions</strong>. Even the Top 500 subreddits only account for 66.2% of all Reddit submissions. The density of link submissions clearly follows a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_tail">long-tail</a> distribution, where most of the content is centralized from the top subreddits. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to see if Reddit is able to utilize that treasure trove of links in the future.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data for the Top 500 subreddits in  <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGQzd0dIQkk1aXRRRkxEY3g0ZmQtWGc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>, and you can see the code use to create the tree map in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/treemap-of-reddit-top-subreddits">this GitHub repository</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
