<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Data | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-24T08:06:17-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Statistical Analysis of All Hacker News Submissions]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-23T17:35:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news">Hacker News</a> is a very popular link aggregator for the technology and startup community. Officially titled <a href="http://ycombinator.com/hackernews.html">by Paul Graham in 2007</a>, Hacker News began mostly as a place where the very computational-savvy could submit stories around the internet and discuss the latest computing trends.</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-wordcloud-2007i.png"></p>

<p>Back then, people were talking about networking, software users, and a little up-and-coming startup known as &ldquo;<a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a>.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Six years later, during the new renaissance of computing accessibility and startup entrepreneurship, not much has changed.</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-wordcloud-2013i.png"></p>

<p>Hacker News, from 2007 to 2014, always illustrates what&rsquo;s &ldquo;new&rdquo; in technology. After downloading all 1,265,114 Hacker News submissions from the official <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/api">Hacker News API</a>, I gathered a few interesting statistics which show the true impact of Hacker News.</p>

<h1>How many stories are submitted to Hacker News?</h1>

<p>In the past few years, Hacker News has had an interesting growth pattern.</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-monthly-submissions.png"></p>

<p>From the beginning of 2010 with 12k monthly submissions to to the end of 2011 with 31k monthly submissions, the amount of monthly submissions to Hacker News nearly tripled. It&rsquo;s a similar growth rate to that of the startups that Y Combinator typically funds.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s <em>really</em> interesting is that the end of 2011 is the peak: since then, the amount of submissions has been trending downward. Is Hacker News dying?</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think so. Hacker News implements a proprietary anti-spam algorithm which &ldquo;kills&rdquo; submissions, and moderators can kill submissions manually if necessary. Killed articles do not appear in the submission count, so a change in policy would cause the discrepancy. At the least, it helps improve the quality of discussion.</p>

<h1>How many submissions receive large amounts of points?</h1>

<p>On Hacker News, users are able to upvote submissions. The more upvotes a submission has, the higher the position that it appears on the front page of the main site. A simple heuristic for calculating exposure from a Hacker News front page submission is 100 page views per point minimum, which means a submission that earns hundreds of points can go viral very quickly!</p>

<p><img src="/img/hntop.png"></p>

<p>But how many submissions actually make it to the front page, and how many actually make it to the top?</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-points-hist.png"></p>

<p>On a logarithmic scale, it&rsquo;s evident that the vast majority of Hacker News submissions don&rsquo;t even hit 10 points. (the average amount of points for a submission is 9.51). Usually, hitting 10 points is the sign that you&rsquo;ve appeared on the front page atleast briefly; there, the submission either receives voting momentum or dies quickly due to other rising stars.</p>

<p>But how many submissions <em>do</em> receive hundreds of points? Here&rsquo;s a chart of submissions by month which have received more than 100 points:</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-monthly-submissions-front.png"></p>

<p>The growth rate of top-scoring submissions is correlated with the growth rate of Hacker News submissions themselves, which is not surprising. The number of points a post receives is also dependent on the number of users; as Hacker News grows, the number of users grows as well. Even though the front page cycles frequently, there is still room for great content.</p>

<h1>When is the best time to submit to Hacker News?</h1>

<p>The age old question. What is the best time to post such that your post makes it to the front page?</p>

<p>First, let&rsquo;s see when Hacker News has the most activity by observing the average number of submissions for each combination of submission hour and weekday:</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-submissions.png"></p>

<p>Hacker News activity is most active at around 12 PM EST / 9 AM PST at about 40 submissions per hour, when hackers on the East Coast submit just before eating lunch, and hackers on the West Coast submit just after getting to work. Weekends, unsurprisingly, are completely dead.</p>

<p>If you submitted your link at 12 PM, you&rsquo;d have a lot competition, but it would be easier to get upvotes since there would be more people visiting the site. If you submitted your post on the weekend, there would be no competition, but would be harder to make the front page.</p>

<p>What is the best weekday + hour to submit such that your submission goes viral? An easy way to estimate the best time is to analyze the times of submission of previous posts with large amounts of points; with enough data (we have enough), it&rsquo;ll provide a strong guess.</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-front-page.png"></p>

<p>As it turns out, the submission times of posts are <em>uncorrelated</em> with the number of viral posts. Your odds are <em>slightly</em> better when submitting at peak activity (weekdays at 12 PM EST / 9 AM PST), but it&rsquo;s not a necessity.</p>

<p>Having good content is more important to having a post get to the top of Hacker News. Although you probably shouldn&rsquo;t submit an article when there&rsquo;s a major tech event. (e.g. Facebook&rsquo;s WhatsApp Purchase)</p>

<h1>Do Y Combinator startup announcements score better on HN?</h1>

<p>One of the main benefits of Hacker News is to showcase the startups which Y Combinator has funded. Links about YC Startups contain the YC class name of that startup in their title, such as &ldquo;<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6103506">Watsi (YC W13) raises $1.2M first-of-its-kind philanthropic seed round</a>.&rdquo; Do these links perform better than the typical links submitted to Hacker News?</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-points-class-hist.png"></p>

<p>As it turns out, yes. For normal posts, the average number of points is 9.5 points, but for YC class announcements, the average is 41.7 points (from 1,745 submissions analyzed).</p>

<p>For fun, which YC classes perform the best on Hacker News?</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-top-class.png"></p>

<p>W06 placed first because of <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2481576">two</a> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2481610">announcements</a> about Wufoo, and S11 placed second because of <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6585071">CryptoSeal</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2846725">Parse</a>.</p>

<h1>Who are the best submitters on Hacker News?</h1>

<p>Like all popular link aggregators, Hacker News has many spammers who submit large amounts of low quality content. Who are the users who submit quality content?</p>

<p>Calculating the average points of a user&rsquo;s submitted content isn&rsquo;t an accurate measurement, since that can be heavily skewed by one viral post. Therefore, I created a Hacker News &ldquo;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batting_average">batting average</a>&rdquo; statistic: which posters have the highest proportion of posts that make it to the front page vs. the total number submitted? (for posts since 2010 and number of submitted posts >= 10)</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-top-submitters.png"></p>

<p>It should be no surprise that most of the people on the list are startup founders. It&rsquo;s also not surprising that most of those founders, such as <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=mwseibel">mwseibel</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=rahulvohra">rahulvohra</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=tikhon">tikhon</a> also founded a Y Combinator startup. (although Paul Graham <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=pg">himself</a> only has a 0.856 average).</p>

<h1>What are Hacker News' favorite programming languages?</h1>

<p>One of the infamous memes about Hacker News is programming language elitism, with favoritism for languages such as Lisp and Erlang.</p>

<p>But what programming languages are indeed the most popular on Hacker News?</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-lang-num-submissions.png"></p>

<p>Javascript is very popular, especially with the rising popularity of node.js. Go is unexpectedly frequently submitted for being such a new language. (although it&rsquo;s possible for &ldquo;go&rdquo; to be used in a context outside of a programing language.) Lisp and Erlang are indeed obscure, which might discredit the meme.</p>

<p>Which programming languages are most well-liked on HN?</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-lang-avg-submissions.png"></p>

<p>&hellip;so Lisp and Erlang <em>are</em> well-liked on HN.</p>

<p>At the least, in both cases, no one on Hacker News likes PHP.</p>

<h1>Snowden and Bitcoin</h1>

<p>Edward Snowden&rsquo;s leaks in June 2013 about the NSA and PRISM affected the entire tech industry, including Hacker News. How did Hacker News react to the leaks?</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-snowden.png"></p>

<p>Strongly.</p>

<p>But after the June spike, discussion about the NSA decreased significantly, but it&rsquo;s still a popular topic.</p>

<p>Bitcoin is more interesting since it has had three distinct surges:</p>

<p><img src="/img/hn-bitcoin.png"></p>

<p>The June 2011 spike was due to the theft of <a href="https://bitcointalk.org/index.php?topic=16457.0">25,000 Bitcoin</a>, the April 2013 spike happened during the first rise-and-fall from $200/BTC, and the November 2013 spike happened during the second rise-and-fall from $1,000/BTC.</p>

<p>Hacker News is a great model for a link aggregator.  It emphasizes more on quality content than the quantity of content, and it has paid off over the years.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Code for getting all the HN submissions is <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/hacker-news-download-all-stories">available on GitHub</a>. Unfortunately, the Hacker News data is too large to distribute freely. <a href="http://minimaxir.com/contact/">Contact me</a> if you want the raw data or any data to reproduce the charts.</em></p>

<p><em>Note: there appear to be <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Zdex42KE-8DFIHujhVWjJ3yqilJSws2EbT8VAARPYgE/edit?usp=sharing">some gaps in the data</a> for dates before 2010. This appears to be caused by the API server: for example, compare the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitted?id=liebke">number of submissions as reported by HN for top user liebke</a> (21) and the <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=story,author_liebke">number of submissions as reported by the API</a> for liebke (14, with the last 7 submitted stories missing relative to the HN output). Also, number of stories (1,265,114) in the output data and the <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/">server data</a> (~1,267,000 as of publishing) are very close, making the discrepancy unlikely caused by client error. As a result, any chart that is based on a time series does not start earlier than 2010.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Many #nofilter Instagram Photos Actually Have No Filter?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/the-filter-truth/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/the-filter-truth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most <a href="http://instagram.com/">Instagram</a> photos have filters applied to make them look more retro/cool. Instagram users are also able to apply tags to a photo to help categorize and promote them to the Instagram community. One such tag, #nofilter, is intended to emphasize such natural beauty that no filter is necessary to enhance the image. (or the photographer is just too lazy to decide on a filter)</p>

<p>But how many #nofilter images actually <em>have</em> no filter?</p>

<p><img src="/img/instagram_selfie.gif"></p>

<p>As it turns not, not all of them.</p>

<p>After retrieving about 50,000 images through the Instagram API (code <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/get-data-from-photos-from-instagram-tags">available on GitHub</a>), here is the breakdown of filters on #nofilter-tagged Instagram images:</p>

<p><img src="/img/nofilter.png"></p>

<p>Only 83% of #nofilter images have no filter?! You had one job, Instagram! :(</p>

<hr />

<p><em>The actual reason that this is happening is because Instagram rewards #tagspamming. More on that in a future blog post.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Thoughtful Analysis of the Most Poorly-Designed Chart Ever]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/01/more-language-more-problems/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-20T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/01/more-language-more-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I was surfing Reddit and came across an <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ProgrammerHumor/comments/1ur3ny/unnecessary_graph_of_most_desired_skills_in_2013/">interesting infographic</a> within the <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ProgrammerHumor/">ProgrammerHumor subreddit</a>. The infographic, as compiled by tech blog <a href="http://readwrite.com/">ReadWrite</a>, depicts the Top 10 Most In-Demand Developer Skills of 2013, as compiled by <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/">Stack Overflow</a> through keyword searches.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/infographic-1.jpg"></p>

<p>Take a look at the chart. What’s good and bad about it?</p>

<h1>The Good</h1>

<p>The data is properly cited.</p>

<h1>The Bad</h1>

<p><strong>EVERYTHING ELSE.</strong></p>

<p>What’s terrible about the graph? Let me count the ways:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Using discrete values in the X-Axis for a continuous measurement (i.e. the percentage). And not only that, discrete values with two significant figures, which make the X-Axis unusually cluttered.</p></li>
<li><p>The Y-Axis is Language. This implies that some programming languages are more language than others.  (<a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10152166149970450&amp;set=a.432190050449.225968.582270449&amp;type=1&amp;stream_ref=10">to be fair</a>, Java is more language than Android)</p></li>
<li><p>Not all entries on the chart are programming languages. (Android, for example, is an operating system.)</p></li>
<li><p>The 45-degree line in the chart implies that the relationship between language and %-of-searches is perfectly linear, where in reality the data has an upward-parabolic shape.</p></li>
<li><p>No relative proportions between the programming languages. We can&rsquo;t accurately see the increase in language Java has relative to Android just by looking at the graph.</p></li>
<li><p>Cannot easily associate a language with the given X-Axis value. The logos representing the programming language oscillate around the line, and it&rsquo;s hard to see at a glance which percentage corresponds to which language.</p></li>
</ul>


<h1>Fixing the Chart</h1>

<p>This isn’t one of those blog posts that make snarky criticism without offering any constructive input. (those will be posted next week). How can we make the chart somewhat logical?</p>

<p>The easiest way to improve the chart is to convert the chart from a line chart to a column chart. Here’s a column chart that keeps the intended impression of the original chart:</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-1.png"></p>

<p>A much bigger improvement, although unfortunately without the cool hand-drawn logos. The axes are no longer illogical and it’s easy to determine the relative impact of each language (e.g. Java is clearly, clearly at the top). However, the large amount of text can clutter the bars, and it can be difficult to correlate the raw percentage with the scale at a glance.</p>

<p>Another option is to rotate the chart and use bars instead of columns:</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-2.png"></p>

<p>This fixes the text issue by giving more room for text with most of the factors, but the Java text clips outside the chart. The correlation issue between language and percent value persists.</p>

<p>A best-of-both-worlds approach is to display the language on the Y-Axis and the raw percent value on the corresponding bar itself, allowing us to forgo the percent metric axis entirely.</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-3.png"></p>

<p>There we go. Minimalist, fixes both the text and correlation issues, and gets the point across effectively.</p>

<p>All of these charts were created using R and ggplot2, and you can download the R code in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/developer-graphs">this GitHub repository</a>. I wish the <a href="http://readwrite.com/2014/01/08/in-demand-tech-skills-of-2013-java">orginal ReadWrite article</a> used a chart like the last one and…</p>

<p>Wait, they changed the infographic?</p>

<p><img src="/img/infographic-2.jpg"></p>

<p>Hey, they fixed the chart, and it’s using a similar design as mine! What a crazy random happenstance!</p>

<p>The article was appended with an update:</p>

<blockquote><p>An earlier version of the infographic in this story presented the StackOverflow data in a confusing and conceptually problematic fashion. It has been updated.</p></blockquote>

<p>&ldquo;Problematic&rdquo; is the world&rsquo;s biggest understatement.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Probabilistically Generating GitHub Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/innovation-rng/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-29T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/innovation-rng</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Grant Slatton made an amusing post on Hacker News yesterday titled &ldquo;<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6815282">Show HN: Probabilistically Generating HN Post Titles</a>&rdquo;. By using the statistical principle of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain">Markov chains</a>, Slatton was able to <a href="http://grantslatton.com/hngen/">generate eerily-realistic Hacker News headlines</a> such as &ldquo;Facebook detects if you are not a pilot&rdquo; and &ldquo;The No. 1 Habit of Highly Effective Mediocre Entrepreneurs.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Could Markov chains be applied to any other data sets for hilarious effect? By using Slatton&rsquo;s <a href="https://gist.github.com/grantslatton/7694811">Python implementation of Markov chains</a> plus 300,000 descriptions of public GitHub repositories retrieved from their API, I discovered that statistical randomness can indeed create funny innovation.</p>

<p><img src="/img/github-wordcloud-mac.png"></p>

<p>You can download a list of 1,000 Markov chain-generated projects <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/github_markov.txt">here</a>. Here are a few interesting ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>MaNGOS is a free, Open Source implementation of a tag at relatively random intervals.</li>
<li>A Warhammer 40k simulator to teach myself both OpenGL and Clojure</li>
<li>Perl interface to Git repositories via Ruby.</li>
<li>A windows live messenger network client written in Erlang</li>
<li>Rails plugin which allows to talk anonymously and use tripcodes if you want.</li>
<li>A Firebug extension for displaying the latest from Hacker News</li>
<li>Sinatra-inspired JavaScript node.js web development framework for lua. Inspired by rspec</li>
<li>Inverted Index on top of Tornado</li>
<li>Android LED interface library for various wave propagation techniques.</li>
<li>CatchAPI is a Java API to remove the need for boring project setup.</li>
<li>Adds basic social networking capabilities to your lighting system based on the concept of the Working with Rails</li>
<li>Brute force your OpenERP data integration with flatfiles</li>
<li>Culerity integrates Cucumber and Celerity in order to shutdown the computer.</li>
<li>Parses ANSI color codes and converts them to iphone compatible mp4s using HandBrake</li>
<li>A simple OFX (Open Financial Exchange) parser built on top of WordPress. Rolopress core theme</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>The code used to get the project descriptions from the GitHub API is available in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/get-github-repo-descriptions">this GitHub repository</a>, and you can download the ~300k repo descriptions <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/github_repo_desc.zip">here</a>. [5MB .zip]</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reddit is Growing Slowly, but Surely]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-18T07:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reddit has certainty received more attention in the mainstream media with its involvement in such events as the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/business/media/bombings-trip-up-reddit-in-its-turn-in-spotlight.html?_r=0">Boston Marathon Bombings</a> and <a href="hhttp://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/z1c9z/i_am_barack_obama_president_of_the_united_states/">President Obama&rsquo;s AMA</a>. But has this publicity led to increase in overall activity on the site?</p>

<p>I analyzed the daily number of submissions from over two years, August 6th, 2011 to September 25, 2013 (41 million submissions total), to see which events, if any, have affected Reddit&rsquo;s growth rate. As it turns out, Reddit grows by itself.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/reddit_daily-mac.png"></p>

<p>Reddit&rsquo;s growth over the past two years has been almost entirely <strong>linear</strong>, with no notable acceleration in submission activity at any point in time.</p>

<p>Running a linear regression on daily number of submissions vs. number of days since the first date (8/6/11) reveals that the expected increase in number of submissions each successive day on average is <strong>66.48 submissions</strong>  (+1,948 submissions each successive month, +24,259 submissions each successive year)</p>

<p>This growth rate alone explains <strong>86.83%</strong> of the variation in number of submissions, indicating that external factors such as media publicity explain the remaining 13% of the variation.</p>

<p>From a business perspective, it&rsquo;s impressive that Reddit still continues to grow for being such a mature internet business, but prospective investors for a rumored <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/06/reddit-rumored-to-be-raising-money-at-a-400-million-valuation/">fundraising at a $400 Million valuation</a> might be weary that Reddit&rsquo;s growth is only linear, in contrast to the <strong>exponential</strong> growth of other startups such as Snapchat. (In fairness, submission activity may not necessarily correlate with revenue-driving content consumption activity)</p>

<p>A couple stray observations:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>On January 18th, 2012, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the minimum among the two-year period due to Reddit&rsquo;s participation in the Internet blackout in protest of SOPA. (Reddit&rsquo;s blackout was only from 8AM to 8PM EST, which is why there are a nonzero number of submissions for that day).</p></li>
<li><p>On April 1st, 2013, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the maximum among the two-year period due to April Fool&rsquo;s Day, and the numerous amount of submissions for <em>X</em> brand/website&rsquo;s well-timed joke. However, I&rsquo;m not entirely sure why there&rsquo;s a spike for April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2013, but not April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2012.</p></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data used to create the time-series chart at <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGZ2Zkk1MGF3SjZxdC1sRzV5SW9zRWc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
