<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Data | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-26T10:27:55-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[max@minimaxir.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Least Effective Method For Blocking Web Scraping of a Website]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/09/buzzscrape/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-26T10:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/09/buzzscrape</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As someone who typically plays around with data from public website APIs, I figured it would be worthwhile to learn how to get data from websites the old-fashioned way: through force, via web scraping. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_scraping">Web scraping</a> is a technique where the user downloads the raw HTML of a webpage, and parses the inherent structure of the webpage to extract the necessary data.</p>

<p>In order to understand the mechanics behind web scraping, I used a tool from new Y Combinator startup <a href="https://www.kimonolabs.com/">Kimono Labs</a>, which allows the user to click structured elements of any website and quickly create an API that can access all the collected data and convert it into an easy-to-access form. My first target was BuzzFeed, since their social interaction data might be useful in determining how it became so big so quickly, and maybe also determine just how effective those stupid listicles are.</p>

<h1><span><i class="fa fa-terminal"></i></span> Live Free and Scrape Hard</h1>

<p>For example, here&rsquo;s a pair of typical BuzzFeed articles:</p>

<p><img src="/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_example.png"></p>

<p>And here&rsquo;s the corresponding output of <a href="https://www.kimonolabs.com/apis/1x3l57k0">my Kimono Labs BuzzFeed scraper</a> for those two articles:</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='html'>{&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;     &quot;title&quot;: {
      &quot;text&quot;: &quot;Stop Tweeting Instagram Links&quot;,
      &quot;href&quot;: &quot;http://www.buzzfeed.com/katienotopoulos/stop-tweeting-instagram-links&quot;
    },
    &quot;content&quot;: &quot;I CANNOT REMAIN SILENT ON THIS ISSUE ANY LONGER.&quot;,
    &quot;author&quot;: &quot;Katie Notopoulos&quot;,
    &quot;num_responses&quot;: &quot;123&quot;
  },
  {
    &quot;title&quot;: {
      &quot;text&quot;: &quot;28 Things Your Gchat Availability Status Really Means&quot;,
      &quot;href&quot;: &quot;http://www.buzzfeed.com/katieheaney/28-things-your-gchat-availability-status-really-means&quot;
    },
    &quot;content&quot;: &quot;Let’s chat.&quot;,
    &quot;author&quot;: &quot;Katie Heaney&quot;,
    &quot;num_responses&quot;: &quot;13&quot;
  }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>This data format (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON">JSON</a>) can be processed and manipulated by nearly any modern programming language.</p>

<p>Each BuzzFeed category page has about 22 articles, but the scraper can also access successive pages to retrieve more articles. This works by finding the URL of the next page by deriving the URL from the &ldquo;Older&rdquo; button if present on that page. Then the scraper can find the Older button on the page after that, and so forth, until all pages on BuzzFeed are scraped.</p>

<p><img src="/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_page.png"></p>

<p>My BuzzFeed scraper, for some reason, only retrieved 10 pages maximum. So I used my QA skills and traced the exact route the scraper took, navigating through all 10 pages by clicking the Older button.</p>

<p>What was on Page #10 shocked me. OMG. I could not believe my eyes.</p>

<p><img src="/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_disable.png"></p>

<h1><span><i class="fa fa-times-circle-o"></i></span> No Scrape For You</h1>

<p>The Older button is <em>disabled</em> on page 10? <strong>WHY?</strong></p>

<p>BuzzFeed is a website created in the 21st century that <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/08/11/technology/a-move-to-go-beyond-lists-for-content-at-buzzfeed.html?_r=0">just raised $50 million</a>. This is not a peculiar technical limitation due to bad coding or bad infrastructure; this is a deliberate functional aspect of the product.</p>

<p>It is my personal mantra that if a startup has a particularly unintuitive UI/UX behavior, it&rsquo;s a form of &ldquo;growth hacking&rdquo; that my feeble brain cannot comprehend.</p>

<p>Could the reason that BuzzFeed disables access to pages past 10 is that they want to prevent archive browsing, thereby putting more of an emphasis on more recent and more potentially-viral articles? That wouldn&rsquo;t make sense; if a person is so hooked on BuzzFeed articles that they are at Page 10, why stop them? It&rsquo;s still free page views and ad revenue.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s likely that BuzzFeed has statistics on how many users actually visit article pages up to Page 10. Perhaps their data analysts noted &ldquo;hey, only 0.0027% of our visitors actually read up to Page 10, anyone who actually reads that far is three standard deviations away from normal therefore they must be a web scraper!&rdquo; and recommend punitive action accordingly.</p>

<p>I noted earlier that it definitely was not a technical limitation that kept pages greater than 10 from being accessed. If you look at the URLs of the BuzzFeed screenshots above, you&rsquo;ll notice a &ldquo;<em>p=2</em>&rdquo; parameter for Page 2 or a &ldquo;<em>p=10</em>&rdquo; parameter for Page 10. What happens if you just change the 10 to a 11?</p>

<p>You go to Page 11. And you can go all the way to page <em>200</em> in some categories.</p>

<p><img src="/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_200.png"></p>

<p>Incidentally, this is easier and more reliable to implement programmatically than searching for the Older button and extracting the URL.</p>

<p>So the disabling of the button will only stop stupid web scrapers. Yes, that makes my BuzzFeed web scraper a stupid web scraper, <em>but that&rsquo;s not the point!</em> It just makes the BuzzFeed&rsquo;s motive behind disabling the button at Page 10  even more baffling.</p>

<p>What did I do now that my quick-and-dirty BuzzFeed scraper couldn&rsquo;t parse a statistically significant amount of BuzzFeed articles? I did the only logical thing.</p>

<p>I spent a weekend learning how to use <a href="http://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/">BeautifulSoup</a> in Python and parsed BuzzFeed the hard way, while changing the page number in the URL to pagenate through the pages. And I even was able to add new features to the scraper, such as simultaneously scraping the number of Facebook Shares a given BuzzFeed article generates.</p>

<p><img src="/img/buzzscrape/buzzfeed_listicles.png"></p>

<p>Hey, there <em>is</em> a relationship between listicle size and social media engagement!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Statistical Difference Between 1-Star and 5-Star Reviews on Yelp]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/09/one-star-five-stars/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/09/one-star-five-stars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many business in the real world encourage their customers to &ldquo;Rate us on Yelp!&rdquo;. <a href="http://www.yelp.com/">Yelp</a>, the &ldquo;best way to find local businesses,&rdquo; relies on user reviews to help its viewers find the best places. Both positive and negative reviews are helpful in this mission: positive reviews on Yelp identify the best places, negative reviews identify places where people <em>shouldn&rsquo;t</em> go. Usually, both positive and negative reviews are not based on objective attributes of the business, but on the experience the writer has with the establishment.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp_review_pos.png"></p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp_review_neg.png"></p>

<p>I analyzed the language present in 1,125,458 Yelp Reviews using the dataset from the <a href="http://www.yelp.com/dataset_challenge">Yelp Dataset Challenge</a> containing reviews of businesses in the cities of Phoenix, Las Vegas, Madison, Waterloo and Edinburgh. Users can rate businesses 1, 2, 3, 4, or 5 stars. When comparing the most-frequent two-word phrases between 1-star and 5-star reviews, the difference is apparent.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/Yelp-2-Gram-Small.jpg"></p>

<p>The 5-star Yelp reviews contain many instances of &ldquo;Great&rdquo;, &ldquo;Good&rdquo;, and &ldquo;Happy&rdquo;. In contrast, the 1-star Yelp reviews use very little positive language, and instead discuss the amount of &ldquo;minutes,&rdquo; presumably after long and unfortunate waits at the establishment. (Las Vegas is one of the cities where the reviews were collected, which is why it appears prominently in both 1-star and 5-star reviews)</p>

<p>Looking at three-word phrases tells more of a story.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/Yelp-3-Gram-Small.jpg"></p>

<p>1-Star reviews frequently contain warnings for potential customers, which promises that the author will &ldquo;never go back&rdquo; and a strong impression that issues stem from conflicts with &ldquo;the front desk&rdquo;, such as those at hotels. 5-star reviews &ldquo;love this place&rdquo; and &ldquo;can&rsquo;t wait to&rdquo; go back.</p>

<p>Can this language be used to predict reviews?</p>

<h1><span><i class="fa fa-line-chart"></i></span> Regression of Language</h1>

<p>To determine the causal impact on positive and negative words on the # of stars given in a review, we can perform a simple linear regression of stars on the number of positive words in the review, the number of negative words in the review, and the number of words in the review itself (since the length of the review is related to the number of positive/negative words; the longer the review, the more words)</p>

<p>A quick-and-dirty way to determine the number of positive/negative words in a given Yelp review is to compare each word of the review against a lexicon of positive/negative words, and count the number of review words in the lexicon. In this case, I use the <a href="http://www.cs.uic.edu/~liub/FBS/sentiment-analysis.html">lexicons compiled by UIC professor Bing Liu</a>.</p>

<p>Running a regression of # stars in a Yelp review on # positive words, # negative words, and # words in review, returns these results:</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='html'>Coefficients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;           Estimate  Std. Error  t value  Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)    
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Intercept)    3.692      1.670e-03  2210.0   &amp;lt;2e-16 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;
pos_words      0.122      2.976e-04   411.3   &amp;lt;2e-16 &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
neg_words     -0.154      4.887e-04  -315.9   &amp;lt;2e-16 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;
review_words  -0.003      1.984e-05  -169.4   &amp;lt;2e-16 &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residual standard error: 1.119 on 1125454 degrees of freedom
Multiple R-squared:  0.2589,    Adjusted R-squared:  0.2589
F-statistic: 1.311e+05 on 3 and 1125454 DF,  p-value: &amp;lt; 2.2e-16</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>The regression output explains these things:</p>

<ul>
<li>If a reviewer posted a blank review with no text in it, that review gave an average rating of 3.692.</li>
<li>For every positive word, the predicted average star rating given is increased by 0.122 on average (e.g. 8 positive words indicate a 1-star increase)</li>
<li>For every negative word, the predicted average star rating given is decreased by 0.15 on average (e.g. 6-7 negative words indicate a 1-star decrease)</li>
<li>The amount of words in the review has a lesser, negative effect. (A review that is 333 words indicates a 1-star decrease, but the average amount of words in a Yelp review is 130 words)</li>
<li>This model explains 25.98% of the variation in the number of stars given in a review. This sounds like a low percentage, but is impressive for such a simple model using unstructured real-world data.</li>
</ul>


<p>All of these conclusions are <em>extremely</em> statistically significant due to the large sample size.</p>

<p>Additionally, you could rephrase the regression as a logistic classification problem, where reviews rated 1, 2, or 3 stars are classified as &ldquo;negative,&rdquo; and reviews with 4 or 5 stars are classified as &ldquo;positive.&rdquo; Then, run the regression to determine the likelihood of a given review being positive. Running this regression (not shown) results in a logistic model with up to <em>75% accuracy</em>, a noted improvement over the &ldquo;no information rate&rdquo; of 66%, which is the model accuracy if you just guessed that every review was positive. The logistic model also has similar conclusions for the predictor variables as the linear model.</p>

<p>It can be proven that language has a strong statistical effect on review ratings, but that&rsquo;s intuitive enough. How have review ratings changed?</p>

<h1><span><i class="fa fa-bar-chart"></i></span> 1-Star and 5-Star Reviews, Visualized</h1>

<p>Since 2005, Yelp has had incredible growth in the number of new reviews.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp-review-time-series.png"></p>

<p>For that chart, it appears that each of the five rating brackets have grown at the same rate, but that isn&rsquo;t the case. Here&rsquo;s a chart of the rating brackets showing how the proportions of new reviews of each rating have changed over time.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp-review-time-proportion.png"></p>

<p>Early Yelp had mostly 4-star and 5-star reviews, as one might expect for an early Web 2.0 startup where the primary users who would be the only ones who would put in the effort to write a review would be those who had positive experiences. However, the behavior from 2010 onward is interesting: the relative proportions of both 1-star reviews <em>and</em> 5-star reviews increases over time.</p>

<p>As a result, the proportions of ratings in reviews from Yelp&rsquo;s beginning in 2005 and Yelp&rsquo;s present 2014 are incredibly different.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/Yelp-2005-2014.png"></p>

<p>More negativity, more positivity. Do they cancel out?</p>

<h1><span><i class="fa fa-heart"></i></span> How Positive Are Yelp Reviews?</h1>

<p>We can calculate relative <strong>positivity</strong> between reviews by taking the number of positive reviews in a review and dividing it by the number of words in the review itself.</p>

<p>The average positivity among all reviews is <em>5.6%</em>. Over time, the positivity has been relatively flat.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp-review-time-series-positivity.png"></p>

<p>Flat, but still increasing, mostly likely due to the increasing proportion of 5-star reviews. But the number of 1-star reviews also increased: do the two offset each other?</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp-review-positivity.png"></p>

<p>This histogram of positivity scores shows that 1-star reviews have lower positivity with rarely high positivity, and 5-star reviews rarely have low positivity and instead have very high positivity. The distribution for each star rating is close to a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_distribution">Normal distribution</a>, with each successive rating category peaking at increasing positivity values.</p>

<p>The relative proportion of each star rating reinforces this.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp-review-positivity-density.png"></p>

<p>Over half of the 0% positivity reviews are 1-star reviews, while over three-quarters of the reviews at the highest positivity levels are 5-star reviews. (note that the 2-star, 3-star, and 4-star ratings are not as significant at either extreme)</p>

<h1><span><i class="fa fa-meh-o"></i></span> How Negative Are Yelp Reviews?</h1>

<p>When working with the negativity of reviews, calculated by taking the number of negative words and dividing them by the number of total words in the review, the chart looks much different.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp-review-time-series-negativity.png"></p>

<p>The average negativity among all reviews is <em>2.0%</em>. Since the average positivity is 5.6%, this implies that the net sentiment among all reviews is positive, despite the increase in 1-star reviews over time.</p>

<p>The histogram of negative reviews looks much different as well.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp-review-negativity.png"></p>

<p>Even 1-star reviews aren&rsquo;t completely negative all the time.</p>

<p>The chart is heavily skewed right, making it difficult to determine the proportions of each rating at first glance.</p>

<p>Henceforth here&rsquo;s another proportion chart.</p>

<p><img src="/img/one-star-five-stars/yelp-review-negativity-density.png"></p>

<p>At low negativity, the proportions of negative review scores (1-star, 2-stars, 3-stars) and positive review scores (4-stars, 5-stars) are about equal, implying that negative reviews can be just as civil as positive reviews. But high negativity is solely present in 1-star and 2-star reviews.</p>

<p>From this article, you&rsquo;ve seen that Yelp reviews with 5-star ratings are generally positive, and Yelp reviews with 1-star are generally negative. Yes, this blog post is essentially &ldquo;Pretty Charts Made By Captain Obvious,&rdquo; but what&rsquo;s important is confirmation of these assumptions. Language plays a huge role in determining the ratings of reviews, and that knowledge could be applied to many other industries and review websites.</p>

<h1><span><i class="fa fa-star"></i><i class="fa fa-star"></i><i class="fa fa-star"></i><i class="fa fa-star"></i></span></h1>

<p>I&rsquo;d give this blog post a solid 4-stars. The content was great, but the length was long, although not as long as <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/06/reviewing-reviews/">some others</a>. Can&rsquo;t wait to read this post again!</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Yelp reviews were preprocessed with Python, by simultaneously converting the data from JSON to a tabular structure, tokenizing the words in the review, counting the positive/negative words, and storing bigrams and trigrams in a dictionary to later be exported for creaitng word clouds.</em></li>
<li><em>All data analysis was performed using R, and a ll charts were made using ggplot2. <a href="http://www.pixelmator.com/">Pixelmator</a> was used to manually add relevant annotations when necessary.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view both the Python and R code used to process and chart the data <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/yelp-review-analysis">in this GitHub repository</a>. Note that since Yelp prevents redistribution of the data, the code may not be reproducible.</em></li>
<li><em>You can download full-resolution PNGs of the two word clouds [5000x2000px] in <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/f20gwh9jvkibi4z/Yelp_Wordclouds_5000_200.zip?dl=0">this ZIP file</a> [18 MB]</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Data From Our Comments to the FCC About Net Neutrality]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/08/comments-about-comments/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-08T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/08/comments-about-comments</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year, the Federal Communications Commission, one of the governmental entities which polices the Internet in the United States, announced significant rule changes to the policy of &ldquo;<a href="http://www.fcc.gov/openinternet">Open Internet</a>.&rdquo; Open Internet, more commonly known as &ldquo;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Net_neutrality">net neutrality</a>,&rdquo; helps businesses facilitate competition and promote innovation on the internet, which help improve the internet as a whole. However, the proposed rule changes allow internet service providers (ISPs) to discriminate between different types of internet traffic (a &ldquo;fast lane&rdquo; for video and social media, for example).  Said pricing discrimination may end up affecting the consumers instead (e.g. paying $10/month for access to Facebook), which may reduce innovation due to increased costs to the consumers of internet bandwidth, i.e. the average American citizen.</p>

<p>The FCC recently <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/comments">opened up a comment period</a>, where the U.S. public can <a href="http://apps.fcc.gov/ecfs/upload/display?z=s6uf0">send or e-mail comments</a> on the changes to this policy. Naturally, the consumers of the internet reacted strongly. By August 2014, over <em>1.1 million comments</em> have been received by the FCC.</p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-words-small.png"></p>

<p>This week, the FCC <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/blog/fcc-makes-open-internet-comments-more-accessible-public">released a dataset</a> of about <a href="http://www.fcc.gov/files/ecfs/14-28/ecfs-files.htm">450,000 of these comments</a>. Looking at the data behind these comments, it&rsquo;s clear to see that the entire country is passionate against the rule changes to net neutrality.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a timeline of when comments about net neutrality were sent to the FCC:</p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-timeline-annotated.png"></p>

<p>There are clear spikes after important initiatives for awareness of the FCC&rsquo;s ruling. May 15th marked the <a href="http://www.savetheinternet.com/net-neutrality-resources">beginning of the Open Comment period</a> for the FCC&rsquo;s new guidelines, June 3rd marked the week after an airing of Last Week Tonight with John Oliver, which contained an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fpbOEoRrHyU">anti-net-neutrality rant</a> which went viral for the rest of the week. July 15th marked the close of the Open Comment period, which is why on July 14th, the internet rallied and sent in over a hundred thousand comments, which <a href="http://www.nydailynews.com/news/politics/fcc-extends-net-neutrality-open-comment-deadline-friday-article-1.1868238#kDMozMu84rJ5TPsl.97">crashed their servers</a> and forced them to extend the deadline.</p>

<p>But as with many awareness campaigns over the internet, this campaign may have &ldquo;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slacktivism">slacktivists</a>&rdquo;, as evidenced by the flat lines after the events where people stopped writing comments. How much effort did the U.S. people actually put into their submissions? One way to tell is to check the length of the submissions.</p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-comment-length.png"></p>

<p>Many comments were one-liners at about 20 words each, and many comments were multiparagraph notes at about 180 words each. But why is there a giant spike at about 300 words?</p>

<p>As it turns out, there were over 100,000 comments with exactly 1,477 characters (approximately 290 words). That number of characters (before cleaning) corresponds to a comment following this template:</p>

<blockquote><p>Net neutrality is the First Amendment of the Internet, the principle that Internet service providers (ISPs) treat all data equally. As an Internet user, net neutrality is vitally important to me. The FCC should use its Title II authority to protect it.</p>

<p>Most Americans have only one choice for truly high speed Internet: their local cable company. This is a political failure, and it is an embarrassment. America deserves competition and choice.</p>

<p>Without net neutrality, a bad situation gets even worse. These ISPs will now be able to manipulate our Internet experience by speeding up some services and slowing down others. That kills choice, diversity, and quality.</p>

<p>It also causes tremendous economic harm. If ISPs can speed up favored services and slow others, new businesses will no longer be able to rely on a level playing field. When ISPs can slow your site and destroy your business at will, how can any startup attract investors?</p>

<p>My friends, family, and I use the Internet for conversation and fun, but also for work and business. When you let ISPs mess with our Internet experience, you are attacking our social lives, our entertainment, and our economic well being. We won&rsquo;t stand for it.</p>

<p>ISPs are opposing Title II so that they can destroy the FCC&rsquo;s net neutrality rules in court. This is the same trick they pulled last time. Please, let&rsquo;s not be fooled again. Title II is the strong, legally sound way to enforce net neutrality. Use it.</p></blockquote>

<p>This is the default template for a submission at the <a href="https://www.battleforthenet.com">Battle for Net Neutrality</a> website. That means over about &frac14;th of the comments in the dataset, and atleast 1/10th of all comments submitted, used this website&rsquo;s submission form.</p>

<h1>Comments Across the Nation</h1>

<p>Net neutrality affects some individuals more than others. Not everyone in the U.S. may be as passionate over the issue, and many may not even be aware that such a threat to the modern internet even exists.</p>

<p>Which cities in the United States sent the most comments to the FCC?</p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-city.png"></p>

<p>Yes, Brooklyn, NY counts as a city according to the FCC.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not surprising that the three most populated cities in the U.S. (New York, Los Angeles, Chicago) top this chart due to the higher potential number of commenters. What is surprising yet important is that tech hubs with much fewer populations, such as San Francisco, Seattle, and Portland, all have extremely strong showings.</p>

<p>When you look at the distribution of comments by state of origin, it&rsquo;s even more apparent that California and Washington are some of the key drivers of the comments. (admittingly, it does resemble a <a href="https://xkcd.com/1138/">population map</a>)</p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-state-map.png"></p>

<p>What are the key words mentioned in the comments to the FCC?</p>

<p>The key players in who would benefit the most from the implementation of net neutrality are <a href="http://www.comcast.com/">Comcast</a> and <a href="http://www.verizon.com/">Verizon</a>, two of the biggest ISPs in the country. Which states have been speaking out the most against these institutions?</p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-state-map-comcast.png"></p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-state-map-verizon.png"></p>

<p>Comcast is a frequent topic of discussion (5.2% of all comments about net neutrality contain atleast 1 mention of Comcast), especially on the West Coast. On the other hand, less than half as many talk about Verizon (2.0% of all comments), except on the East Coast.</p>

<p>Although not on the map, Washington, DC actually had the most to comment on these two topics, with 11.7% comments having atleast one mention of Comcast and 8.8% of comments having atleast one mention of Verizon.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.netflix.com/">Netflix</a>, an internet video-streaming service which would likely be negatively impacted by the FCC ruling, was also discussed.</p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-state-map-netflix.png"></p>

<p>Discussion of Netflix from all around the country is very evenly distributed (2.1% of all comments), potentially because it&rsquo;s not location-specific as the presence of an ISP. (Montana apparently does not care much about Netflix.)</p>

<p>Another concern about net neutrality is the potential <a href="https://www.aclu.org/net-neutrality">fight against the First Amendment</a> and free speech itself, as ISPs could theoretically restrict traffic to unfavorable websites under the system. Which states are most passionate about free speech?</p>

<p><img src="/img/fcc/fcc-state-map-free-speech.png"></p>

<p>Much more activity in the Midwest and especially the North West than the previous maps. (2.1% of all comments discuss &ldquo;free speech&rdquo;) North Dakota apparently is relatively indifferent about the freedom of speech.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, at this period of time, it&rsquo;s hard to guess if the hundreds of thousands of comments sent to the FCC will actually cause them to reconsider their plans. The sheer quantity of comments, at the least, lets the FCC know that Americans feel strongly about the issue. It&rsquo;s clear that in the worst-case scenario where the ISPs win the net neutrality battle, the consumers of the internet in the United States <strong>will not remain passive</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Charts were generated using R and ggplot2.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view the data aggregated by date, by state, and by city in <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1D2T5Lg41IWfkQPEMLWq3fjU7_kJ8lDNc4H2wsbr4BbU/edit?usp=sharing">this Google Sheet</a>. You can download a CSV of the original comment metadata <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/7tzsk7kv7ctgydp/fcc_comments.zip">here</a>. [7.6MB .zip]</em></li>
<li><em>You can view a 3000px x 3000px image of the FCC comments word cloud <a href="http://i.imgur.com/I0dpEA6.png">here</a>.</em></li>
</ul>


<p><em><strong>EDIT: 8/9/14</strong>: Per <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8153091">comments on Hacker News</a>, I&rsquo;ve changed wording in a few paragraphs for clarification.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Wikipedia Entries Which Are Most-Edited by Members of the U.S. Congress]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/caucus-needed/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-15T08:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/caucus-needed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, the Twitter account <a href="https://twitter.com/congressedits">@congressedits</a> launched. This account is a bot that tweets edits to Wikipedia that were made by members of the U.S. Congress, in order to help <a href="http://inkdroid.org/journal/2014/07/10/why-congressedits/">facilitate transparency</a>. The account <a href="https://github.com/edsu/anon">works</a> by automatically tweeting any Wikipedia edits made by anonymous contributors with IP addresses between the known IP address blocks of the <a href="http://whois.arin.net/rest/org/USSAA/nets">U.S. Senate</a> or the <a href="http://whois.arin.net/rest/org/ISUHR/nets">House of Representatives</a>.</p>

<p>Google&rsquo;s <a href="https://developers.google.com/bigquery/">BigQuery</a> tool has a <a href="https://developers.google.com/bigquery/docs/dataset-wikipedia">sample dataset</a> of Wikipedia data, representing the data on 314 million article edits up to April 2010. Out of curiosity, I wrote a query which returns the top 100 pages with the most amount of edits by Wikipedia contributors in the U.S. Senate&rsquo;s IP block.</p>

<p><img src="/img/caucus-needed/senate-query.png"></p>

<p>Using this query for the Senate&rsquo;s IP block, and a similar one for the House of Representatives IP blocks, I retrieved the most-edited entries for both entities. You can access the spreadsheet of this data by <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/Congress_Wikipedia_Edits.pdf">downloading a .pdf</a> or by viewing the data online with <a href="https://www.icloud.com/iw/#numbers/BALY8siqBP4jYZq5E2OB20P-wlPpyXdycqqF/Congress_Wikipedia_Edits">Numbers for iCloud</a>, both of which contain high-resolution charts and clickable Wikipedia links. A <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qfFEwzNzc4KL4gqe2i4IoMO0ksmoYndCK0O0m46n37I/edit?usp=sharing">Google Sheets</a> version is also available.</p>

<p>Here are the Top 10 Wikipedia entries with the most amount of edits by members of the Senate:</p>

<p><img src="/img/caucus-needed/senate-wikipedia.png"></p>

<p>Wait a minute. Hawk from G.I. Joe?!</p>

<p>Saying that the query results were surprising would be the understatement of the century.</p>

<p>Two of the top-edited entries are directly pertaining to the U.S. Senate, which helps prove that the IP block is indeed the Senate&rsquo;s IP block. Both Kappa Upsilon Chi and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beta_Upsilon_Chi">Beta Upsilon Chi</a> are Christian fraternities. (however, the Kappa Upsilon Chi Wikipedia entry no longer exists for some reason)</p>

<p>The edits corresponding to actual people are ones which are the most interesting. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Swain_Lee">William Swain Lee</a> is a Delaware politician whose entry was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=William_Swain_Lee&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=31202175">created and edited</a> by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/156.33.148.107">user in the Senate IP block</a>. OrangePie is  a user who, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=7319910">according to his talk page</a>, was criticized for repeatedly recreating an entry for &ldquo;Michael Hardaway&rdquo; after deletion, who coincidentally worked for the Senate <a href="https://twitter.com/michaelhardaway">according to his Twitter bio</a>. In journalist <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=8593106">Paul D. Thacker&rsquo;s</a> entry, one Senate editor <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Paul_D._Thacker&amp;diff=311839513&amp;oldid=311689066">replaced a paragraph</a> of Thacker&rsquo;s biography with the word &ldquo;anus?&rdquo;. Jay Rockefeller is an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=337026">actual U.S. Senator</a>, so the edits are definitely a conflict of interest. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/156.33.96.28">user who made the edits</a> apparently also removed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jay_Rockefeller&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=33857327">information about a government investigation</a> into the Senator.</p>

<p>I have nothing to add for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=2814171">Hawk from G.I. Joe</a>.</p>

<p>Other interesting frequently-edited Wikipedia entries from members of the U.S. Senate are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=3626593">Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actor – Comedy Series</a> (11 edits), <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1226609">Wikipedia:Introduction</a> (5 edits) and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1749535">Crash (2004 film)</a> (5 edits)</p>

<p>The Wikipedia entries with the most amount of edits by members of the House of Representatives are somehow even <em>weirder</em>, and that&rsquo;s quite an accomplishment.</p>

<p><img src="/img/caucus-needed/house-wikipedia.png"></p>

<p>Well, if <em>anyone</em> in the entire United States would be experts on the topics of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=2352587">cleft chins</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1924543">dimples</a>, it would be the members of the House of Representatives.</p>

<p>Again, one of the most-edited entries corresponds to a House of Representatives topic, which helps validate the IP blocks. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=107610">Cerritos, California</a> location had <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Cerritos,_California&amp;diff=21384826&amp;oldid=21363395">neutral edits</a> made by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.231.249.141">rather dedicated Wikiuser</a>. Wynne, Arkansas and Michelle Ye&rsquo;s edits were made by the same dedicated Wikiuser. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1143590">Waverly, Pennsylvania</a> was edited by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/137.18.255.33">user</a> who&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Waverly,_Pennsylvania&amp;diff=7763793&amp;oldid=7761053">really passionate about Doc&rsquo;s Deli</a>. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1129560">Luis Fortuno</a>, former governor of Puerto Rico, had his <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Luis_Fortu%C3%B1o&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=134653411">history excised</a> by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.231.249.137">another user</a>. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=6260346">Betty Sutton</a>, however, is a actual Representative from Ohio, representing another conflict of interest, as another <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.228.129.9">user</a> constructed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Betty_Sutton&amp;diff=303743778&amp;oldid=296652449">most of her entry</a>.</p>

<p>I have nothing to add regarding <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=862471">effeminacy</a> in the House of Representatives.</p>

<p>Other interesting edits by members of the House include <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=18951054">Apocalypse Now</a> (10 edits), <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1161298">History of Italy as a monarchy and in the World Wars</a> (9 edits), and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=34071">Whitney Houston</a> (9 edits)</p>

<p>In the end, the members of the U.S. Congress have the same peculiar interests as typical Americans. However, when these people edit entries on topics in which they are directly involved, the potential bias threatens the integrity of all Wikipedia. And this is just the tip of the iceburg.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impact of the New Show HN Section on Show HN Submissions]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/show-hn/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T08:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/show-hn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hacker News, a tech-oriented link aggregator managed by Y Combinator, is a platform where software projects have launched to literally become multibillion-dollar companies. Submissions which contain the phrase &ldquo;Show HN&rdquo; usually designate a clever hack or weekend project. On <a href="http://blog.ycombinator.com/make-things-and-show-them">July 3rd 2014</a>, Hacker News <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/show">created a section of Hacker News</a> just for these Show HN projects.</p>

<p>Did this feature help or harm Show HN submissions as a whole?</p>

<p>Over the past few years, the average number of Show HN submissions per day has steadily risen. (this is strongly correlated with the <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/">growth of Hacker News as a whole</a>)</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-submissions.png"></p>

<p>More on that spike at the end later.</p>

<p>On Hacker News, users can upvote link submissions, which increases the point score of the submission; this point score is used as a rough proxy of link quality. The average amount of points per submission peaked in 2012, and has trended downward since then.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a chart of the points of Show HN submissions averaged by date of submission, then averaged across the previous 30-days to further smooth the variation and make the trend more apparent:</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-points.png"></p>

<p>Users can also comment on these Show HN posts. The average amount of comments has trended downward over time, albeit only slightly.</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-comments.png"></p>

<p>The combination of increased Show HN submissions and a decrease in point quality over time may imply that Show HN submissions have a low signal-to-noise ratio, i.e. a low amount of good submissions relative high amount of bad submissions.</p>

<p>Hitting the front page of Hacker News is the first step to virality. When users upvote submissions on Hacker News, those submissions can hit the front page after achieving enough points (combined with other factors, such as submission age and quantity of other submissions). At the least, if a submission has 10 points, it has most likely hit the front page sometime in its lifespan.</p>

<p>What proportion of the Show HN submissions hit the front page?</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-perc-front.png"></p>

<p>Over time, the amount of good Show HNs relative to the amount of bad Show HNs has been steadily decreasing.</p>

<p>Has the new Show HN feature helped improve the signal-to-noise ratio?</p>

<h1>Show and Tell HN</h1>

<p>We can look at the immediate impact of the new Show HN section by comparing the behavior of submissions before and after the announcement. The red area in the following charts represents the daily behavior in the couple months before the release (with the red horizontal dotted line representing the statistical average for the corresponding measurement), and the blue area/blue line represents the behavior after the release.</p>

<p>When the Show HN feature was first announced, everyone rushed to make a submission to test it out, and it showed. In fact, the number of submissions for every day after the feature was added was greater than the average number of submissions from before the addition.</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-submissions.png"></p>

<p>Average number of daily submissions before Show HN section is <strong>19.13</strong> submissions/day, average after is <strong>53.44</strong> submissions/day.</p>

<p>Average submission points and average submission comments (both aggregated by date of submission for smoothing) received a slight boost too.</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-points.png"></p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-comments.png"></p>

<p>Average number of daily points before Show HN section is <strong>11.40</strong> points/submission/day, average after is <strong>12.12</strong> points/submission/day.</p>

<p>Average number of daily comments before Show HN section is <strong>6.57</strong> comments/submission/day, average after is <strong>7.16</strong> comments/submission/day.</p>

<p>The percentage of Show HN submissions that hit the front page, however, moves in a different direction.</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-perc-front.png"></p>

<p>Average daily % of Show HN submissions which hit the front page before Show HN section is <strong>19.33%</strong>, average after is <strong>16.37%</strong>.</p>

<p>While the Show HN section gives more focus to Show HN submissions, the increased motivation for making Show HN submissions does not necessarily imply that the submissions will be better. It will take more time to see of the downward trend of Show HN quality continues over time.</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data was processed using R and all charts were made using ggplot2.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view the data of all the Show HN submissions and the derived moving averages <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1JHIlzYdsavWnw8Y5efHrOHCo3-WFGtIosJ2WqIV_Bn4/edit?usp=sharing">in this Google Sheet</a>.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view code necessary to reproduce these results  and reproduce all the charts in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/show-hn">this GitHub repository</a>. This repository also includes a .csv of all ~20,000 Show HNs obtained.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
