<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Data | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-15T08:31:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Wikipedia Entries Which Are Most-Edited by Members of the U.S. Congress]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/caucus-needed/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-15T08:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/caucus-needed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, the Twitter account <a href="https://twitter.com/congressedits">@congressedits</a> launched. This account is a bot that tweets edits to Wikipedia that were made by members of the U.S. Congress, in order to help <a href="http://inkdroid.org/journal/2014/07/10/why-congressedits/">facilitate transparency</a>. The account <a href="https://github.com/edsu/anon">works</a> by automatically tweeting any Wikipedia edits made by anonymous contributors with IP addresses between the known IP address blocks of the <a href="http://whois.arin.net/rest/org/USSAA/nets">U.S. Senate</a> or the <a href="http://whois.arin.net/rest/org/ISUHR/nets">House of Representatives</a>.</p>

<p>Google&rsquo;s <a href="https://developers.google.com/bigquery/">BigQuery</a> tool has a <a href="https://developers.google.com/bigquery/docs/dataset-wikipedia">sample dataset</a> of Wikipedia data, representing the data on 314 million article edits up to April 2010. Out of curiosity, I wrote a query which returns the top 100 pages with the most amount of edits by Wikipedia contributors in the U.S. Senate&rsquo;s IP block.</p>

<p><img src="/img/caucus-needed/senate-query.png"></p>

<p>Using this query for the Senate&rsquo;s IP block, and a similar one for the House of Representatives IP blocks, I retrieved the most-edited entries for both entities. You can access the spreadsheet of this data by <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/Congress_Wikipedia_Edits.pdf">downloading a .pdf</a> or by viewing the data online with <a href="https://www.icloud.com/iw/#numbers/BALY8siqBP4jYZq5E2OB20P-wlPpyXdycqqF/Congress_Wikipedia_Edits">Numbers for iCloud</a>, both of which contain high-resolution charts and clickable Wikipedia links. A <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qfFEwzNzc4KL4gqe2i4IoMO0ksmoYndCK0O0m46n37I/edit?usp=sharing">Google Sheets</a> version is also available.</p>

<p>Here are the Top 10 Wikipedia entries with the most amount of edits by members of the Senate:</p>

<p><img src="/img/caucus-needed/senate-wikipedia.png"></p>

<p>Wait a minute. Hawk from G.I. Joe?!</p>

<p>Saying that the query results were surprising would be the understatement of the century.</p>

<p>Two of the top-edited entries are directly pertaining to the U.S. Senate, which helps prove that the IP block is indeed the Senate&rsquo;s IP block. Both Kappa Upsilon Chi and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beta_Upsilon_Chi">Beta Upsilon Chi</a> are Christian fraternities. (however, the Kappa Upsilon Chi Wikipedia entry no longer exists for some reason)</p>

<p>The edits corresponding to actual people are ones which are the most interesting. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Swain_Lee">William Swain Lee</a> is a Delaware politician whose entry was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=William_Swain_Lee&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=31202175">created and edited</a> by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/156.33.148.107">user in the Senate IP block</a>. OrangePie is  a user who, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=7319910">according to his talk page</a>, was criticized for repeatedly recreating an entry for &ldquo;Michael Hardaway&rdquo; after deletion, who coincidentally worked for the Senate <a href="https://twitter.com/michaelhardaway">according to his Twitter bio</a>. In journalist <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=8593106">Paul D. Thacker&rsquo;s</a> entry, one Senate editor <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Paul_D._Thacker&amp;diff=311839513&amp;oldid=311689066">replaced a paragraph</a> of Thacker&rsquo;s biography with the word &ldquo;anus?&rdquo;. Jay Rockefeller is an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=337026">actual U.S. Senator</a>, so the edits are definitely a conflict of interest. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/156.33.96.28">user who made the edits</a> apparently also removed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jay_Rockefeller&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=33857327">information about a government investigation</a> into the Senator.</p>

<p>I have nothing to add for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=2814171">Hawk from G.I. Joe</a>.</p>

<p>Other interesting frequently-edited Wikipedia entries from members of the U.S. Senate are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=3626593">Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actor – Comedy Series</a> (11 edits), <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1226609">Wikipedia:Introduction</a> (5 edits) and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1749535">Crash (2004 film)</a> (5 edits)</p>

<p>The Wikipedia entries with the most amount of edits by members of the House of Representatives are somehow even <em>weirder</em>, and that&rsquo;s quite an accomplishment.</p>

<p><img src="/img/caucus-needed/house-wikipedia.png"></p>

<p>Well, if <em>anyone</em> in the entire United States would be experts on the topics of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=2352587">cleft chins</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1924543">dimples</a>, it would be the members of the House of Representatives.</p>

<p>Again, one of the most-edited entries corresponds to a House of Representatives topic, which helps validate the IP blocks. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=107610">Cerritos, California</a> location had <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Cerritos,_California&amp;diff=21384826&amp;oldid=21363395">neutral edits</a> made by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.231.249.141">rather dedicated Wikiuser</a>. Wynne, Arkansas and Michelle Ye&rsquo;s edits were made by the same dedicated Wikiuser. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1143590">Waverly, Pennsylvania</a> was edited by a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/137.18.255.33">user</a> who&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Waverly,_Pennsylvania&amp;diff=7763793&amp;oldid=7761053">really passionate about Doc&rsquo;s Deli</a>. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1129560">Luis Fortuno</a>, former governor of Puerto Rico, had his <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Luis_Fortu%C3%B1o&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=134653411">history excised</a> by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.231.249.137">another user</a>. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=6260346">Betty Sutton</a>, however, is a actual Representative from Ohio, representing another conflict of interest, as another <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/143.228.129.9">user</a> constructed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Betty_Sutton&amp;diff=303743778&amp;oldid=296652449">most of her entry</a>.</p>

<p>I have nothing to add regarding <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=862471">effeminacy</a> in the House of Representatives.</p>

<p>Other interesting edits by members of the House include <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=18951054">Apocalypse Now</a> (10 edits), <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=1161298">History of Italy as a monarchy and in the World Wars</a> (9 edits), and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki?curid=34071">Whitney Houston</a> (9 edits)</p>

<p>In the end, the members of the U.S. Congress have the same peculiar interests as typical Americans. However, when these people edit entries on topics in which they are directly involved, the potential bias threatens the integrity of all Wikipedia. And this is just the tip of the iceburg.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impact of the New Show HN Section on Show HN Submissions]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/show-hn/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T08:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/show-hn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hacker News, a tech-oriented link aggregator managed by Y Combinator, is a platform where software projects have launched to literally become multibillion-dollar companies. Submissions which contain the phrase &ldquo;Show HN&rdquo; usually designate a clever hack or weekend project. On <a href="http://blog.ycombinator.com/make-things-and-show-them">July 3rd 2014</a>, Hacker News <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/show">created a section of Hacker News</a> just for these Show HN projects.</p>

<p>Did this feature help or harm Show HN submissions as a whole?</p>

<p>Over the past few years, the average number of Show HN submissions per day has steadily risen. (this is strongly correlated with the <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/hacking-hacker-news/">growth of Hacker News as a whole</a>)</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-submissions.png"></p>

<p>More on that spike at the end later.</p>

<p>On Hacker News, users can upvote link submissions, which increases the point score of the submission; this point score is used as a rough proxy of link quality. The average amount of points per submission peaked in 2012, and has trended downward since then.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a chart of the points of Show HN submissions averaged by date of submission, then averaged across the previous 30-days to further smooth the variation and make the trend more apparent:</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-points.png"></p>

<p>Users can also comment on these Show HN posts. The average amount of comments has trended downward over time, albeit only slightly.</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-comments.png"></p>

<p>The combination of increased Show HN submissions and a decrease in point quality over time may imply that Show HN submissions have a low signal-to-noise ratio, i.e. a low amount of good submissions relative high amount of bad submissions.</p>

<p>Hitting the front page of Hacker News is the first step to virality. When users upvote submissions on Hacker News, those submissions can hit the front page after achieving enough points (combined with other factors, such as submission age and quantity of other submissions). At the least, if a submission has 10 points, it has most likely hit the front page sometime in its lifespan.</p>

<p>What proportion of the Show HN submissions hit the front page?</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-perc-front.png"></p>

<p>Over time, the amount of good Show HNs relative to the amount of bad Show HNs has been steadily decreasing.</p>

<p>Has the new Show HN feature helped improve the signal-to-noise ratio?</p>

<h1>Show and Tell HN</h1>

<p>We can look at the immediate impact of the new Show HN section by comparing the behavior of submissions before and after the announcement. The red area in the following charts represents the daily behavior in the couple months before the release (with the red horizontal dotted line representing the statistical average for the corresponding measurement), and the blue area/blue line represents the behavior after the release.</p>

<p>When the Show HN feature was first announced, everyone rushed to make a submission to test it out, and it showed. In fact, the number of submissions for every day after the feature was added was greater than the average number of submissions from before the addition.</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-submissions.png"></p>

<p>Average number of daily submissions before Show HN section is <strong>19.13</strong> submissions/day, average after is <strong>53.44</strong> submissions/day.</p>

<p>Average submission points and average submission comments (both aggregated by date of submission for smoothing) received a slight boost too.</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-points.png"></p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-comments.png"></p>

<p>Average number of daily points before Show HN section is <strong>11.40</strong> points/submission/day, average after is <strong>12.12</strong> points/submission/day.</p>

<p>Average number of daily comments before Show HN section is <strong>6.57</strong> comments/submission/day, average after is <strong>7.16</strong> comments/submission/day.</p>

<p>The percentage of Show HN submissions that hit the front page, however, moves in a different direction.</p>

<p><img src="/img/show-hn/show-hn-end-perc-front.png"></p>

<p>Average daily % of Show HN submissions which hit the front page before Show HN section is <strong>19.33%</strong>, average after is <strong>16.37%</strong>.</p>

<p>While the Show HN section gives more focus to Show HN submissions, the increased motivation for making Show HN submissions does not necessarily imply that the submissions will be better. It will take more time to see of the downward trend of Show HN quality continues over time.</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data was processed using R and all charts were made using ggplot2.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view the data of all the Show HN submissions and the derived moving averages <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1JHIlzYdsavWnw8Y5efHrOHCo3-WFGtIosJ2WqIV_Bn4/edit?usp=sharing">in this Google Sheet</a>.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view code necessary to reproduce these results  and reproduce all the charts in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/show-hn">this GitHub repository</a>. This repository also includes a .csv of all ~20,000 Show HNs obtained.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who Performs the Best in Online Classes?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/online-class-charts/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-10T08:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/online-class-charts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the end of May, <a href="http://www.harvard.edu/">Harvard</a> and <a href="http://web.mit.edu/">MIT</a> jointly <a href="http://newsoffice.mit.edu/2014/mit-and-harvard-release-de-identified-learning-data-open-online-courses">released a dataset</a> containing statistics about their online courses in the Academic Year of 2013. This <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7910/DVN/26147">Person-Course De-Identified dataset</a> contains 641,138 events, chronicling 476,532 students who have taken up to 13 unique courses from a variety of topics:</p>

<p><img src="/img/gender-course/mit-harvard-courses.png"></p>

<p>However, this assortment of courses is not a substitution for a typical college education, as the vast majority of students only take one class.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/student-courses.png"></p>

<p>Very, very few students take more than one class (22% of all students).</p>

<p>Other interesting variables included with the data set are the level-of-education of the student, the birth date of the student, the gender of the student, and the geographical location of student.</p>

<p>Which types of student characteristics lead to the best performance in these online classes? That depends on how you define &ldquo;performance.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a look at the attendance of all the classes:</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/class-attendance.png"></p>

<p>Harvard&rsquo;s Introduction to Computer Science is by far the most popular class, and that&rsquo;s only accounting for one semester. (it still beat MIT&rsquo;s Intro to CS/Programming, which had 2 semesters).</p>

<p>Each color bar indicates the level of student participation in the class. <strong>Registered</strong> means the student simply registered for the class; <strong>Viewed</strong> means that the student viewed some of the course material, <strong>Explored</strong> means that students viewed atleast half of the course material, and <strong>Certified</strong> means that students completed the course and received a certificate of accomplishment. For the chart, it&rsquo;s interesting to note that most classes have a high percentage of people in each class who simply register just for fun and <em>don&rsquo;t actually do anything.</em></p>

<p>One metric of course success is the completion rate of each course, i.e. how many people actually complete the course after starting it. A frequent criticism of free online classes is that this number is very low, but what are the actual completion rates of these 13 classes?</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/class-perc-finished.png"></p>

<p>Completion rates are low across the board, from 0.8% to 7.5%. A <a href="http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2013/05/10/new-study-low-mooc-completion-rates">2013 study</a> found that completion rate is less than 7%, which this data follows. Apparently, Challenges of Global Poverty is a very interesting course.</p>

<p>After the student completes a class, he or she receives a final grade, and if the grade is above the cutoff point (usually 50% &ndash; 80%), they will complete the class and receive the certificate. Here&rsquo;s the distribution of the average grades for students in each class, given that the student has successfully completed the class:</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/class-perc-grade.png"></p>

<p>The grades vary significantly between classes. This doesn&rsquo;t necessarily imply that some classes are harder than others; it&rsquo;s possible some classes had lower cutoffs and therefore the effort put in by the students is lower. However, the perfect 100% average for Harvard&rsquo;s Intro to CS course implies that the class is pass/fail and that students can&rsquo;t get a final grade less than 100%. (as a result, we&rsquo;ll need to remove that class from future grade analyses in order to prevent bias due to the lack of score variance)</p>

<h1>Age</h1>

<p>Online classes are marketed toward college-age students.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/student-age.png"></p>

<p>The mean age is about <strong>27.7</strong>, with a standard deviation of 8.89. The shape skews right and resembles a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_distribution">gamma distribution</a>. There are even plenty of teenagers taking these classes too.</p>

<p>The proportion of students who take more than one class for each age group has a slightly flatter distribution, although more centralized at students in their 20&rsquo;s.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/student-num-classes.png"></p>

<p>What about completion rate?</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/student-fulfillment.png"></p>

<p>Completion rate is a little more evenly distributed between the ages, indicating that the two metrics are  likely uncorrelated. However, the older students have nearly double the completion rate of classes. (more on this later)</p>

<h1>Education</h1>

<p>One of the student-provided attributes is his or her highest level of education. These values are &ldquo;Less than Secondary,&rdquo; &ldquo;Secondary&rdquo;, &ldquo;Bachelor&rsquo;s&rdquo;, &ldquo;Master&rsquo;s&rdquo;, and &ldquo;Doctorate.&rdquo; Here&rsquo;s the distribution of the 409,601 students who provided their LoE:</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/education-count.png"></p>

<p>This shows that the majority of students who are taking these online classes have already finished college and already obtained a degree, and therefore are likely taking the course as supplemental material.</p>

<p>We can correlate the levels of education with the average age for each LoE as a double-check.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/education-age.png"></p>

<p>Indeed, each LoE average age is above the minimum expected threshold of time needed for each degree (~18 years for Secondary, ~22 years for Bachelor&rsquo;s, etc.)</p>

<p>How does the completion rate vary?</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/education-fulfillment.png"></p>

<p>Interestingly, those with Less than Secondary education have a much higher completion rate than those with Secondary educations and Bachelor&rsquo;s Degrees.</p>

<p>But are Doctorate smarter than those with lower education levels? Do they get higher grades on average?</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/education-grade.png"></p>

<p>As it turns out, yes. The education level of a student is very relevant to a his or her academic performance in online classes.</p>

<h1>Gender</h1>

<p>I previously <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/gender-course/">made a blog post</a> discussing the genders of students and the proportion of students by course. As it turns out, gender is a very important part of the student body composition.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/gender-count.png"></p>

<p>425,108 students have a gender on record, with 311,534 male students (73.3%) and 113,571 female students (26.7%). The fact that it&rsquo;s not even close to 50:50 is surprising.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/gender-age.png"></p>

<p>Age wise, there&rsquo;s not much difference between the genders. Female students are about a year older than male students on average.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/gender-completion.png"></p>

<p>Completion rate varies a bit more. Female students finish classes more frequently than male students.</p>

<p>Now to answer the age-old question: who get better grades: men or women?</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/gender-grade.png"></p>

<p>Ok, it&rsquo;s a tie.</p>

<h1>Country</h1>

<p>The home location of the students is, in my opinion, the most interesting student attribute in the data set. There are 24 different countries which were specified among 325,012 different students.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/country-count.png"></p>

<p>The United States, as one of the more technologically-savvy countries, accounts for nearly 1/3rd of all online students. India has a very strong presence as well due to  the combination of population and accessibility of materials. All the other countries have significantly fewer students.</p>

<p>Given such accessibility of online classes, students in some countries take more classes than others.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/country-more-than-one.png"></p>

<p>India&rsquo;s students also take the most classes on average.</p>

<p>The United States also has the oldest students on average among all the countries.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/country-age.png"></p>

<p>Completion rate by country, however, is very, very significant.</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/country-completion.png"></p>

<p>The top seven countries with the highest rate of completion are <strong>all European countries</strong>, with Spain and Poland in particular having a higher rate of completion than all the other countries, and nearly <strong>four times</strong> the completion rate of the United States.</p>

<p>But which country has the students which get the best grades?</p>

<p><img src="/img/online-class-charts/country-grade.png"></p>

<p>China is at the top with 86%, but otherwise the distribution is fairly flat with no outliers, and no economic or demographical pattern to the top or bottom of the ranks. It&rsquo;s possible that the more structured format of the classes make it harder to skew.</p>

<p>This Person-Course dataset has helped reveal many interesting insights about online classes at Harvard and MIT. Whether you measure performance by % of classes completed or a % score received at the end of the class, it&rsquo;s clear that age, country, and level of education all have a statistically significant impact on performance. The impact of the student&rsquo;s gender on performance, however, is more ambiguous and could use further analysis.</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data was processed using R and all charts were made using ggplot2.</em></li>
<li><em>You can view code necessary to reproduce these results  AND reproduce all the charts in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/online-class-charts">this GitHub repository</a>. Since MIT/Harvard prevent redistribution of the dataset, you&rsquo;ll have to <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7910/DVN/26147">download the dataset</a> yourself.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Interesting Percentages of Female Students in MIT and Harvard Online Courses]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/gender-course/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-04T10:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/07/gender-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the end of May, <a href="http://www.harvard.edu/">Harvard</a> and <a href="http://web.mit.edu/">MIT</a> jointly <a href="http://newsoffice.mit.edu/2014/mit-and-harvard-release-de-identified-learning-data-open-online-courses">released a dataset</a> containing statistics about their online courses in the Academic Year of 2013. This <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7910/DVN/26147">Person-Course De-Identified dataset</a> contains 476,532 students who have taken up to 13 unique courses from a variety of topics:</p>

<p><img src="/img/gender-course/mit-harvard-courses.png"></p>

<p>About half of the courses involve subjects in the humanities, while the other half involve computer science and electrical engineering.</p>

<p>One of the statistics I wanted to analyze was the gender ratio of students of online courses. In the data set, 425,105 students have a gender on record, with 311,534 male students (73.3%) and 113,571 female students (26.7%). This population proportion of female students is surprisingly low, especially since the male/female ratio is <a href="http://colleges.findthebest.com/q/1929/1270/What-is-the-male-to-female-ratio-at-Harvard-University">about 50:50</a> at MIT and Harvard themselves.</p>

<p>Therefore, I took a looked at the gender distribution of each of the 13 unique courses. Is the gender ratio similar across all classes, or is there a huge difference between classes?</p>

<p><img src="/img/gender-course/course-female.png"></p>

<p>Yeah, there&rsquo;s a huge difference.</p>

<p>The proportion of female students in each of Harvard and MIT&rsquo;s online courses range from <strong>5% to 49%</strong>.</p>

<p>The top half of the gender ratios are all well above the 26.7%  threshold. All six of these courses are in the humanities or in the life sciences. The bottom half of the gender ratio are all well below the 26.7% threshold. All seven are these courses are engineering or computer science courses with a strong focus on mathematics. (for clarification, the <a href="https://www.edx.org/course/mitx/mitx-2-01x-elements-structures-1759#.U7ZfKvldV8F">Elements of Structures</a> course at MIT is a physics course with linear algebra programming)</p>

<p>Is there a correlation? As it turns out, the reason that the average proportion of female students is so low is that both Harvard&rsquo;s Introduction to Computer Science I  (where 169,621 students took the class; about 40% of all students) and MIT&rsquo;s Introduction to CS/Programming (124,446 students total across both semesters) are so popular that the low percentage of women in those particular classes is drastically affecting the average.</p>

<p>The presence and interest of <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/eop/ostp/women">women in STEM fields</a> (science, technology, engineering, and mathematics) has been a topic of <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/stella-kasdagli/should-women-avoid-jobs-in-stem_b_5549016.html">controversy</a> for a very long time. However, the chart shows that indeed the percentage of women interested in STEM classes is measurably lower than other fields, and hopefully awareness of this issue will help cause changes in the future.</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data was processed using R and the chart was made using ggplot2. (w/ a few annotations added using a photo editor)</em></li>
<li><em>You can view code necessary to reproduce these results in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/gender-course">this GitHub repository</a>. Since MIT/Harvard prevent redistribution of the dataset, you&rsquo;ll have to <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7910/DVN/26147">download the dataset</a> yourself.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Statistical Analysis of 1.2 Million Amazon Reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/06/reviewing-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T08:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/06/reviewing-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When buying the latest products on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/">Amazon</a>, reading reviews is an important part of the purchasing process.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/ore.png"></p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amazon-review.png"></p>

<p>Customer reviews from customers who have actually purchased and used the product in question can give you more context to the product itself. Each reviewer rates the product from 1 to 5 stars, and provides a text summary of their experiences and opinions about the product. The ratings for each product are averaged together in order to get an overall product rating.</p>

<p>The number of reviews on Amazon has grown over the years.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-basic-time-count.png"></p>

<p>But how do people write reviews? What types of ratings do reviewers give? How many of these reviews are considered helpful?</p>

<p>Stanford researchers Julian McAuley and Jure Leskovec collected <a href="https://snap.stanford.edu/data/web-Amazon.html">all Amazon reviews </a>from the service&rsquo;s online debut in 1995 to 2013. Analyzing the dataset of 1.2 million Amazon reviews of products in the Electronics section, I found some interesting statistical trends; some are intuitive and obvious, but others give insight to how Amazon&rsquo;s review system actually works.</p>

<h1>Describing the Data</h1>

<p>First, let&rsquo;s see how the user ratings are distributed among the reviews.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-basic-score.png"></p>

<p>More than half of the reviews give a 5-star rating. Aside from perfect reviews, most reviewers give 4-star or 1-star ratings, with <em>very</em> few giving 2-stars or 3-stars relatively.</p>

<p>As as result, the statistical average for all review ratings is on the high-end of the scale at about <strong>3.90</strong>.  In fact, the average review rating for newly-written reviews has varied from 3.4 to 4.2 over time.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-basic-time-rating.png"></p>

<p>Another metric used to measure reviews is review helpfulness. Other Amazon reviewers can rate a particular review as &ldquo;helpful&rdquo; or &ldquo;not helpful.&rdquo; A &ldquo;review helpfulness&rdquo; statistic can be calculated by taking the number of &ldquo;is-helpful&rdquo; indicators divided by the total number of is-helpful/is-not-helpful indicators (in the example at the beginning of the article, 639/665 people found the review helpful, so the helpfulness rating would be 96%). This gives an indication of review quality to a prospective buyer. Only 10% of the reviews had atleast 10 is-helpful/is-not-helpful data points, and of those reviews, the vast majority of the reviews had perfect helpfulness scores.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-basic-helpful.png"></p>

<p>That would make sense; if you&rsquo;re writing a review (especially a 5 star review), you&rsquo;re writing with the intent to help other prospective buyers.</p>

<p>Another consideration is review length. Do reviews frequently write essays, or do reviews typically write a single paragraph?</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-basic-length.png"></p>

<p>Most reviews are 100-150 characters, but the average amount of characters in a review is about <strong>582</strong> (there are some outlier reviews with 30,000+ characters!). Assuming that the average amount of characters in a paragraph <a href="http://wiki.answers.com/Q/How_many_characters_does_the_average_paragraph_have">is 352</a>, reviewers typically write about half a paragraph. Interestingly, reviews are rarely less than a sentence. (the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/community-help/customer-reviews-guidelines">Review Guidelines</a> suggest a minimum of 20 words in a review, so this discrepancy could be attributed to moderator removal of short, one-liner reviews)</p>

<h1>Particularizing the Products</h1>

<p>The 1.2 million reviews in the Electronics data set address about 82,003 distinct products. However, most of those entries represent different SKUs of the same product (e.g. different colors of headphones). Of those products, only 30,577 products have pricing information which identify them as the source product.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-product-price.png"></p>

<p>Over 2/3rds of Amazon Electronics are priced between $0 and $50, which makes sense as popular electronics such as television remotes and phone cases are not extremely expensive. However, there&rsquo;s no statistical correlation between the price of a product and the number of reviews it receives.</p>

<p>For the overall rating of a particular product, which is the average rating of all reviews for that product, the ratings are no longer limited to discrete numbers between 1 and 5, and can take decimal values between those numbers as well. The distribution of product ratings is similar to the distribution of review ratings.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-product-rating.png"></p>

<p>Again, the perfect rating of 5 is most popular for products. This distribution resembles the distribution of scores of all reviews for the discrete rating values, but this view reveals local maxima at the midpoint between each discrete value. (i.e. 3-and-a-half stars and 4-and-a-half stars are surprisingly common ratings)</p>

<p>What happens when you plot product rating and product price together?</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-product-score-price.png"></p>

<p>The most expensive products have 4-star and 5-star overall ratings, but not 1-star and 2-star ratings. However, the correlation is very weak. (r = 0.04)</p>

<p>In contrast, the relationship between product price and the average <em>length</em> of reviews for the product is surprising.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-product-price-length.png"></p>

<p>This relationship is logarithmic with a relatively good correlation (r = 0.29), and it shows that reviewers put more time and effort into reviewing products which are worth more.</p>

<h1>Reviewing the Reviewers</h1>

<p>As you might expect, most people leave only 1 or 2 reviews on Amazon, but some have left <em>hundreds</em> of reviews. Out of 1.2 Million reviews, there are 510,434 distinct reviewers.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-count.png"></p>

<p>Over 80% of the reviewers of Amazon electronics left only 1 review. Analyzing reviewers who have left only 1 review is not helpful statistically, so for the rest of the analysis, only reviews who have made 5 or more reviews (which have received atleast 1 is-helpful/is-not-helpful indicator) will be considered. This makes it much easier to get the overall profile of a reviewer. 11,676 reviewers fit this criteria.</p>

<p>Do repeat Amazon users tend to give 5-star reviews?</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-score.png"></p>

<p>Distribution of review ratings when averaged across is similar to the other distributions of review ratings. However, this distribution is less skewed toward 5-stars and is more uniform between 4-stars and 5-stars.</p>

<p>What about the average helpfulness of the reviews written by a single reviewer? If a reviewer has enjoyed Amazon enough such that they make 5 or more reviews, chances are that their reviews are high quality.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-helpfulness.png"></p>

<p>Again, the data is slightly skewed. 8% of the reviewers have perfect helpfulness scores on all their reviews, and the average helpfulness score for all repeat reviews is 80%. Interestingly, a few repeat reviewers have average helpfulness scores of 0.</p>

<p>If you plot <em>both</em> average score and average helpfulness in a single chart, the picture becomes much more clear:</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-count-score.png"></p>

<p>As the chart shows, there&rsquo;s a good positive correlation (r = 0.27) between rating and helpfulness, with a discernible cluster at the top. However, I don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s a causal relationship. Reviewers who give a product a 4 &ndash; 5 star rating are more passionate about the product and likely to write better reviews than someone who writes a 1 &ndash; 2 star &ldquo;this product sucks and you suck too!&rdquo; review.</p>

<p>Another interesting bivariate relationship is the relationship between the helpfulness of a review and the length of a review). Stereotypically, you might think that longer reviews are more helpful reviews. And in the case of Amazon&rsquo;s Electronics reviews, you&rsquo;d be correct.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-reviewer-helpful-length.png"></p>

<p>Again, there&rsquo;s a good positive correlation (r = 0.26) between average helpfulness and average length, which the trend line supports. (the dip at the end is caused by the high amount of low-character reviews). All the longer reviews have high helpfulness; there are very, very few unhelpful reviews that are also long.</p>

<h1>Completing the Conclusion</h1>

<p>The reviews on Amazon&rsquo;s Electronics products very frequently rate the product 4 or 5 stars, and such reviews are almost always considered helpful. 1-stars are used to signify disapproval, and 2-star and 3-stars reviews have no significant impact at all. If that&rsquo;s the case, then what&rsquo;s the point of having a 5 star ranking system at all if the vast majority of reviewers favor the product? Would Amazon benefit if they made review ratings a binary like/dislike?</p>

<p>Having a 5-star system can allow the prospective customer to make more informed comparisons between two products: a customer may be more likely to buy a product that&rsquo;s rated 4.2 stars than a product that is rated 3.8 stars, which is a subtlety that can&rsquo;t easily be emulated with a like/dislike system. Likewise, if products are truly bad, the propensity toward 5-star reviews can help obfuscate the low quality of the product when a like/dislike system would make the low quality more apparent.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, only Amazon has the data that would answer all these questions.</p>

<p>Of course, there are many other secrets to be uncovered from Amazon reviews. The Stanford professors who collected the initial data used <a href="http://i.stanford.edu/~julian/pdfs/recsys13.pdf">machine learning techniques on the review text</a> to predict the rating given by a review from just the review text itself. Other potential topics for analysis are comparisons between <em>types</em> of Electronics (e.g. MP3 players, headphones) or using natural language processing to determine the common syntax in reviews.</p>

<p><img src="/img/amazon/amzn-word-review-start.png"></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a topic for another blog post. :)</p>

<hr />

<ul>
<li><em>Data analysis was performed using R, and all charts were made using ggplot2.</em></li>
<li><em>You can download a ZIP file containing CSVs of the time series, the aggregate product data, and the anonymized aggregate reviewer data <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/amazon_data.zip">here</a>.</em></li>
<li><em>No, I have no relation to &ldquo;<a href="http://www.amazon.com/review/R1KHEP16MXXWCN/ref=cm_cr_rdp_perm?ie=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B000796XXM">M. Wolff</a>&rdquo;.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
