<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Data | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-18T08:10:10-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Many #nofilter Instagram Photos Actually Have No Filter?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/the-filter-truth/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/02/the-filter-truth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most <a href="http://instagram.com/">Instagram</a> photos have filters applied to make them look more retro/cool. Instagram users are also able to apply tags to a photo to help categorize and promote them to the Instagram community. One such tag, #nofilter, is intended to emphasize such natural beauty that no filter is necessary to enhance the image. (or the photographer is just too lazy to decide on a filter)</p>

<p>But how many #nofilter images actually <em>have</em> no filter?</p>

<p><img src="/img/instagram_selfie.gif"></p>

<p>As it turns not, not all of them.</p>

<p>After retrieving about 50,000 images through the Instagram API (code <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/get-data-from-photos-from-instagram-tags">available on GitHub</a>), here is the breakdown of filters on #nofilter-tagged Instagram images:</p>

<p><img src="/img/nofilter.png"></p>

<p>Only 83% of #nofilter images have no filter?! You had one job, Instagram! :(</p>

<hr />

<p><em>The actual reason that this is happening is because Instagram rewards #tagspamming. More on that in a future blog post.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Thoughtful Analysis of the Most Poorly-Designed Chart Ever]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2014/01/more-language-more-problems/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-20T08:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2014/01/more-language-more-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I was surfing Reddit and came across an <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ProgrammerHumor/comments/1ur3ny/unnecessary_graph_of_most_desired_skills_in_2013/">interesting infographic</a> within the <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ProgrammerHumor/">ProgrammerHumor subreddit</a>. The infographic, as compiled by tech blog <a href="http://readwrite.com/">ReadWrite</a>, depicts the Top 10 Most In-Demand Developer Skills of 2013, as compiled by <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/">Stack Overflow</a> through keyword searches.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/infographic-1.jpg"></p>

<p>Take a look at the chart. What’s good and bad about it?</p>

<h1>The Good</h1>

<p>The data is properly cited.</p>

<h1>The Bad</h1>

<p><strong>EVERYTHING ELSE.</strong></p>

<p>What’s terrible about the graph? Let me count the ways:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Using discrete values in the X-Axis for a continuous measurement (i.e. the percentage). And not only that, discrete values with two significant figures, which make the X-Axis unusually cluttered.</p></li>
<li><p>The Y-Axis is Language. This implies that some programming languages are more language than others.  (<a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10152166149970450&amp;set=a.432190050449.225968.582270449&amp;type=1&amp;stream_ref=10">to be fair</a>, Java is more language than Android)</p></li>
<li><p>Not all entries on the chart are programming languages. (Android, for example, is an operating system.)</p></li>
<li><p>The 45-degree line in the chart implies that the relationship between language and %-of-searches is perfectly linear, where in reality the data has an upward-parabolic shape.</p></li>
<li><p>No relative proportions between the programming languages. We can&rsquo;t accurately see the increase in language Java has relative to Android just by looking at the graph.</p></li>
<li><p>Cannot easily associate a language with the given X-Axis value. The logos representing the programming language oscillate around the line, and it&rsquo;s hard to see at a glance which percentage corresponds to which language.</p></li>
</ul>


<h1>Fixing the Chart</h1>

<p>This isn’t one of those blog posts that make snarky criticism without offering any constructive input. (those will be posted next week). How can we make the chart somewhat logical?</p>

<p>The easiest way to improve the chart is to convert the chart from a line chart to a column chart. Here’s a column chart that keeps the intended impression of the original chart:</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-1.png"></p>

<p>A much bigger improvement, although unfortunately without the cool hand-drawn logos. The axes are no longer illogical and it’s easy to determine the relative impact of each language (e.g. Java is clearly, clearly at the top). However, the large amount of text can clutter the bars, and it can be difficult to correlate the raw percentage with the scale at a glance.</p>

<p>Another option is to rotate the chart and use bars instead of columns:</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-2.png"></p>

<p>This fixes the text issue by giving more room for text with most of the factors, but the Java text clips outside the chart. The correlation issue between language and percent value persists.</p>

<p>A best-of-both-worlds approach is to display the language on the Y-Axis and the raw percent value on the corresponding bar itself, allowing us to forgo the percent metric axis entirely.</p>

<p><img src="/img/dev-graph-3.png"></p>

<p>There we go. Minimalist, fixes both the text and correlation issues, and gets the point across effectively.</p>

<p>All of these charts were created using R and ggplot2, and you can download the R code in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/developer-graphs">this GitHub repository</a>. I wish the <a href="http://readwrite.com/2014/01/08/in-demand-tech-skills-of-2013-java">orginal ReadWrite article</a> used a chart like the last one and…</p>

<p>Wait, they changed the infographic?</p>

<p><img src="/img/infographic-2.jpg"></p>

<p>Hey, they fixed the chart, and it’s using a similar design as mine! What a crazy random happenstance!</p>

<p>The article was appended with an update:</p>

<blockquote><p>An earlier version of the infographic in this story presented the StackOverflow data in a confusing and conceptually problematic fashion. It has been updated.</p></blockquote>

<p>&ldquo;Problematic&rdquo; is the world&rsquo;s biggest understatement.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Probabilistically Generating GitHub Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/innovation-rng/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-29T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/innovation-rng</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Grant Slatton made an amusing post on Hacker News yesterday titled &ldquo;<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6815282">Show HN: Probabilistically Generating HN Post Titles</a>&rdquo;. By using the statistical principle of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain">Markov chains</a>, Slatton was able to <a href="http://grantslatton.com/hngen/">generate eerily-realistic Hacker News headlines</a> such as &ldquo;Facebook detects if you are not a pilot&rdquo; and &ldquo;The No. 1 Habit of Highly Effective Mediocre Entrepreneurs.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Could Markov chains be applied to any other data sets for hilarious effect? By using Slatton&rsquo;s <a href="https://gist.github.com/grantslatton/7694811">Python implementation of Markov chains</a> plus 300,000 descriptions of public GitHub repositories retrieved from their API, I discovered that statistical randomness can indeed create funny innovation.</p>

<p><img src="/img/github-wordcloud-mac.png"></p>

<p>You can download a list of 1,000 Markov chain-generated projects <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/github_markov.txt">here</a>. Here are a few interesting ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>MaNGOS is a free, Open Source implementation of a tag at relatively random intervals.</li>
<li>A Warhammer 40k simulator to teach myself both OpenGL and Clojure</li>
<li>Perl interface to Git repositories via Ruby.</li>
<li>A windows live messenger network client written in Erlang</li>
<li>Rails plugin which allows to talk anonymously and use tripcodes if you want.</li>
<li>A Firebug extension for displaying the latest from Hacker News</li>
<li>Sinatra-inspired JavaScript node.js web development framework for lua. Inspired by rspec</li>
<li>Inverted Index on top of Tornado</li>
<li>Android LED interface library for various wave propagation techniques.</li>
<li>CatchAPI is a Java API to remove the need for boring project setup.</li>
<li>Adds basic social networking capabilities to your lighting system based on the concept of the Working with Rails</li>
<li>Brute force your OpenERP data integration with flatfiles</li>
<li>Culerity integrates Cucumber and Celerity in order to shutdown the computer.</li>
<li>Parses ANSI color codes and converts them to iphone compatible mp4s using HandBrake</li>
<li>A simple OFX (Open Financial Exchange) parser built on top of WordPress. Rolopress core theme</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>The code used to get the project descriptions from the GitHub API is available in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/get-github-repo-descriptions">this GitHub repository</a>, and you can download the ~300k repo descriptions <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/github_repo_desc.zip">here</a>. [5MB .zip]</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reddit is Growing Slowly, but Surely]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-18T07:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reddit has certainty received more attention in the mainstream media with its involvement in such events as the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/business/media/bombings-trip-up-reddit-in-its-turn-in-spotlight.html?_r=0">Boston Marathon Bombings</a> and <a href="hhttp://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/z1c9z/i_am_barack_obama_president_of_the_united_states/">President Obama&rsquo;s AMA</a>. But has this publicity led to increase in overall activity on the site?</p>

<p>I analyzed the daily number of submissions from over two years, August 6th, 2011 to September 25, 2013 (41 million submissions total), to see which events, if any, have affected Reddit&rsquo;s growth rate. As it turns out, Reddit grows by itself.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/reddit_daily-mac.png"></p>

<p>Reddit&rsquo;s growth over the past two years has been almost entirely <strong>linear</strong>, with no notable acceleration in submission activity at any point in time.</p>

<p>Running a linear regression on daily number of submissions vs. number of days since the first date (8/6/11) reveals that the expected increase in number of submissions each successive day on average is <strong>66.48 submissions</strong>  (+1,948 submissions each successive month, +24,259 submissions each successive year)</p>

<p>This growth rate alone explains <strong>86.83%</strong> of the variation in number of submissions, indicating that external factors such as media publicity explain the remaining 13% of the variation.</p>

<p>From a business perspective, it&rsquo;s impressive that Reddit still continues to grow for being such a mature internet business, but prospective investors for a rumored <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/06/reddit-rumored-to-be-raising-money-at-a-400-million-valuation/">fundraising at a $400 Million valuation</a> might be weary that Reddit&rsquo;s growth is only linear, in contrast to the <strong>exponential</strong> growth of other startups such as Snapchat. (In fairness, submission activity may not necessarily correlate with revenue-driving content consumption activity)</p>

<p>A couple stray observations:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>On January 18th, 2012, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the minimum among the two-year period due to Reddit&rsquo;s participation in the Internet blackout in protest of SOPA. (Reddit&rsquo;s blackout was only from 8AM to 8PM EST, which is why there are a nonzero number of submissions for that day).</p></li>
<li><p>On April 1st, 2013, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the maximum among the two-year period due to April Fool&rsquo;s Day, and the numerous amount of submissions for <em>X</em> brand/website&rsquo;s well-timed joke. However, I&rsquo;m not entirely sure why there&rsquo;s a spike for April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2013, but not April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2012.</p></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data used to create the time-series chart at <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGZ2Zkk1MGF3SjZxdC1sRzV5SW9zRWc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Subreddits on Reddit are the Largest?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/subreddit-size/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T07:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/subreddit-size</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit&rsquo;s</a> subreddits cover, quite literally, an infinite amount of different topics. But which of its subreddits are the biggest?</p>

<p>Sure, Reddit is known for subreddits such as /r/pics and /r/aww, but in actuality, many of the lesser-known subreddits are much bigger than you think.</p>

<p>By tabulating the data of 37,561,369 total sitewide Link submissions, from 12/18/2011 to 9/26/2013, I created a tree map of the Top 100 subreddits by the number of Link submissions to that subreddit.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/subreddit-treemap.png" title="" ></p>

<p>In the tree map, the size of the rectangle and the saturation of the blue color indicate the relative size of the subreddit.</p>

<p>Unsurprisingly, the <a href="http://blog.reddit.com/2013/07/new-default-subreddits-omgomgomg.html">default subreddits</a>, which all new users are subscribed to, are ranked mostly at the top. However, subreddits such as /r/POLITICO, /r/leagueoflegends, and /r/trees are higher (no pun intended) than most of the default subreddits.</p>

<p>And then you have the meta subreddits such as /r/ModerationLog and /r/reportthespammers, showing that people spend a considerable amount of time talking about Reddit itself.</p>

<p>Gaming has a very significant presence as well, with /r/Minecraft, /r/DotA2, and /r/tf2. (notably for the latter two, the trading subreddits for the respective games have significantly more link submissions than the subreddits themselves.)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth nothing that these Top 100 subreddits only account for <strong>46.3% of all Reddit link submissions</strong>. Even the Top 500 subreddits only account for 66.2% of all Reddit submissions. The density of link submissions clearly follows a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_tail">long-tail</a> distribution, where most of the content is centralized from the top subreddits. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to see if Reddit is able to utilize that treasure trove of links in the future.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data for the Top 500 subreddits in  <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGQzd0dIQkk1aXRRRkxEY3g0ZmQtWGc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>, and you can see the code use to create the tree map in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/treemap-of-reddit-top-subreddits">this GitHub repository</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
