<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Data | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-29T08:38:32-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Probabilistically Generating GitHub Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/innovation-rng/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-29T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/innovation-rng</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Grant Slatton made an amusing post on Hacker News yesterday titled &ldquo;<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6815282">Show HN: Probabilistically Generating HN Post Titles</a>&rdquo;. By using the statistical principle of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain">Markov chains</a>, Slatton was able to <a href="http://grantslatton.com/hngen/">generate eerily-realistic Hacker News headlines</a> such as &ldquo;Facebook detects if you are not a pilot&rdquo; and &ldquo;The No. 1 Habit of Highly Effective Mediocre Entrepreneurs.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Could Markov chains be applied to any other data sets for hilarious effect? By using Slatton&rsquo;s <a href="https://gist.github.com/grantslatton/7694811">Python implementation of Markov chains</a> plus 300,000 descriptions of public GitHub repositories retrieved from their API, I discovered that statistical randomness can indeed create funny innovation.</p>

<p><img src="/img/github-wordcloud-mac.png"></p>

<p>You can download a list of 1,000 Markov chain-generated projects <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/github_markov.txt">here</a>. Here are a few interesting ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>MaNGOS is a free, Open Source implementation of a tag at relatively random intervals.</li>
<li>A Warhammer 40k simulator to teach myself both OpenGL and Clojure</li>
<li>Perl interface to Git repositories via Ruby.</li>
<li>A windows live messenger network client written in Erlang</li>
<li>Rails plugin which allows to talk anonymously and use tripcodes if you want.</li>
<li>A Firebug extension for displaying the latest from Hacker News</li>
<li>Sinatra-inspired JavaScript node.js web development framework for lua. Inspired by rspec</li>
<li>Inverted Index on top of Tornado</li>
<li>Android LED interface library for various wave propagation techniques.</li>
<li>CatchAPI is a Java API to remove the need for boring project setup.</li>
<li>Adds basic social networking capabilities to your lighting system based on the concept of the Working with Rails</li>
<li>Brute force your OpenERP data integration with flatfiles</li>
<li>Culerity integrates Cucumber and Celerity in order to shutdown the computer.</li>
<li>Parses ANSI color codes and converts them to iphone compatible mp4s using HandBrake</li>
<li>A simple OFX (Open Financial Exchange) parser built on top of WordPress. Rolopress core theme</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>The code used to get the project descriptions from the GitHub API is available in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/get-github-repo-descriptions">this GitHub repository</a>, and you can download the ~300k repo descriptions <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/2017402/github_repo_desc.zip">here</a>. [5MB .zip]</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reddit is Growing Slowly, but Surely]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-18T07:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/daily-reddit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reddit has certainty received more attention in the mainstream media with its involvement in such events as the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/business/media/bombings-trip-up-reddit-in-its-turn-in-spotlight.html?_r=0">Boston Marathon Bombings</a> and <a href="hhttp://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/z1c9z/i_am_barack_obama_president_of_the_united_states/">President Obama&rsquo;s AMA</a>. But has this publicity led to increase in overall activity on the site?</p>

<p>I analyzed the daily number of submissions from over two years, August 6th, 2011 to September 25, 2013 (41 million submissions total), to see which events, if any, have affected Reddit&rsquo;s growth rate. As it turns out, Reddit grows by itself.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/reddit_daily-mac.png"></p>

<p>Reddit&rsquo;s growth over the past two years has been almost entirely <strong>linear</strong>, with no notable acceleration in submission activity at any point in time.</p>

<p>Running a linear regression on daily number of submissions vs. number of days since the first date (8/6/11) reveals that the expected increase in number of submissions each successive day on average is <strong>66.48 submissions</strong>  (+1,948 submissions each successive month, +24,259 submissions each successive year)</p>

<p>This growth rate alone explains <strong>86.83%</strong> of the variation in number of submissions, indicating that external factors such as media publicity explain the remaining 13% of the variation.</p>

<p>From a business perspective, it&rsquo;s impressive that Reddit still continues to grow for being such a mature internet business, but prospective investors for a rumored <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/06/reddit-rumored-to-be-raising-money-at-a-400-million-valuation/">fundraising at a $400 Million valuation</a> might be weary that Reddit&rsquo;s growth is only linear, in contrast to the <strong>exponential</strong> growth of other startups such as Snapchat. (In fairness, submission activity may not necessarily correlate with revenue-driving content consumption activity)</p>

<p>A couple stray observations:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>On January 18th, 2012, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the minimum among the two-year period due to Reddit&rsquo;s participation in the Internet blackout in protest of SOPA. (Reddit&rsquo;s blackout was only from 8AM to 8PM EST, which is why there are a nonzero number of submissions for that day).</p></li>
<li><p>On April 1st, 2013, the daily number of Reddit submissions hit the maximum among the two-year period due to April Fool&rsquo;s Day, and the numerous amount of submissions for <em>X</em> brand/website&rsquo;s well-timed joke. However, I&rsquo;m not entirely sure why there&rsquo;s a spike for April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2013, but not April Fool&rsquo;s Day in 2012.</p></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data used to create the time-series chart at <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGZ2Zkk1MGF3SjZxdC1sRzV5SW9zRWc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Subreddits on Reddit are the Largest?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/subreddit-size/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T07:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/11/subreddit-size</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit&rsquo;s</a> subreddits cover, quite literally, an infinite amount of different topics. But which of its subreddits are the biggest?</p>

<p>Sure, Reddit is known for subreddits such as /r/pics and /r/aww, but in actuality, many of the lesser-known subreddits are much bigger than you think.</p>

<p>By tabulating the data of 37,561,369 total sitewide Link submissions, from 12/18/2011 to 9/26/2013, I created a tree map of the Top 100 subreddits by the number of Link submissions to that subreddit.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/subreddit-treemap.png" title="" ></p>

<p>In the tree map, the size of the rectangle and the saturation of the blue color indicate the relative size of the subreddit.</p>

<p>Unsurprisingly, the <a href="http://blog.reddit.com/2013/07/new-default-subreddits-omgomgomg.html">default subreddits</a>, which all new users are subscribed to, are ranked mostly at the top. However, subreddits such as /r/POLITICO, /r/leagueoflegends, and /r/trees are higher (no pun intended) than most of the default subreddits.</p>

<p>And then you have the meta subreddits such as /r/ModerationLog and /r/reportthespammers, showing that people spend a considerable amount of time talking about Reddit itself.</p>

<p>Gaming has a very significant presence as well, with /r/Minecraft, /r/DotA2, and /r/tf2. (notably for the latter two, the trading subreddits for the respective games have significantly more link submissions than the subreddits themselves.)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth nothing that these Top 100 subreddits only account for <strong>46.3% of all Reddit link submissions</strong>. Even the Top 500 subreddits only account for 66.2% of all Reddit submissions. The density of link submissions clearly follows a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_tail">long-tail</a> distribution, where most of the content is centralized from the top subreddits. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to see if Reddit is able to utilize that treasure trove of links in the future.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>You can access the data for the Top 500 subreddits in  <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGQzd0dIQkk1aXRRRkxEY3g0ZmQtWGc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a>, and you can see the code use to create the tree map in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/treemap-of-reddit-top-subreddits">this GitHub repository</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do startups with short names containing few vowels raise more money?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/10/wrds-and-vwls/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-14T07:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/10/wrds-and-vwls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One reason startups use crazy and bizarre names like <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">NegaCycl</a> and <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/">Filtrzzz</a> is to ensure that their name is unique, making it easier to acquire the .com domain name and Twitter handle for their startup. Another reason is to make their startup sound <em>kewl</em> and theoretically make the name more memorable in the minds of users and potential investors.</p>

<p>Dakwak, Wibki, Zeef, Funifi. These aren&rsquo;t random words: these are funded startups which were featured at <a href="http://startupalley.techcrunch.com/">TechCrunch Disrupt Startup Alley 2013</a>. And then you have startups such as Lyft, SCVNGR, and Fastly, which have all raised <em>tens of millions of dollars</em> in venture capital.</p>

<p>Do startups with these short, low-vowel names actually raise more money than startups with traditional names?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First, let&rsquo;s take a look at the association between the length of words in the English language and the number of vowels that they contain:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/img/english-words.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>In the English language, the majority of the words have 8 letters, with 3 of those letters being vowels. (8,3) is also the center of the density distribution for the heat map, spreading outward.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s compare the vowel distribution of normal English words to the distribution of the names of startups that have successfully raised venture capital, in order to identify just how many funded startups have quirky names:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/img/count-startups.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>Wait, the two distributions are nearly identical! Both graphs are centered at about (8,3), radiating outward. This implies that the number of startups with uniquely-constructed names are outliers and not the typical names for startups.</p>

<p>But that doesn&rsquo;t answer the core question: sure, fewer funded startups have weird names relative to the amount of total funded startups, but do they raise more money on average than startups with typical names?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/img/mean-startups-fund.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>Nope.</p>

<p>There is no discernible pattern for the average amount raised, unlike with the previous two charts. For the vast majority of the possible combinations of name length and $ vowels, the range of capital raised is between $5M and $25M. There are higher values at the lower-end of the graph (low length, low vowels), but that can be attributed to the relatively low amount of startup data for those combinations to smooth out the average. (e.g. the $78M spike at 3 length, 2 vowels is due to the always-lovely <a href="http://www.crunchbase.com/company/aol">AOL</a> and a <a href="http://googlepress.blogspot.com/2005/12/time-warners-aol-and-google-to-expand_20.html">$1 billion investment from Google</a>, and there are only 15 other startups in the segment.)</p>

<p>In fact, the statistical correlation between name length and funding, number of vowels and funding, and ratio of length to vowels and funding, are all effectively <strong>zero</strong>.</p>

<p>Sure, quirky startup names may make it easier to find a domain name, but it won&rsquo;t necessarily give an edge in the investment process.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Data for English words from <a href="http://wordlist.sourceforge.net/">Kevin&rsquo;s Word List Page</a>, and data for the startup names/funding from <a href="http://info.crunchbase.com/about/crunchbase-data-exports/">CrunchBase&rsquo;s September Data Export</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[1 in 3 Links Submitted To Reddit Go To Imgur Or YouTube]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/09/reddit-imgur-youtube/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-29T10:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/09/reddit-imgur-youtube</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;ve been on <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a>, you may have noticed that many link submissions go to &ldquo;imgur.com&rdquo;. <a href="http://imgur.com/">Imgur</a>, an image hosting service that launched on Reddit a few years ago and has seen outstanding growth ever since, even <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2013/09/26/imgur-traffic-milestone-100m-uniques/">surpassing Reddit itself</a>.</p>

<p>But how many of Reddit&rsquo;s many, many links are actually links to Imgur? As it turns out, Imgur, along with YouTube, account for <em>32%</em> of the links submitted to Reddit.</p>

<p>Using Reddit&rsquo;s API, I have downloaded about 5 million link submissions from Reddit, accounting for nearly two months of activity from July 22nd to September 26th. I complied a list of the most-frequent link destination domains for the links submitted anywhere on Reddit. The results were interesting.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/links722_926.png"></p>

<p>The imgur domains (i.imgur.com and imgur.com) account for <strong>23.7%</strong> of all links submitted to Reddit, and the YouTube domains (youtube.com and youtu.be) account for <strong>8.2%</strong> of all links.</p>

<p>Two websites account for <strong>32%</strong> of all links submitted to Reddit (i.e. 1 in every 3 submitted links go to Imgur or YouTube), and no other website is remotely close. Not the meme sites, not the music sites, not the news sites, not the <em>porn</em> sites: Reddit is images and video.</p>

<p>But <em>where</em> on Reddit are the Imgur and YouTube links most prominent?</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a chart of the top subreddits, by percentage of all  Imgur links submitted on Reddit:</p>

<p><img src="/img/imgur722_926.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting to note how the <em>funny</em> subreddit has more Imgur links than the <em>pics</em> subreddit.</p>

<p>For YouTube, and the percentage of all YouTube links submitted on Reddit by subreddit:</p>

<p><img src="/img/youtube722_926.png"></p>

<p><em>Videos</em> wins as you might expect, but <em>Music</em> is in second place. Along with <em>listentothis</em>,
<em>Metal</em>, and <em>hiphopheads</em>, YouTube is the de facto website for <em>music</em> as well as video. Gaming is also  very popular with YouTube links, with <em>gaming</em>, <em>leagueoflegends</em>, and <em>Minecraft</em>.</p>

<p>Images and video are the backbone of Reddit, and both Imgur and YouTube are the primary sources. Although, there appears to be a nontrivial demand for pure music websites such as <a href="https://soundcloud.com/">SoundCloud</a> and gaming video websites such as <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/">Twitch.tv</a> &hellip;could there be another big success story in the making?</p>

<hr />

<p><em>The tabulated data used to create each of the three charts is located at <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGxoVGFyX19hV2paMk5lOFRvNXlkcnc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a> for your perusal.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
