<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Data | minimaxir | Max Woolf's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com//data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://minimaxir.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-14T06:55:09-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://minimaxir.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Max Woolf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do startups with short names containing few vowels raise more money?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/10/wrds-and-vwls/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-14T07:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/10/wrds-and-vwls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One reason startups use crazy and bizarre names like <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/totally-real-totally-serious/">NegaCycl</a> and <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/12/powerpoint-promo-party/">Filtrzzz</a> is to ensure that their name is unique, making it easier to acquire the .com domain name and Twitter handle for their startup. Another reason is to make their startup sound <em>kewl</em> and theoretically make the name more memorable in the minds of users and potential investors.</p>

<p>Dakwak, Wibki, Zeef, Funifi. These aren&rsquo;t random words: these are funded startups which were featured at <a href="http://startupalley.techcrunch.com/">TechCrunch Disrupt Startup Alley 2013</a>. And then you have startups such as Lyft, SCVNGR, and Fastly, which have all raised <em>tens of millions of dollars</em> in venture capital.</p>

<p>Do startups with these short, low-vowel names actually raise more money than startups with traditional names?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First, let&rsquo;s take a look at the association between the length of words in the English language and the number of vowels that they contain:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/img/english-words.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>In the English language, the majority of the words have 8 letters, with 3 of those letters being vowels. (8,3) is also the center of the density distribution for the heat map, spreading outward.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s compare the vowel distribution of normal English words to the distribution of the names of startups that have successfully raised venture capital, in order to identify just how many funded startups have quirky names:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/img/count-startups.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>Wait, the two distributions are nearly identical! Both graphs are centered at about (8,3), radiating outward. This implies that the number of startups with uniquely-constructed names are outliers and not the typical names for startups.</p>

<p>But that doesn&rsquo;t answer the core question: sure, fewer funded startups have weird names relative to the amount of total funded startups, but do they raise more money on average than startups with typical names?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/img/mean-startups-fund.png" width="600" height="600"></p>

<p>Nope.</p>

<p>There is no discernible pattern for the average amount raised, unlike with the previous two charts. For the vast majority of the possible combinations of name length and $ vowels, the range of capital raised is between $5M and $25M. There are higher values at the lower-end of the graph (low length, low vowels), but that can be attributed to the relatively low amount of startup data for those combinations to smooth out the average. (e.g. the $78M spike at 3 length, 2 vowels is due to the always-lovely <a href="http://www.crunchbase.com/company/aol">AOL</a> and a <a href="http://googlepress.blogspot.com/2005/12/time-warners-aol-and-google-to-expand_20.html">$1 billion investment from Google</a>, and there are only 15 other startups in the segment.)</p>

<p>In fact, the statistical correlation between name length and funding, number of vowels and funding, and ratio of length to vowels and funding, are all effectively <strong>zero</strong>.</p>

<p>Sure, quirky startup names may make it easier to find a domain name, but it won&rsquo;t necessarily give an edge in the investment process.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Data for English words from <a href="http://wordlist.sourceforge.net/">Kevin&rsquo;s Word List Page</a>, and data for the startup names/funding from <a href="http://info.crunchbase.com/about/crunchbase-data-exports/">CrunchBase&rsquo;s September Data Export</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[1 in 3 Links Submitted To Reddit Go To Imgur Or YouTube]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/09/reddit-imgur-youtube/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-29T10:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/09/reddit-imgur-youtube</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;ve been on <a href="http://www.reddit.com/">Reddit</a>, you may have noticed that many link submissions go to &ldquo;imgur.com&rdquo;. <a href="http://imgur.com/">Imgur</a>, an image hosting service that launched on Reddit a few years ago and has seen outstanding growth ever since, even <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2013/09/26/imgur-traffic-milestone-100m-uniques/">surpassing Reddit itself</a>.</p>

<p>But how many of Reddit&rsquo;s many, many links are actually links to Imgur? As it turns out, Imgur, along with YouTube, account for <em>32%</em> of the links submitted to Reddit.</p>

<p>Using Reddit&rsquo;s API, I have downloaded about 5 million link submissions from Reddit, accounting for nearly two months of activity from July 22nd to September 26th. I complied a list of the most-frequent link destination domains for the links submitted anywhere on Reddit. The results were interesting.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/img/links722_926.png"></p>

<p>The imgur domains (i.imgur.com and imgur.com) account for <strong>23.7%</strong> of all links submitted to Reddit, and the YouTube domains (youtube.com and youtu.be) account for <strong>8.2%</strong> of all links.</p>

<p>Two websites account for <strong>32%</strong> of all links submitted to Reddit (i.e. 1 in every 3 submitted links go to Imgur or YouTube), and no other website is remotely close. Not the meme sites, not the music sites, not the news sites, not the <em>porn</em> sites: Reddit is images and video.</p>

<p>But <em>where</em> on Reddit are the Imgur and YouTube links most prominent?</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a chart of the top subreddits, by percentage of all  Imgur links submitted on Reddit:</p>

<p><img src="/img/imgur722_926.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting to note how the <em>funny</em> subreddit has more Imgur links than the <em>pics</em> subreddit.</p>

<p>For YouTube, and the percentage of all YouTube links submitted on Reddit by subreddit:</p>

<p><img src="/img/youtube722_926.png"></p>

<p><em>Videos</em> wins as you might expect, but <em>Music</em> is in second place. Along with <em>listentothis</em>,
<em>Metal</em>, and <em>hiphopheads</em>, YouTube is the de facto website for <em>music</em> as well as video. Gaming is also  very popular with YouTube links, with <em>gaming</em>, <em>leagueoflegends</em>, and <em>Minecraft</em>.</p>

<p>Images and video are the backbone of Reddit, and both Imgur and YouTube are the primary sources. Although, there appears to be a nontrivial demand for pure music websites such as <a href="https://soundcloud.com/">SoundCloud</a> and gaming video websites such as <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/">Twitch.tv</a> &hellip;could there be another big success story in the making?</p>

<hr />

<p><em>The tabulated data used to create each of the three charts is located at <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddGxoVGFyX19hV2paMk5lOFRvNXlkcnc&amp;usp=sharing">this Google Spreadsheet</a> for your perusal.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Universities Produce the Most Successful Startup Founders?]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/alma-mater-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-20T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/07/alma-mater-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you read startup funding announcements on tech blogs frequently, you&rsquo;ve may have noticed that these startup founders have often attended prestigious universities. Founders who have graduated from Ivy League schools, such as Harvard, Yale and Princeton, unsurprisingly raise millions for their startups. Of course, top tier tech schools such as Stanford, MIT, and Carnegie Mellon foster a strong technical and entrepreneurial background: attributes which venture capitalists seek when investing in a startup founder. <em>(Disclosure: I&rsquo;m a Carnegie Mellon alumnus)</em></p>

<p>Do the tech universities produce more funded graduates than the Ivy League universities? Do the founders from Ivy League Universities receive more funding than those from the top tier tech universities?</p>

<p>Using TechCrunch&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.crunchbase.com/">CrunchBase</a> API, I obtained the data of about 2,500 startup founders in the United States who have created a startup which has received investment from venture capitalists.</p>

<p>With that data, I found some rather interesting trends.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Which universities produced the most amount of graduates who have received funding?</h1>

<p>Thousands of university graduates attempt to make a startup, but most will not succeed. Are the graduates of some universities more frequently successful?</p>

<p>Here are the Top 16 universities with the most number of successfully-funded graduates:</p>

<p><img src="/img/founder-colleges.png"></p>

<p>Stanford has the most amount of funded graduates, which is unsurprising as it&rsquo;s located in the Silicon Valley heart of venture capital.</p>

<p>Seven out of the eight Ivy League Universities (colored green on the chart) are present, but most of the Ivies are  in the middle of the chart. MIT and UC Berkeley each have nearly <em>double</em> the amount of successful graduates from Yale and Columbia.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth noting that Tel Aviv University, an Israeli university, ties Duke University at 21.</p>

<h1>Which university&rsquo;s graduates have cumulatively raised the most amount of total funding?</h1>

<p>Another way to measure success is through the success of the founders' subsequent startups and the amount of venture capital they have raised.</p>

<p>Here are the Top 8 universities whose graduates have received the most amount of funding:</p>

<p><img src="/img/sum-funding.png"></p>

<p>Harvard and Stanford graduates are very close in terms of total funding raised. However, there&rsquo;s a clear <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law">Power Law</a> in effect, as those two along with UC Berkeley, have  produced founders who&rsquo;ve generated much, much more venture funding than those of the other universities.</p>

<h1>Which university&rsquo;s graduates raise the most amount of money in their first round of funding on average?</h1>

<p>Startup founders with big, world changing ideas need lots of venture capital. Only the founders with <em>good</em> ideas will actually receive it.</p>

<p>Here are the average amount of first-round funding for the top 16 universities with the most number of successfully-funded graduates:</p>

<p><img src="/img/avg-first-raised.png"></p>

<p>Carnegie Mellon and Princeton, which had a relatively low number of funded founders and a relatively low number of total capital raised, instead have a <em>significantly</em> higher amount of average first funding. UCLA also placed. Perhaps the students from these three universities tend to have more ambitious startup ideas?</p>

<p>At first glance, Stanford and Harvard appear to be the kings of startups. They have the most amount of graduates, and the most amount of total venture capital raised. The tech blogs would surely consider that a success, but could the greater funding for CMU/Princeton lead to the creation of the next billion-dollar startup? We can only wait and see.</p>

<p><em>UPDATE: As pointed out by robotcookies on the <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6075862">corresponding Hacker News thread</a>, I missed UCLA in the first draft, which had 29 funded graduates. The charts have been updated.</em></p>

<hr />

<p>You are welcome to use the founder data from CrunchBase by <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjPFdCURhZvddEV1LUpaQUVsdmJYcERoM0FNU3lPcVE&amp;usp=sharing">viewing the data on Google Drive</a>, or by <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/3jz2wsr4d6fc4t6/founders_w_college.csv">downloading the raw CSV</a>.</p>

<p><em>Notes:</em></p>

<ul>
<li><em>University data was standardized to make analysis easier (e.g. for Carnegie Mellon, the founders who listed their institution as &ldquo;Carnegie Mellon University&rdquo;, &ldquo;Carnegie Mellon,&rdquo; and &ldquo;CMU,&rdquo; all had their institution changed to be &ldquo;CMU&rdquo;.)</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #1 measures unique founders, so it does not double-count a founder who has founded more than one  funded startup.</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #2 assumes equal contribution of each founder to the funding: if a startup has a total funding of $100,000 with 2 founders, the amount used for the chart will be $50,000 for each founder.</em></li>
<li><em>Chart #3 ignores startup data for the chart which has a Series B, Series C, or Series D listed as their first round on CrunchBase, or if the amount raised was not provided.</em></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Predicting the Number of Likes on a Facebook Status With Statistical Keyword Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2013/06/big-social-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What makes people click the Like button on Facebook Statuses? Does the status say something funny? Does it contain a cool link or a funny photo? Does the status actively engage its readers?</p>

<p>Needless to say, brands on Facebook want to know the answers to these questions. The more people that Like their statuses on their Facebook Pages, the more exposure they gain, and the more money they earn. Many, many companies have been created for the sole purpose of maximizing the number of Facebook Likes.</p>

<p>By 2013, most brands have realized that photo posts and statuses that ask a question <a href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/questions-equals-reponses/">will generate <em>much</em> higher numbers</a> of Likes. Personally, that&rsquo;s not why <em>I</em> like a given Facebook status: I Like statuses that contain new and exciting things that are relevant to my interests. The first thing I read in a status is the Message: if the message is boring and uninteresting, then there&rsquo;s no reason for me to Like the status needlessly.</p>

<p>Can the keywords and language in a Facebook Status predict the number of Likes the status receives?</p>

<p>Running multivariate regressions on keywords from thousands of Facebook statuses, I&rsquo;ve discovered that the language used in a status <em>does</em> help predict the number of Likes a status receives, and actually could help brands learn much more about their fans.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Setup</h1>

<p><img src="/img/rdataset.png"></p>

<p>In order to draw accurate conclusions from the analysis, large amounts of data are needed (and there&rsquo;s no such thing as too much data).</p>

<p>I decided to analyze the Facebook Pages of 3 extremely popular News sources: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cnn">CNN</a>, the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/nytimes">New York Times</a>, and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/bbcworldnews">BBC World News</a>. All three Pages have millions of fans, post the same types of Facebook statuses, and post statuses extremely frequently to Facebook (around 8-9 times a day). The statuses analyzed will be from June 1st 2012 to June 1st 2013, in order to both gather a large sample size (~3,000  statuses from each Page) and a ensure a consistent apples-to-apples comparison between the three sources.</p>

<p>The raw data, code, and a detailed technical explanation of the statistical techniques used to process the data can be found in <a href="https://github.com/minimaxir/facebook-keyword-regression-analysis">this GitHub repository</a>. (tl;dr, it&rsquo;s an optimized <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Least_squares">least squares</a> regression)</p>

<p><em>Can the keywords and language in a Facebook Status predict the number of Likes the status receives?</em> We&rsquo;re ready to test this hypothesis.</p>

<hr />

<h1>CNN</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="/img/cnn_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Bourdain        1962.98         0
NEWS            1272.64         0
Photo           1154.6          0
Barack          1002.45         0
City            851.82          0
Monday          705.42          0
Obama           632.2           0
United          578.77          0
Mitt            562.29          0.01
South           508.43          0.03
America         505.83          0.01
Watch           470.51          0
Boston          398.13          0.05
New             326.74          0.03
ET              -433.96         0
North           -467.05         0.02
Check           -503.5          0
Travel          -988.99         0.02
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for CNN are political keywords.</li>
<li><strong>NEWS</strong> (&ldquo;BREAKING NEWS&rdquo;) predicts more Likes than <strong>Photo</strong> (i.e. <a href="http://www.facebook.com/5550296508/posts/10151626042186509">Travel Photo of the Day</a>).</li>
<li><strong>Bourdain</strong> refers to Anthony Bourdain, who very recently began <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Bourdain:_Parts_Unknown">a food and travel show</a> on CNN. I assume that targets CNN&rsquo;s primary demographic.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Barack</strong> (Barack Obama) predicts more likes than just <strong>Obama</strong>.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Monday</strong> predicts more likes most other keywords. Garfield would be disappointed.</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>North</strong> (North Korea) predicts a <em>decrease</em> in Likes from the average. Is North Korea boring?</li>
<li>The presence of <strong>Check</strong> (&ldquo;Check this out!&rdquo;) also predicts a decrease in Likes from the average. This is interesting because this call-to-action is usually associated with the other keywords. Perhaps it&rsquo;s not necessary?</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h1>NYTimes</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="/img/nytimes_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Mills           1022.9          0
Democratic      496.32          0
Krugman         456.31          0
Senate          431.05          0
London          373.67          0.01
Oscar           367.64          0.01
Sandy           364.61          0
Olympics        339.15          0.01
Sunday          317             0
Clinton         314.64          0.02
You             247.07          0
Obama           237.98          0
Opinion         221             0
Michael         204.2           0.03
Credit          191.92          0.05
Tuesday         187.22          0.03
Times           178.69          0
See             160.12          0.01
Romney          157.66          0.04
Ed              140.86          0.01
Read            -101.23         0.05
Here            -182.72         0.04
Facebook        -187.75         0.02
Are             -216.3          0.01
While           -293.77         0.04
Quotation       -322.29         0.02
House           -362.1          0.01
Thanksgiving    -369.88         0.05
Convention      -448.34         0.01
Jersey          -505.98         0
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for NYTimes are political keywords and current events, such as Hurricane <strong>Sandy</strong> and the <strong>London</strong> <strong>Olympics</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Mills</strong> refers to Doug Mills, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/5281959998/posts/10150252479219999">photographer</a> for the New York Times. The power of photos!</li>
<li><strong>You</strong> and <strong>See</strong> are impactful call-to-action keywords, even though they don&rsquo;t ask any questions. (Interestingly, <strong>Are</strong>, which implicitly asks a question, predicts a decrease in Likes. Maybe people don&rsquo;t Like questions?)</li>
<li><strong>Clinton</strong> has a bigger impact than <strong>Obama</strong>.</li>
<li>No one likes <strong>Jersey</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h1>BBC World News</h1>

<p><img class="pull-right hidden-tablet" src="/img/bbcworldnews_Wordcloud.png"></p>

<pre><code>                +Likes          P-Val
Malala          488.1           0
Japan           186.32          0
Britain         167.25          0.01
That            155.01          0.01
AFP             154.97          0.02
Travel          153.41          0
Now             148.39          0.02
Would           146.45          0.03
Delhi           137.85          0.04
Let             134.93          0.03
Future          127.49          0.02
Barack          125.79          0.02
An              122.18          0.03
David           111.78          0.04
Do              111.13          0
Israel          101.31          0.04
Impact          87.94           0.05
South           78.62           0.03
It              62.7            0.01
The             55.7            0
US              -47.84          0.02
On              -86.22          0.04
BBC             -103.58         0
Sunday          -117.01         0.03
After           -122.38         0.05
Thursday        -143.91         0.03
Twitter         -144.55         0
City            -147.16         0.02
Hi              -149.85         0.03
BBCNewsUS       -150.48         0.03
House           -176.86         0.01
California      -187.57         0
</code></pre>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<ul>
<li>The most impactful keywords for BBC World News are keywords describing news around the world. Unlike CNN and NYTimes, there are very few impactful keywords related to domestic politics (such as Prime Minister <strong>David</strong> Cameron, and even <strong>Barack</strong> is more impactful than him.)</li>
<li><strong>Malala</strong> refers to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malala_Yousafzai">Malala Youdsfzai</a>, a Pakistani activist who survived an assassination attempt.</li>
<li>Implicit question keywords such as <strong>Let</strong>, <strong>Do</strong>, and <strong>Would</strong> are all very effective.</li>
<li>The simple salutation of <strong>Hi</strong> predicts a decrease in Likes. There&rsquo;s a British joke here somewhere.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p>The language used in Facebook Statuses can be very useful in identifying what words Fans like, and what words will be most useful in generating the most exposure. While my analysis can&rsquo;t predict the <em>exact</em> number of Likes a Status receives, and I likely <a href="http://xkcd.com/882/">broke a few rules of statistics</a> in the process of making this post, the impact of language and specific keywords on social media interaction is an endeavor worth pursuing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Does Asking Questions To Readers Increase Response Rate? - And Other TechCrunch Analyses]]></title>
    <link href="http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/questions-equals-reponses/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-07T21:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://minimaxir.com/2012/10/questions-equals-reponses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A long-standing trend in blogging is having the writer ask the readers what they think about your post and having the readers letting the writers know in the comments. Websites such as <a href="http://www.tvguide.com/">TVGuide</a> and <a href="http://mashable.com/">Mashable</a> have such requests in nearly <em>every</em> article. Reminding users to respond so frequently makes it seems insincere and deliberate, so I personally have been skeptical of the practice.</p>

<p>Recently, I&rsquo;ve noticed more and more brands on their Facebook posts asking their readers for their own opinions on news. Anecdotally, I&rsquo;ve also observed that those same posts have more comments than usual. This technique <strong>must</strong> increase the social response rate, I thought, otherwise media companies wouldn&rsquo;t do it.</p>

<p>Like any math nerd, I wasn&rsquo;t comfortable with simple circumstantial evidence. When I <a href="http://www.facebook.com/max.woolf/posts/10151223309670450">asked on Facebook</a> if there is any statistical data indicating that including a question to the community at the end of a blog post / Facebook post increases the response rate, TechCrunch writer and Facebook specialist Josh Constine responded and linked to<a href="http://www.facebook.com/notes/facebook-journalists/study-how-people-are-engaging-journalists-on-facebook-best-practices/245775148767840"> a Facebook report</a> stating that such posts have double the comments and significantly greater feedback.</p>

<p>I decided to put that to the test. I wrote a quick script in R that parses the Facebook page of a brand and extracts the number of likes for all of their posts, the number of comments on all posts, and whether or not each post contained a question. The brand I chose for my testing is none other than <a href="http://www.techcrunch.com/">TechCrunch</a>, because <a href="http://www.facebook.com/techcrunch">its Facebook page</a>, managed by the wonderful <a href="https://twitter.com/elinblesener">Elin Blesner</a>, has large sample sizes in terms of both unique postings and response rates on each post, ensuring that the analysis of the data is statistically significant. Additionally, having a<em>nother</em> perspective on TechCrunch to comment about certainly doesn&rsquo;t hurt either.</p>

<p>After collecting about 2,500 posts &ndash; 12 months of data &ndash; I analyzed the data conditional on whether or not the post was a question, among other things. The results surprised me.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>tl;dr: Asking a question to the readers in a Facebook post <em>does</em> increase the number of comments very significantly, but <em>decreases</em> the number of Likes!</strong></p>

<h2>How many Comments and Likes do TechCrunch posts receive?</h2>

<p>Since the data goes back a year, we can more easily detect seasonal trends in the data. First, let&rsquo;s see the real world numbers as a sanity check.</p>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb1.png" title="How many Comments and Likes do TechCrunch posts receive?" alt="It's much more than you may think." /></p>

<p>The number of Likes per month appears to be positively correlated with the number of comments, which is to be expected. Some months have significantly more activity than others; September 2012 had the most because of TechCrunch Disrupt SF. (interestingly, there wasn&rsquo;t such a spike in May 2012 with Disrupt NYC) The average number of likes/comments per post per month, as opposed to the sum, is a more consistent measurement, so we will be using that going forward.</p>

<h2>How many Comments and Likes do TechCrunch Facebook posts receive on average?</h2>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb2.png" title="How many Comments and Likes do TechCrunch posts receive on average?" alt="Triple-Digit Likes and double-digit Comments. Not too shabby." /></p>

<p>Overall average is 162 Likes and 30 Comments per post. The average number of Likes/Comments are consistent across the past year, with growth in the last few months. Nothing too surprising here. ## Does the time of day of a Facebook posting affect the number of Likes/Comments it receives?</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a fun measurement I decided to analyze. TechCrunch makes postings at all hours as it&rsquo;s a globally-targeted blog, but readers in the US may be asleep at the time. This could be a possible confounding variable (social activity may be correlated with geographic location), so it&rsquo;s best to see whether or not we can rule it out.</p>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb3.png" title="Does the time of day of a Facebook posting affect the number of Likes/Comments it receives?" alt="The spike in average comments at 4AM PST / 7AM EST is interesting. European workday?" /></p>

<p>As it turns out, time of day does <strong>not</strong> appear to have an effect on number of Likes/Comments received for TechCrunch!</p>

<h2>How many TechCrunch Facebook posts ask a question, relative to the ones that do not?</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the main question that began this entire investigation. Has the TechCrunch Facebook been writing posts that ask questions more frequently?</p>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb4.png" title="How many TechCrunch Facebook posts ask a question, relative to the ones that do not?" alt="TechCrunch-themed columns!" /></p>

<p>As it turns out, no, TechCrunch has asked the same proportion of questions on their Facebook page, as there is no change in trend. Overall average is 31.38% of TC&rsquo;s posts ask a question. (about a third of the posts)</p>

<h2>Does including a question to the community increase the number of Likes/Comments on the post?</h2>

<p>And here&rsquo;s the analysis of the main hypothesis. The results were quite surprising.</p>

<p><img src="/img/tcfb5.png" title="Does including a question to the community increase the number of Likes/Comments on the post?" alt="Now with more DROP SHADOWS!" /></p>

<p>The average amount of Likes for a post that asked a question is <em>lower</em> than a post that does not! (141 Likes for post that asks question, 172 for post that does not, a 18% decrease) That&rsquo;s unexpected!</p>

<p>For Comments, the average amount of Comments for a post that asked a question is significantly higher than a post that does not (45 Comments for a post that asks question, 23 comments for post that does not, a 97% increase). This is nearly double, which is what the Facebook report had stated.</p>

<p>What could explain this behavior? A quick theory is that Liking and Commenting on a brand post are mutually exclusive; asking a question in the post drives the user to comment, but not to Like the post, but since the user has already acknowledged the post socially, there&rsquo;s no need for the user to Like it. This follows my personal behavior on brands; if I comment, I usually do not like the post as it seems redundant.</p>

<p>Regardless, I will now admit that there are benefits to asking your users questions in your Facebook or blog posts. Although there appears to be a drop in Likes by asking users what their opinions are, the increase in comments more than counteracts it.</p>

<p>This data raises an interesting dilemma: let&rsquo;s say everyone catches on and <em>most</em> of the top brands start asking their users questions. It&rsquo;ll quickly become an cliche, as it is essentially a subliminal form of the infamous Facebook News Feed spam. Would that cause brands to stop asking questions? If so, how long would it take for the brands to switch back to asking their users questions?</p>

<p>Who knew that social media marketing involved game theory?</p>

<p>-Max</p>

<p><em>(Since all the data is public anyways, <a href="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/2017402/TechCrunch%20Facebook%20Data%20Analysis.xlsx">I am releasing my data and graphs</a> for your perusal. If you decide to use it and find something else interesting, please let me know!)</em></p>

<p>EDIT: One more.</p>

<h2>Do photo posts have greater response rates than posts without photos?</h2>

<p><img src="/img/tc-graph.png" alt="14" /></p>

<p>Yep. Not too surprising. It&rsquo;s why Facebook bought Instagram! (although I&rsquo;m curious what happened in April&hellip;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
